<article article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4" id="jgh370338" xml:lang="en"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JGH Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JGH Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3550</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jghopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JGH3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JGH Open: An Open Access Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2397-9070</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12813275</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12813275.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12813275</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12813275</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41561618</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jgh3.70338</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JGH370338</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">5305892</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Anti‐Tubercular Drug‐Induced Liver Injury: Current Understanding and Emerging Directions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="jgh370338-cr-0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names initials="S">Shubham</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="jgh370338-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="jgh370338-cr-0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Narang</surname><given-names initials="H">Himanshu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="jgh370338-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="jgh370338-cr-0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kedia</surname><given-names initials="S">Saurabh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="jgh370338-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="jgh370338-cr-0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names initials="V">Vineet</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5474-9709</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="jgh370338-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>vineet.aiims@gmail.com</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="jgh370338-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Gastroenterology and Human Nutrition</named-content>
<institution>All India Institute of Medical Sciences</institution>
<city>New Delhi</city>
<country country="IN">India</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence:</bold>
<break/>
Vineet Ahuja (<email>vineet.aiims@gmail.com</email>)<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue seq="140">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503364</issue-id><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jgh3.v10.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e70338</elocation-id><history><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>18</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-21 09:25:13.620"><day>21</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">© 2026 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">JGH Open</italic> published by Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology Foundation and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref content-type="ccbylicense" specific-use="textmining" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="JGH3-10-e70338.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:JGH3-10-e70338.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Most common adverse effect causing cessation of anti‐tubercular treatment (ATT) is drug‐induced liver injury (DILI) which is unpredictable due to its idiosyncratic nature. ATT is the most common cause of DILI and drug‐induced acute liver failure (ALF) in South East Asia. Spectrum of ATT‐DILI ranges from asymptomatic raised transaminases to acute hepatitis to acute liver failure (ALF). ALF due to ATT has a more aggressive course with up to 70% mortality. Both modifiable and non‐modifiable risk factors are involved. Increasing age, female gender, genetic predisposition, poor nutrition, underlying liver disease, and concomitant viral infections make one prone to ATT‐DILI. Thus, pretreatment evaluation is very important. Diagnosis of ATT‐DILI is challenging due to lack of specific diagnostic tests; rather, it is a diagnosis of exclusion. Mild transient asymptomatic raised transaminases is due to hepatic adaptation and does not require any modification or cessation of ATT. Early detection of clinically significant DILI by frequent monitoring is associated with better prognosis and low mortality. Prompt withdrawal of all the potential hepatotoxic drugs is the key step in the management. Since the benefit of first‐line ATT outweighs the monitored risk, reintroduction is always considered after normalization of raised transaminases. Ideal regimen is sequential reintroduction with incremental dosage of least hepatotoxic drug first, but evidence for this is lacking. Since hepatotoxicity rate is similar across different regimens, reintroduction is individualized based on perceived clinical risk. Future research is needed to identify specific biomarker panel for diagnosing ATT‐DILI.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="jgh370338-kwd-0001">anti‐tubercular treatment</kwd><kwd id="jgh370338-kwd-0002">DILI</kwd><kwd id="jgh370338-kwd-0003">hepatotoxicity</kwd><kwd id="jgh370338-kwd-0004">tuberculosis</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="22"/><word-count count="11700"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January 2026</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.6.8 mode:remove_FC converted:19.01.2026</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-1001" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Prasad</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Narang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Kedia</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Ahuja</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Anti‐Tubercular Drug‐Induced Liver Injury: Current Understanding and Emerging Directions</article-title>,” <source>JGH Open</source>
<volume>10</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2026</year>): <elocation-id>e70338</elocation-id>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jgh3.70338</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
</p></notes></front><body id="jgh370338-body-0001"><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Drug‐induced liver injury (DILI) is a major clinical problem in tuberculosis (TB) management. In retrospective analysis of 519 TB patients, hepatotoxicity was the commonest severe adverse effect of anti‐tubercular therapy (ATT), necessitating drug withdrawal in 11% of patients followed by exanthema (6%) and arthralgia (2%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0001">1</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgh370338-fig-0001">1</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" id="jgh370338-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Importance of ATT‐DILI. Superscripts signify references as in text. DILI, drug‐induced liver injury.</p></caption><graphic id="jats-graphic-1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="JGH3-10-e70338-g002.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><p>The spectrum of DILI ranges from acute hepatitis to acute liver failure (ALF) or acute on chronic liver failure (ACLF), ultimately leading to poor adherence to therapy, significant morbidity and mortality. The diagnosis of DILI is challenging due to the lack of specific diagnostic tests; rather, it is a diagnosis of exclusion by excluding infective and other potential noninfective causes with certainty.</p><p>Traditionally, DILI is classified as intrinsic (or direct) and idiosyncratic. Intrinsic DILI is due to drugs that are inherently toxic to the liver. This type of DILI is typically dose‐related, predictable, and onset is within hours to days (short time span). Injurious free radicals cause hepatocyte necrosis in zones farthest from the hepatic arterioles, where metabolism is greatest and antioxidant detoxifying capacity is the least [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0002">2</xref>].</p><p>Idiosyncratic DILI, on the other hand, is due to drugs that are not inherently toxic to the liver. This type of DILI is dose‐independent, unpredictable and has variable latency to onset of days to weeks to months. Hepatocyte necrosis is often distributed throughout hepatic lobules rather than being zonal, as is often seen with predictable DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0003">3</xref>].</p><p>ATT‐related DILI (ATT‐DILI) is of idiosyncratic type and is the most common cause of idiosyncratic DILI worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0004">4</xref>]. Being a TB endemic zone, in many Asian countries, ATT is the most common cause of DILI and drug‐induced ALF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0005">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0006">6</xref>]. ATT is the second most common drug causing ACLF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0007">7</xref>].</p><p>The incidence of ATT‐DILI is variable due to different definitions used for DILI across different time frames. The spectrum of ATT‐DILI ranges from hepatitis in 2.3% to 28% patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0008">8</xref>], to acute liver failure (ALF) in 25% with overall mortality and ALF mortality rate of 22.7% and 69.6%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0006">6</xref>]. ALF due to ATT has a more aggressive course and constituted 5.7% of all ALF at a tertiary center with more than 60% mortality rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0009">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0010">10</xref>].</p><p>It is, therefore, important to understand which ATT drugs cause hepatotoxicity and their metabolism leading to DILI in association with both modifiable and non‐modifiable predisposing factors, so that appropriate steps can be taken for prevention, early detection, and management of ATT‐DILI. Among first‐line ATT drugs, pyrazinamide is the most hepatotoxic, followed by isoniazid and rifampicin.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title>Anti‐Tubercular Drugs</title><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Isoniazid</title><p>Isoniazid (INH) is cleared predominantly by the liver. Acetylation, oxidation, and hydrolysis are the three types of chemical reactions in the isoniazid metabolism pathway that are of clinical interest. Acetylation and oxidation are enzyme‐mediated, and hydrolysis is a non‐enzyme‐mediated reaction. Two key enzymes in the metabolic pathway are microsomal enzyme cytochrome P4502E1 (CYP2E1) and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐acetyltransferase 2 (NAT2), and they determine the risk of hepatotoxicity. NAT2 is responsible for metabolism through acetylation of isoniazid finally to diacetyl hydrazine, which is non‐hepatotoxic. Cytochrome P4502E1 (by oxidation) and hydrolysis lead to the formation of hepatotoxic metabolites like acetyl‐diazine and other reactive acetyl onium ions and acetyl radicals, which covalently bind to cellular macromolecules and cause hepatocyte necrosis.</p><p>Slow acetylation, as seen in certain NAT2 genotype individuals, is associated with accumulation of hepatotoxic intermediates and has four‐fold increased risk of isoniazid induced DILI as compared to controls with an odds ratio of 4.6. Individuals with CYP2E1 c1/c1 genotype were 2.5 times more likely to develop ATT‐DILI when compared with the other genotypes. Slow‐acetylator status (NAT2 gene polymorphism) and the CYP2E1 C/D or C/C genotype together showed a higher frequency in DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0011">11</xref>]. Direct hydrolysis (minor pathway) of INH without acetylation leads to formation of hydrazine which is hepatotoxic. In slow acetylators and with concomitant rifampicin use, this minor hydrolysis pathway is increased 10‐fold, leading to DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0012">12</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgh370338-fig-0002">2</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" id="jgh370338-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Pathway of hepatotoxicity by anti‐tubercular drugs. CYP2E1, cytochrome P4502E1; GST, glutathione S‐transferases; MPT, mitochondrial permeability transition; NAT2, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐acetyltransferase 2; ROS, reactive oxygen species. Light orange‐colored boxes signify hepatotoxic metabolites. Light green‐colored boxes signify nontoxic metabolites. Light blue‐colored boxes signify hepatotoxic anti‐tubercular drugs. “+” signifies potentiation. “–” signifies inhibition.</p></caption><graphic id="jats-graphic-3" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="JGH3-10-e70338-g005.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><p>Glutathione is an intracellular free radical scavenger and plays a protective role by sulfhydryl conjugation of the toxic reactive metabolites thereby facilitating their excretion from the body and decreasing hepatotoxicity. Deficiency in GST activity, because of homozygous null mutations at GSTM1 and GSTT1 loci, modulates susceptibility to drug‐ and xenobiotic‐induced hepatotoxicity. ATT‐DILI was 2.6 times more likely in those with GSTT1 null mutations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0013">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0004"><label>2.2</label><title>Rifampicin</title><p>Rifampicin is metabolized in the liver by deacetylation and hydrolysis to nontoxic metabolites which are almost equally excreted in bile and urine. Rifampicin is associated with a hepatocellular pattern of idiosyncratic DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0014">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0015">15</xref>] mostly by potentiating the hepatotoxicity of other ATT drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0016">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0017">17</xref>] which is by virtue of its potent enzyme‐inducing property, particularly the cytochrome P450 (CYP3A4) system via the hepatocyte xenosensor, that is, pregnane X receptor (PXR) in the cell nucleus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0018">18</xref>]. This leads to increased metabolism of isoniazid to toxic intermediate metabolites. Rifampicin also induces isoniazid hydrolysis minor pathway metabolism by 10‐fold, particularly in slow acetylators, leading to DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0012">12</xref>].</p><p>Rifampicin excretion in bile occurs by transporter ABCB1. Dose‐dependent interference by saturation of the transporter protein is possible, leading to mild unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia without hepatotoxicity. However, any genetic variation in the gene coding this protein can result in increased accumulation of active metabolite backstream with enzyme‐inducing property and thus resultant TB‐DILI, as shown in a study where patients homozygous for ABCB1 3435TT genotype had a three‐fold increased risk of DILI with ATT and anti‐retroviral treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0019">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0020">20</xref>]. Rifampicin can also lead to mild isolated conjugated hyperbilirubinemia by inhibiting bile salt exporter pump (BSEP) and thus causing decreased conjugated bilirubin excretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0021">21</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0005"><label>2.3</label><title>Pyrazinamide</title><p>Pyrazinamide is a nicotinic acid derivative which is de‐amidated to pyrazinoic acid, which is further oxidized to 5‐hydroxy pyrazinoic acid (5‐OH‐PA) by xanthine oxidase and is finally excreted in urine. Xanthine oxidase also directly acts on pyrazinamide to form 5‐hydroxy pyrazinamide which is considered the main toxic metabolite responsible for hepatotoxicity; this is further de‐amidated to 5‐OH‐PA. Xanthine oxidase inhibitors such as allopurinol increase half‐life of pyrazinamide, which is also seen in chronic liver disease. These patients are more prone to dose‐dependent adverse effects with increased risk of idiosyncratic reactions. Half‐life of pyrazinamide is longer than isoniazid and rifampicin. Pyrazinamide can cause both idiosyncratic and dose‐dependent adverse reactions; the latter is less known to occur with the current regimen dosage. Pyrazinamide can also lead to granulomatous hepatitis and hypersensitivity reactions with eosinophilia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0022">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0006"><label>2.4</label><title>Ethambutol</title><p>Ethambutol interferes with the biosynthesis of arabinogalactan in the cell wall and has synergistic effects with INH. This synergistic effect is through binding of ethambutol to a transcription factor encoded by the <italic toggle="yes">Rv0273c</italic> gene which leads to transcriptional repression of the inhA gene that encodes proteins necessary for cell wall integrity. This leads to enhanced INH sensitivity of the inhA gene and increased mycobactericidal effect of INH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0023">23</xref>].</p><p>Being a bacteriostatic drug, it is always used in combination with other ATT drugs even for latent TB prophylaxis. Due to this, the amount of raised transaminases attributable to ethambutol alone is difficult to elicit. However, the addition of ethambutol to isoniazid, rifampin, or pyrazinamide does not appear to increase transaminases and hepatotoxicity. There has been one case report of ethambutol‐induced cholestatic pattern of liver injury which reoccurred after rechallenge, but the data provided were insufficient and circumstances unclear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0024">24</xref>]. In conclusion, due to lack of high‐quality data, ethambutol is not considered a hepatotoxic drug.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0007"><label>2.5</label><title>Fluoroquinolones</title><p>Among commonly used fluoroquinolones, levofloxacin is excreted unchanged in urine and ciprofloxacin is metabolized in the liver. When hepatotoxic first‐line anti‐tubercular drugs are stopped, fluoroquinolones are added, which are per se second line ATT drugs in the context of MDR TB, and it has been observed that such addition of quinolones did not cause increased hepatitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0025">25</xref>]. Furthermore, use of ofloxacin in CLD is well tolerated and is effective. Adverse drug reactions are related to hypersensitivity to the drug which may result in hepatitis, eosinophilia, and febrile illness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0026">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0008"><label>2.6</label><title>Linezolid</title><p>Linezolid is a potent second line ATT. With increasing experience, it is now being used in modified ATT regimens and is considered non‐hepatotoxic. Being a lipophilic drug, it is widely distributed and acts by inhibiting bacterial protein synthesis by preventing the fusion of ribosomal subunits. It is metabolized in the liver by oxidation of the morpholine ring to inactive compounds, without involvement of the cytochrome P450 system. Urinary excretion is a major elimination route. Linezolid has been associated with mild and transient elevations in serum aminotransferase and alkaline phosphatase levels in 1%–10% of patients, the mechanism of which is not known and may relate more to the underlying condition rather than injury from the drug per se [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0027">27</xref>]. This is important in patients with chronic liver disease and in lactic acidosis. The most common reasons for linezolid discontinuation in patients with tuberculosis are non‐hepatic adverse effects like myelosuppression, neurotoxicity, hyperlactatemia, and diarrhea, all of which are probably due to inhibition of human mitochondrial ribosomal function. Linezolid should not be given to patients on serotonergic agents. It is common practice to prescribe linezolid with vitamin B6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0028">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0009"><label>2.7</label><title>
<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">DILI</styled-content> With Other Anti‐<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">TB</styled-content> Agents</title><p>Besides being an antibiotic with no hepatotoxic potential, cycloserine is also a GABA transaminase inhibitor and therefore has a risk of precipitation of alcohol withdrawal seizures in chronic alcoholics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0029">29</xref>]. Ethionamide and prothionamide have a 2% risk and PAS has a 0.3% risk of hepatotoxicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0030">30</xref>] which are minimal. Bedaquiline causes mild to moderate asymptomatic LFT derangement in 8%–12% of patients which is mostly self‐limiting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0031">31</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0010"><label>3</label><title>Pathophysiology</title><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0011"><label>3.1</label><title>Role of Metabolite Accumulation</title><p>Most ATT drugs are lipid soluble. Hepatic metabolism of a liposoluble drug requires a series of biotransformation to a more water‐soluble compound to facilitate elimination from the body. This process of metabolism is divided into three phases. Phase 1 involves functionalization reactions like oxidation or demethylation which are usually performed by CYP450 enzymes. This results in partially water‐soluble and toxic intermediates. Phase 2 involves conjugation reactions like glucuronidation or sulfation which are usually performed via the glutathione detoxification pathway. This results in a more water‐soluble and nontoxic metabolite. Phase 3 refers to transporter‐mediated elimination of metabolites from the body.</p><p>The expression of enzymes and transporters involved in all the above phases of metabolism is regulated by transcription factors like pregnane X receptor and is influenced by the genetic and environmental factors which determine the rate of formation and accumulation of reactive metabolites. Phase 1 reaction leads to increased reactive metabolites. Dysfunctional Phase 2 and Phase 3 reactions lead to failure of detoxification and excretion of these reactive metabolites, respectively. This ultimately leads to cell death through lipid peroxidation caused by excessive reactive oxygen species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0032">32</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0012"><label>3.2</label><title>Role of Cellular Environment</title><p>Hepatocyte can modulate its tolerance and adaptability to oxidative stress. Heterodimers of transcription factor nuclear factor erythroid 2‐related factor‐2 (Nrf2) and small Maf basic leucine zipper (bZIP) proteins upregulate expression of antioxidant pathway and are cyto‐protective, whereas this antioxidant pathway is downregulated by heterodimer complex of bric‐a‐brac (BTB) domain, cap'n'collar (CNC) type of basic region homology 1 (Bach1), and small Maf proteins. Increased downregulation and decreased upregulation of antioxidant pathway may be responsible for perpetuation of ATT‐DILI pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0033">33</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0013"><label>3.3</label><title>Role of Mitochondrial Metabolism</title><p>Mitochondria play an important role in DILI. The inner mitochondrial membrane is the site of oxidative phosphorylation by respiratory chain complex which is inhibited by the reactive drug metabolites leading to ATP depletion and ultimately leading to increased generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS), increased oxidative stress and mitochondria‐mediated cell death. The mitochondrial matrix is the site of manganese superoxide dismutase (MnSOD) which scavenges superoxide anion. These ROS are generated constantly as a byproduct of electron transport in respiratory chain complex and their accumulation due to dysfunctional MnSOD leads to alteration in the permeability of inner mitochondrial membrane. This mitochondrial permeability transition may lead to necrosis due to decreased ATP generation, or may lead to apoptosis through release of pro‐apoptotic factors. A relationship between susceptibility to ATT‐DILI and genetic polymorphisms of this enzyme was shown by a study in which patients with ATT‐induced DILI having mutant C allele (T/C or C/C genotype) of MnSOD had a 2.5‐fold higher risk of hepatotoxicity when compared with those with MnSOD TT genotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0034">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0014"><label>3.4</label><title>Role of Adduct Mediated Immune Response</title><p>Under physiological conditions, it is normal for a drug to undergo metabolism to produce metabolites which may be capable of binding to cellular proteins forming adducts/neo‐antigens. These adducts are cleared subsequently without mounting an immune response in the majority of individuals but not in all. Individuals with susceptible specific class 2 HLA alleles can activate an adaptive immune response against adducts. There can be three types of outcomes following immune activation. First, the majority will have no hepatic injury due to strong tolerance. Second, a minority will have mild hepatic injury which is followed by adaptation with drug continuation. Third, very few susceptible patients will develop overt DILI due to inadvertent and aberrant T‐cell activation mediated end‐organ damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0035">35</xref>].</p><p>The risk of hepatotoxicity from anti‐tuberculosis drugs was more in individuals having of HLA‐DQB1*0201 allele (OR 1.9) and in individuals lacking HLA‐DQA1*0102 allele (OR 4.0). These MHC class 2 alleles were independent risk factors for ATT‐induced DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0036">36</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0015"><label>3.5</label><title>Role of Cytokines/Chemokines</title><p>A co‐stimulatory molecule is required for effective interaction of antigen presenting cells and T cell receptors for mounting an adaptive immune response. This co‐stimulatory molecule can be cytokines released by damage associated molecular patterns (DAMPs) due to oxidative stress or can be released by chronically infected hepatic cells like in chronic viral hepatitis. Patients with chronic viral infections in the liver are at a risk for ATT‐DILI. This although manifests as sub‐clinical response but indicates vulnerability of an individual for overt DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0037">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0016"><label>3.6</label><title>Role of Histone/Epigenetics</title><p>Histones play an important role in gene regulation. Histone acetylation increases gene transcription through the promotor region and deacetylation decreases transcription. Acetylation of histones is mediated by the histone acetyltransferase enzyme. It has been postulated that the acetylation of drugs having hydralazine derivatives like isoniazid is also mediated by the histone acetyltransferase enzyme and prolonged use of such drugs leads to exhaustion of this enzyme leading to histone deacetylation and decreased transcription of factors involved in hepatic regeneration ultimately supporting DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0038">38</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgh370338-fig-0003">3</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" id="jgh370338-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Pathogenesis of ATT‐DILI. ATP, adenosine triphosphate; BTB, bric‐a‐brac gene domain; CNC, cap'n'collar gene domain; DAMPs, damage associated molecular patterns; MnSOD, manganese superoxide dismutase; Nrf, nuclear factor erythroid 2‐related factor‐2; ROS, reactive oxygen species; sMaf, small Maf proteins.</p></caption><graphic id="jats-graphic-5" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="JGH3-10-e70338-g003.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0017"><label>4</label><title>Risk Factors</title><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0018"><label>4.1</label><title>Non‐Modifiable Risk Factors</title><p>
<list id="jgh370338-list-0001" list-type="bullet"><list-item id="jgh370338-li-0001"><p>Age: Reduced hepatic blood flow and altered metabolism with advancing age increase susceptibility to DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0039">39</xref>]. Multiple studies show higher ATT‐DILI risk above 50–60 years, with severity and mortality also rising in older groups.</p></list-item><list-item id="jgh370338-li-0002"><p>Gender: Women have up to four‐fold greater susceptibility which is attributed to higher CYP3A4 activity. Higher risk has been reported in peripartum period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0040">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0041">41</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item id="jgh370338-li-0003"><p>Genetic predisposition: Asian men have greater susceptibility compared to other ethnic groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0042">42</xref>]. Variations in CYP3A4 and PXR genes, absence of <italic toggle="yes">HLA‐DQA1</italic>0102*, and presence of <italic toggle="yes">HLA‐DQB1</italic>0201* alleles are linked with increased risk.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0019"><label>4.2</label><title>Modifiable Risk Factors</title><p>
<list id="jgh370338-list-0002" list-type="bullet"><list-item id="jgh370338-li-0004"><p>Nutrition: Malnutrition and fasting affect cytochrome P450 enzyme system which is responsible for metabolism of anti‐TB drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0043">43</xref>]. Weight loss of more than 2 kg within 4 weeks of initiating ATT is a significant independent risk factor for DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0044">44</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item id="jgh370338-li-0005"><p>Alcohol: Chronic alcohol use independently increases liver injury risk.</p></list-item><list-item id="jgh370338-li-0006"><p>Viral infections: Coinfection with HBV, HCV, or HIV increases both the frequency and severity of hepatotoxicity. ATT‐DILI is ~3–5 times more common in HBV/HCV‐infected patients and up to 14 times higher in HIV‐HCV coinfection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0045">45</xref>].</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0020"><label>5</label><title>Clinical Features</title><p>ATT‐related DILI has a broad spectrum, from asymptomatic raised transaminases to symptomatic hepatitis and acute liver failure (ALF). Differentiation from viral hepatitis is difficult; therefore, exclusion of other causes is essential. In most cases, hepatotoxicity improves after withholding therapy.</p><p>Raised transaminases occur in 50% of patients on ATT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0046">46</xref>]. About 50% of them develop mild, self‐limited raised transaminases which is termed hepatic adaptation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0046">46</xref>]. In a large UK study, DILI occurred in 6.9% of TB patients; half within 2 weeks and nearly 90% within 8 weeks of ATT initiation. The most frequent symptoms were nausea and vomiting (50%), abdominal pain, and skin manifestations, while jaundice occurred in 12% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0047">47</xref>]. Other series report nausea, vomiting, anorexia, and abdominal pain in up to 90% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0048">48</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgh370338-fig-0004">4</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" id="jgh370338-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Risk factors and clinical spectrum of ATT‐DILI. Superscripts signify references as in text. CYP3A4, cytochrome P4503A4; LFT, liver function test; NAT2, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐acetyltransferase 2.</p></caption><graphic id="jats-graphic-7" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="JGH3-10-e70338-g004.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><p>A recent systematic review and meta‐analysis found ATT‐DILI in 12.6% of patients, and ATT‐ALF in 7% with 70% mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0049">49</xref>]. Mean latency from ATT initiation to ALF was 30 days and independent predictors of mortality were bilirubin ≥ 10.8 mg/dL, PT ≥ 26 s, and Grade III–IV encephalopathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0009">9</xref>].</p><p>ALF due to ATT differs from viral hepatitis related ALF. It usually has subacute onset, disproportionately elevated bilirubin and INR, mixed‐pattern liver injury, and poorer prognosis due to high mortality and TB treatment challenges. By contrast, viral hepatitis ALF presents with abrupt onset, higher transaminase elevations, and generally better recovery.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0021"><label>6</label><title>Diagnosis of ATT‐Induced Hepatitis</title><p>Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) thresholds are less reliable in TB, since granulomatous hepatitis itself may elevate levels. Mild aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) elevation during ATT can also reflect hepatic adaptation. Isolated bilirubin elevation is rare in ATT‐DILI and usually reflects rifampicin induced transient, benign unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia without hepatocellular injury. Significant bilirubin rise almost always occurs with ALT/AST elevation. Thus, distinguishing benign changes from DILI is essential to avoid premature drug withdrawal while ensuring timely recognition of clinically significant hepatotoxicity, which carries high mortality.</p><p>According to the American Thoracic Society (ATS) guidelines and widely accepted expert recommendations, ATT‐induced hepatotoxicity is defined as: (1) AST or ALT ≥ 3 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) with clinical symptoms suggestive of hepatotoxicity (nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, jaundice, or unexplained fatigue) or (2) AST or ALT ≥ 5 times the ULN without symptoms.</p><p>In addition, other causes should be excluded and there should be improvement in AST/ALT after cessation of hepatotoxic ATT.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0022"><label>7</label><title>Management of ATT‐Dili</title><p>The guidelines for ATT‐induced hepatotoxicity come from the American Thoracic Society (ATS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0022">22</xref>] the British Thoracic Society (BTS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0050">50</xref>], the World Health Organization (WHO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0051">51</xref>], the Asian Pacific Association for the Study of the Liver (APASL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0052">52</xref>], and the Revised national tuberculosis control program (RNTCP) in India.</p><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0023"><label>7.1</label><title>Pretreatment Evaluation for <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">TB</styled-content>‐<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">DILI</styled-content>
</title><p>All patients should be screened for conditions that might have predisposition for ATT‐induced hepatotoxicity. This assessment mainly focuses on detecting any baseline hepatitis or presence of chronic liver disease, if any, prior to initiation of ATT. History of high‐risk sexual behavior, intravenous drug abuse, chronic ethanol consumption, prior history of chronic viral hepatitis, jaundice and history of use of concomitant potential hepatotoxic drugs/complementary and alternate medicines (CAM) should always be elicited. Assessment for malnutrition is important. If history is suggestive of the possibility of underlying liver disease, appropriate assessment should be done accordingly. It is recommended to get baseline serological evaluation including LFT and chronic viral infection markers (HIV, hepatitis B and C) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0050">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0053">53</xref>]. Taking into consideration the known risk factors for ATT‐DILI, it is very important to assess risk‐benefit ratio before starting empirical treatment as studies have shown more adverse drug reactions in them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0009">9</xref>].</p><p>If ATT is to be given for latent TB, then it is preferable to start a monotherapy with isoniazid (first preference) or rifampicin (second preference due to drug interactions by virtue of its CYP enzyme‐inducing property). The combination therapy has been shown to be associated with a higher risk of hepatotoxicity. The risk of clinical hepatitis with isoniazid alone, rifampicin alone, and with combination therapy of both is 0.6%, 0%, and 2.73%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0022">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0054">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0055">55</xref>].</p><p>If ATT is to be given in an individual with baseline liver disease, then ATT should consist of fewer hepatotoxic drugs depending upon the severity of liver disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0051">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0055">55</xref>] (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="jgh370338-tbl-0001">1</xref>). Patients with Child Turcotte Pugh (CTP) scores of 7 or less generally tolerate two hepatotoxic drugs, whereas, those with scores between 8 and 10 are able to tolerate only one [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0056">56</xref>]. Based on experts' opinion, oral linezolid can be added as a substitute to injectable aminoglycosides in Child's class A and B liver cirrhosis. There is no adequate dose adjustment data of linezolid for Child's class C liver cirrhosis. Some authors recommend the use of a low dose of linezolid (600 mg/day) for maintaining adequate trough level in patients with Child's class C liver cirrhosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0057">57</xref>]. Therapeutic drug monitoring of linezolid should be done whenever feasible. Myelosuppression (particularly thrombocytopenia) should be monitored particularly in the background of chronic liver disease.</p><table-wrap content-type="TABLE" id="jgh370338-tbl-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Modified ATT regimens in ATT‐DILI and in CLD.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Modified ATT regimens in ATT‐DILI and in CLD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0055">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0056">56</xref>]</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Regimens</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Drugs and duration</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">CTP score</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Liver disease</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Comments in CLD</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1" valign="top">Two hepatotoxic drugs regimen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top">Regimen without isoniazid</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">6–9 months of rifampicin, pyrazinamide, and ethambutol</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&lt; 7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Stable</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Less preferable; rarely used<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="jgh370338-note-0004">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="2" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top">Regimen without pyrazinamide</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">9 months of isoniazid and rifampicin, plus ethambutol</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2" valign="top">&lt; 8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2" valign="top">Stable</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="2" valign="top">Avoid pyrazinamide</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2 months of isoniazid, rifampicin, streptomycin/linezolid<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="jgh370338-note-0002">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref> and ethambutol, followed by 6 months of isoniazid and rifampicin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">One hepatotoxic drug regimen</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2 months of isoniazid (or rifampicin), ethambutol and streptomycin/linezolid<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="jgh370338-note-0002">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>, followed by 10 months of isoniazid and ethambutol</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">8–10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Advanced</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Rifampicin is preferred over isoniazid. Pyrazinamide should not be used</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">No hepatotoxic drug regimen</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">18–24 months treatment with a combination of ethambutol, fluoroquinolone, cycloserine, and capreomycin or aminoglycoside/linezolid<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="jgh370338-note-0003">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&gt; 10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Very advanced</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">If improvement in CTP is persistent, above regimens may be considered on case‐to‐case basis</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot id="jgh370338-ntgp-0001"><fn id="jgh370338-note-0001"><p>Abbreviations: CLD, chronic liver disease; CTP, Child Turcotte Pugh score.</p></fn><fn id="jgh370338-note-0002"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Indicate that oral linezolid can be used instead of streptomycin but has still not been positioned in guidelines.</p></fn><fn id="jgh370338-note-0003"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Indicates that dose of oral linezolid needs to be modified (600 mg/day) and therapeutic drug monitoring should be considered.</p></fn><fn id="jgh370338-note-0004"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>May be used if only isoniazid has proven idiosyncratic DILI and pyrazinamide has proven good tolerance in a particular patient.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0024"><label>7.2</label><title>Monitoring for Early Detection of <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">ATT</styled-content>‐<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">DILI</styled-content>
</title><p>Early detection by frequent monitoring is associated with better prognosis and lower mortality. In situations where baseline LFT is normal, almost all the guidelines do not recommend LFT monitoring unless the patient is symptomatic. However, in routine clinical practice, it is reasonable to monitor LFT every 2–4 weeks during the first 1–2 months, since slow acetylator status cannot be predicted. If baseline LFT is deranged, the frequency of LFT monitoring on ATT should be weekly if baseline ALT is &gt; 2 times ULN and 2–4 weekly if baseline ALT is &lt; 2 times ULN. If underlying liver disease is present, then LFT should be monitored weekly at least for 2 months, followed by clinical monitoring on a case‐to‐case basis.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0025"><label>7.3</label><title>Intervention for <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">ATT</styled-content>‐<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">DILI</styled-content>
</title><p>Prompt withdrawal of all the potential hepatotoxic drugs is the key step in the management of DILI after diagnosis. In the absence of symptoms attributable to hepatotoxicity, hepatotoxic ATT (Isoniazid, rifampicin, and pyrazinamide) should be stopped only if ALT is &gt; 5 times ULN. Mild raised transaminases to less than five times ULN in asymptomatic individuals may represent physiological hepatic adaptation to ATT and is expected to resolve with continuation of therapy. In the presence of symptoms attributable to hepatotoxicity, hepatotoxic ATT should be stopped if ALT is &gt; 3 times ULN. It is important to note that in the absence of a specific biomarker that can differentiate between hepatic adaptation and potential DILI, the cut‐offs for stopping hepatotoxic ATT are based more on practical experiences rather than evidence based.</p><p>Increase in bilirubin with ATT should be taken as a guide to evaluate whether it is related to worsening of hepatic functions due to hepatotoxicity of drugs as suggested by concomitant raised transaminases and deranged INR. Else, isolated hyperbilirubinemia does not require modification of therapy but careful monitoring should be done [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0047">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0050">50</xref>].</p><p>After ATT‐DILI diagnosis, all first‐line ATT except ethambutol should be stopped and other non‐hepatotoxic ATT like levofloxacin with either aminoglycoside (injectable) or linezolid/cycloserine (oral) should be added. Since there are no recent guidelines for choosing non‐hepatotoxic ATT in this scenario, the choice of ATT, besides ethambutol, depends upon the physician's preference and experience. Therapy can also be individualized depending upon the patient's preference of injectable or oral drug. A total of at least three non‐hepatotoxic drug‐based ATT regimens should be given during this time till the likely culprit drug is identified.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0026"><label>7.4</label><title>Restarting <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">ATT</styled-content>
</title><p>Hepatotoxic drugs should be withheld ideally till ALT normalizes or at least till ALT decreases to &lt; 2 times ULN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0054">54</xref>]. Since the first‐line ATT drugs are well known to be highly efficacious, the benefits of reintroduction of these drugs outweigh the closely monitored risk of hepatotoxicity with rechallenge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0058">58</xref>]. Sharma et al. found that re‐exposure to the same ATT drug regimen leads to recurrence of DILI in only 11%–24% of patients which is not affected by the degree of initial injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0059">59</xref>].</p><p>Since more than one first‐line ATT is potentially hepatotoxic, reintroduction can be done in two ways: either sequential or concomitant, with either starting with full dose or incremental dose of individual drugs. A new drug should be reintroduced only if LFT is normal or &lt; 2 times ULN. The first hepatotoxic drug to be reintroduced varies with different guidelines. The ideal regimen should be sequential with incremental dosage starting with least hepatotoxic drug first, but evidence for this is lacking. Since hepatotoxicity rate does not differ significantly between different regimens, reintroduction is often individualized guided by perceived clinical risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0059">59</xref>]. ATS and BTS favor sequential regimen. WHO recommends starting all drugs simultaneously and if a second episode of DILI occurs, then to follow sequential regimen. ATS recommends reintroducing rifampicin full dose first followed by isoniazid full dose after 3–7 days followed by pyrazinamide only if the initial injury was mild. BTS recommends isoniazid incremental dose first followed by rifampicin incremental dose followed by pyrazinamide. APASL recommends a combination of two regimens, that is, reintroducing rifampicin in incremental dose first followed by Isoniazid in incremental dose followed by pyrazinamide only if the initial injury was mild. RNTCP advocates use of any these regimens with rifampicin first; however, sequential full‐dose regimen is mostly practiced with repeat LFT every week to find the culprit drug. If ATT‐induced hepatotoxicity is severe (ALF or coagulopathy), pyrazinamide reintroduction should be avoided if rifampicin and isoniazid are well tolerated.</p><p>A landmark randomized study of 175 patients with ATT‐DILI found no difference in the recurrence rate of hepatotoxicity with three different reintroductory regimens of ATT (arm 1 with concomitant regimen including pyrazinamide, arm 2 with sequential regimen according to ATS, and arm 3 with sequential regimen according to BTS). Another randomized controlled trial of 45 patients with ATT‐DILI found that sequential reintroduction regimen without pyrazinamide had better safety than the concomitant regimen including pyrazinamide. An individualized approach based on risk factor assessment is needed. Malnutrition, HIV positivity, chronic viral hepatitis, low albumin, and chronic alcoholics have a higher risk of hepatotoxicity and may benefit more from sequential regimen with or without pyrazinamide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0059">59</xref>].</p><p>A systematic review and network meta‐analysis of four RCTs comprising over 500 patients found that when compared to concomitant regimen, the ATT‐induced hepatitis was significantly less in sequential and incremental regimen, and there was no difference in the rate of ATT‐induced hepatitis with rifampicin first or isoniazid first regimen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0060">60</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgh370338-fig-0005">5</xref>). Major studies on ATT‐DILI are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="jgh370338-tbl-0002">2</xref>.</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" id="jgh370338-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Pathway for management of ATT‐DILI. CAM, complementary and alternative medicines; CLD, chronic liver disease; f/b, followed by; HAV, hepatitis A; HBsAg, hepatitis B surface antigen; HCV, hepatitis C; HEV, hepatitis E; INR, international normalized ratio; LFT, liver function test; ULN, upper limit of normal; USG, ultrasound.</p></caption><graphic id="jats-graphic-9" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="JGH3-10-e70338-g001.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><table-wrap content-type="TABLE" id="jgh370338-tbl-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Summary of major studies on anti‐tuberculosis drug related hepatotoxicity.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Author/year</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Country</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Study design</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Study population and setting</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Patients on ATT</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">ATT‐DILI</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Diagnostic criteria</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Time to onset of DILI</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Outcome measures</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Key findings</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="bottom">Practical implications</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Tahaoğlu et al. 2001 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0061">61</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Turkey</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">RCT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI patients requiring reintroduction of ATT; single‐center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">45</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">45</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">LFT normalization after ATT withdrawal + ≥ 1: AST/ALT ≥ 5× ULN; or Bil. &gt; 1.5 mg/dL; or any rise in AST/ALT with hepatitis symptoms; or exclude viral hepatitis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Recurrence rate of ATT‐DILI with incremental versus concomitant reintroduction regimen</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incremental regimen without pyrazinamide better than concomitant full‐dose regimen with pyrazinamide (DILI = 0% vs. 24%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Early evidence comparing reintroduction regimens</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Sharma et al. 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0059">59</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">RCT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI patients needing rechallenge at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">175</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">175</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">LFT normalization after ATT withdrawal + ≥ 1: AST/ALT ≥ 5× ULN; or Bil. &gt; 1.5 mg/dl; or any rise in AST/ALT with hepatitis symptoms; or exclude viral hepatitis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>Median: 23 days (IQR: 4–44 days)</p>
<p>Normalization time</p>
<p>Median: 18 days (IQR: 14–28 days)</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DILI with 3 reintroduction regimens: full‐dose simultaneous versus ATS versus BTS</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>No difference in DILI</p>
<p>Reintroduction to DILI ~18 days (range: 5–35 days)</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">All major rechallenge protocols considered safe</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Azuma et al. 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0062">62</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Japan</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">RCT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Newly diagnosed TB stratified by NAT2 acetylator genotype; Multicenter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">172</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">14</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT &gt; 2× ULN; or ALP &gt; 2× ULN; or mixed pattern + causality (RUCAM)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Isoniazid DILI and treatment failure in standard versus pharmacogenetic based treatment</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>Within 8 weeks‐DILI in 78% patients on standard treatment</p>
<p>NAT2‐guided dosing reduced isoniazid DILI and failures</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Proof of pharmacogenetic dosing utility</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Zuberi et al. 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0063">63</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Pakistan</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">RCT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI patients requiring reintroduction of ATT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">325</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">325</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Exclusion of other causes + ≥ 1: ALT &gt; 5× ULN on one occasion; or ALT &gt; 3× ULN on three consecutive occasions; or Bil. &gt; 1.5 mg/dL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Recurrence rate of ATT‐DILI with incremental versus sequential full‐dose reintroduction regimen</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">No significant difference between two reintroduction strategy</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Both the regimens are efficacious</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Meena et al. 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0064">64</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">RCT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI patients requiring reintroduction of ATT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">32</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">32</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 5× ULN, or ALT ≥ 3× ULN with bilirubin &gt; 2× ULN, or ALP ≥ 2× ULN (with increased GGT)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Recurrence rate of ATT‐DILI with sequential isoniazid first versus sequential rifampicin first versus concomitant regimen (isoniazid and rifampicin)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">No significant difference between three reintroduction strategy</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">All reintroduction strategy with isoniazid and rifampicin have similar efficacy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Tweed et al. 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0065">65</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Multi‐country</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">RCT dataset (post hoc)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Pulmonary TB patients enrolled in trial</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1928</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">58</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 5× ULN or ALT ≥ 3× ULN with Bil. &gt; 2× ULN + causality (RUCAM)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median: 4 weeks (IQR: 2–8 weeks)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Risk factors, onset of DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>Increased risk‐Isoniazid, older age, Asian ethnicity, HIV +ve.</p>
<p>3/4th DILI in 2 months</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Frequent LFT monitoring in intensive phase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Moosa et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0066">66</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">South Africa</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">RCT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">HIV‐prevalent hospitalized ATT‐DILI; multicenter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">102</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">102</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATS criteria: AL ≥ 5× ULN (asymptomatic) or ALT ≥ 3× ULN (with symptoms) + exclusion of other causes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median: 3 weeks (IQR: 10–40 days)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">N‐acetylcysteine (NAC) versus placebo; ALT, hospital stay, mortality</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">NAC shortened length of stay; no difference in biochemical recovery and mortality</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">NAC may help as inpatient adjunctive therapy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Cai et al. 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0067">67</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">China</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Meta‐analysis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT tolerant (controls) and intolerant (DILI) patients</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">7131</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2225</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Heterogenous</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Genetic risk</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Slow NAT2, GSTM1 null, CYP2E1*1A genotype‐ increased risk of DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Predicting clinical response with genetic risk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Wang et al. 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0068">68</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">China</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Meta‐analysis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT tolerant (controls) and intolerant (DILI) patients</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1920</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">474</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Heterogenous</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Genetic risk</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">NAT2 slow acetylators‐ increased risk of DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Predicting clinical response with genetic risk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Soni et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0060">60</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Systematic review and network meta‐analysis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI patients requiring reintroduction of ATT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">577</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">577</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Heterogenous</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Recurrence rate of ATT‐DILI with different reintroduction regimen</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>Probability of recurrence of DILI: Incremental &gt; Sequential &gt; Concomitant regimen; but difference not significant.</p>
<p>Rifampicin first versus Isoniazid first, similar DILI risk after reintroduction</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">All reintroduction strategy similar. Choice may be individualized with perceived risk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Wang et al. 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0069">69</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">China</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Systematic review and meta‐analysis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">116 147</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">~12 776</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Heterogenous</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incidence, trend, predictors</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Global pooled ATT‐DILI incidence ~11%; upward trend over decades</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Benchmark incidence with temporal trends</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Akkahadsee et al. 2023 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0070">70</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Thailand</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Network meta‐analysis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patients on ATT + hepatoprotective agents/placebo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3423</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Heterogenous</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prevention of DILI (intervention versus placebo)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">NAC, turmeric plus <italic toggle="yes">Tinospora cordifolia</italic> significantly decreases DILI incidence</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Evidence certainty is limited</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Kumar et al. 2025 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0049">49</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Systematic review and meta‐analysis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">TB patients</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">12 041</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">~1518</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT/AST ≥ 5× ULN (asymptomatic) or ALT/AST ≥ 3× ULN (with symptoms) + exclusion of other causes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median: 10–65 days</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incidence, risk factors</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DILI: 12.6%; ALF ~7%; pooled mortality‐1.72%; ALF mortality ~70%; Increased risk: daily &gt; intermittent regimen, HBV, HCV, alcohol, CLD, female, old age, low BMI, low albumin, slow acetylator</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Intensify monitoring in India</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Singh et al. 1996 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0071">71</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI patients at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">72</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">72</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">LFT normalization after ATT withdrawal + ≥ 1: AST/ALT ≥ 5× ULN; or Bil. &gt; 1.5 mg/dL; or any rise in AST/ALT with hepatitis symptoms; or exclude viral hepatitis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean ± SD: 7 ± 5 weeks versus 5 ± 4 weeks (mortality vs. survival group)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Clinical and ATT reintroduction outcome</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>Jaundice‐61%, Prodomal‐39%</p>
<p>Hepatic failure ~17%</p>
<p>Mortality‐12.5%</p>
<p>Reintroduction safe after recovery (41/44)</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Early evidence supporting reintroduction of ATT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Agal et al. 2005 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0072">72</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT tolerant and intolerant patients at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">224</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">45</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Exclusion of viral, alcohol, drug causes + ≥ 1: symptoms of hepatitis; or AST/ALT &gt; 5× ULN, or &gt; 2× ULN with symptoms; or Bil. &gt; 2× ULN</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean ± SD: 12.6 ± 3.6 days</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Monitoring and reintroduction strategy</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mortality ~17%. Sequential full‐dose reintroduction with weekly LFT successful strategy (38/39)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Guidance on reintroduction strategy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Kumar et al. 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0009">9</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALF patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1223) at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">85</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">85</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Jaundice + encephalopathy ≤ 4 weeks</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>ATT to encephalopathy</p>
<p>Median (range): 4 weeks (1–50 weeks)</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incidence, mortality, predictors</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐ALF‐5.7%; ATT‐ALF mortality ~67%; bilirubin (&gt; 10.8), INR (PT &gt; 26), encephalopathy independently predicted mortality</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐ALF an important entity; early referral to transplant setting needed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Shang et al. 2011 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0073">73</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">China</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT; multicenter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4304</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">106</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">AST/ALT ≥ 3× ULN; or Bil. &gt; 2× ULN + exclusion of other causes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median: 52 days (IQR: 30–63 days)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Clinical and treatment outcomes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Nausea (41%), vomiting (40%), anorexia (25%); asymptomatic DILI‐33%; mortality‐1.8%; 70% changed treatment; 50% transient cessation of ATT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Up to 1/3rd with DILI can be asymptomatic highlighting importance of monitoring</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Singanayagam et al. 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0074">74</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UK</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">288</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">21</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATS criteria: ALT ≥ 5× ULN (asymptomatic) or ALT ≥ 3× ULN (with symptoms) + exclusion of other causes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">57% DILI ≤ 2 weeks; 43% DILI &gt; 2 weeks</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Early versus late DILI in two monitoring approaches</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">LFT every two weekly promptly identifies early DILI better than ATS risk‐factor based monitoring</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Guides monitoring strategy for patients on ATT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Gupta et al. 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0075">75</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT; multicenter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">215</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">50</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 2× ULN, or a combined increase in AST and bilirubin levels with either ≥ 2× ULN</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Gene polymorphism in ATT‐DILI versus No DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Slow‐acetylator NAT2 polymorphism‐ increased susceptibility to isoniazid DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Genetic risk profiling may lead to precision medicine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Rana et al. 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0076">76</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">300</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">55</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">AST/ALT ≥ 5× ULN, or AST/ALT ≥ 2× ULN + increased bilirubin</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Gene polymorphisms in ATT‐DILI versus No DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Slow‐acetylator genotypes (NAT2 5/7, 6/7) and GSTM1 allele of GST enzyme‐ increased risk of DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Genetic risk profiling may lead to precision medicine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Singla et al. 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0077">77</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">408</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">17</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">AST/ALT ≥ 2× ULN</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Gene polymorphism in ATT‐DILI versus No DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Increased risk: slow‐acetylator NAT2 genotypes, GSTM1 and GSTT1 double null genotype, heterozygote genotype “c1c2” of CYP2E1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Genetic risk profiling may lead to precision medicine</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Satyaraddi et al. 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0078">78</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">110</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">15</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT/AST ≥ 5× ULN (asymptomatic) or ALT/AST ≥ 3× ULN (with symptoms) or ALT/AST ≥ 3× ULN with Bil. &gt; 2× ULN + exclusion of other causes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median (range): 22 days (10–35 days)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Serial plasma drug levels of isoniazid, rifampicin and pyrazinamide</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Only rifampicin drug levels correlated with subsequent development of DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">First mechanistic study of its kind. Drug levels of isoniazid and pyrazinamide cannot predict DILI</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Gaude et al. 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0079">79</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">3900</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">150</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">LFT normalization after ATT withdrawal + ≥ 1: AST/ALT ≥ 5× ULN; or Bil. &gt; 1.5 mg/dL; or any rise in AST/ALT with hepatitis symptoms; or exclude viral hepatitis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean 20 days; lasted for 14 days</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incidence, risk factors</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DILI‐3.8%; risk factors‐advanced age, hypoalbuminemia, regular alcohol intake and radiologically advanced nature of the disease</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Regional variation in ATT‐DILI across different studies</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Bright‐Thomas et al. 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0080">80</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UK.</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT; multicenter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">2070</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">63</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 5× ULN, or rising bilirubin</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DILI incidence and trend over 30 years</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DILI‐3%; incidence increased with age; presumed culprit: Pyrazinamide‐57%, Rifampicin‐32%, Isoniazid‐11%, Ethambutol‐0%. No increasing trend in incidence over time</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incidence and its trend have geographical variations</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Latief et al. 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0081">81</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">200</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">16</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATS criteria: ALT ≥ 5× ULN (asymptomatic) or ALT ≥ 3× ULN (with symptoms) + exclusion of other causes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">63% DILI ≤ 2 weeks</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Risk factors, monitoring outcomes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>Increased risk‐Female, extra‐pulmonary TB.</p>
<p>Early LFT monitoring at second, fourth, and eighth week leads to early DILI detection, irrespective of risk factors</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">LFT based early monitoring in all is better than risk‐factor based approach</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Bessone et al. 2019 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0082">82</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Latin America</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective registry cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">All cause idiosyncratic DILI (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 468)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">20</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 5× ULN, or ALT ≥ 3× ULN with bilirubin &gt; 2× ULN, or ALP ≥ 2× ULN (with increased GGT) + causality (RUCAM)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Etiology</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI (4.3%) less frequent</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Regional variation in ATT‐DILI</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Devarbhavi et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0083">83</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective registry cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">All cause DILI patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1228); multicenter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">~565</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 5× ULN, or ALP ≥ 2× ULN, or ALT ≥ 3× ULN with Bil. &gt; 2× ULN + causality (RUCAM)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Etiology and overall clinical outcomes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">46% ATT‐DILI; high hospitalization rate</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Significant burden of ATT‐DILI in India</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Jiang et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0084">84</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">China</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patients on ATT (derivation + validation cohorts)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">4652</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">255</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 5× ULN, or ALP ≥ 2× ULN, or ALT ≥ 3× ULN with Bil. &gt; 2× ULN</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median: ~42 days</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incidence, clinical outcomes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>5.5% DILI, 0.8% mortality</p>
<p>Increased risk‐older age, hepatitis B, high baseline ALT</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Monitor high‐risk groups</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Raj Mani et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0085">85</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patients on ATT</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">393</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">38</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 5× ULN (asymptomatic) or ALT ≥ 3× ULN (with symptoms) or Bil. &gt; 1.5 mg/dL rise + exclusion of other causes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incidence, risks, predictor score for ATT‐DILI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DILI‐ 9.7%, mortality ~5%, clinical risk score with HIV, CLD, daily treatment regimen, disseminated disease, undernutrition, female gender (sensitivity‐74%, specificity‐ 67%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">The scoring system needs validation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Moosa et al. 2023 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0086">86</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">South Africa</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective nested cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI patients receiving NAC; multicenter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">45</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">45</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATS criteria: ALT ≥ 5× ULN (asymptomatic) or ALT ≥ 3× ULN (with symptoms) + exclusion of other causes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median: 18 days (IQR: 10–31 days)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Biomarker (miR‐122)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">miR‐122 correlated with ALT; unaffected by NAC</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Promising biomarker for ATT‐DILI</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Lim et al. 2023 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0087">87</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Korea</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patients on ATT; multicenter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">684</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">52</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT/AST ≥ 200 U/L or ≥ 120 U/L with symptoms; or Bil. ≥ 3 mg/dL or ≥ 1.5 mg/dL with symptoms</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median (range): 8 weeks (4–18 weeks)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Risk (presence or absence of metabolic disorder)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DILI‐7.6%. Metabolic comorbidities increase risk</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Closer monitoring in metabolic syndrome</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Petros et al. 2025 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0088">88</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Ethiopia</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patients on ATT; multicenter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">219</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">35</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 5× ULN, or ALT ≥ 3× ULN with Bil. &gt; 2× ULN, or ALP &gt; 2× ULN</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">75% DILI ≤ 4 weeks</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incidence, risk factors</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>ATT‐DILI incidence ~16%</p>
<p>Female, old age, low BMI, HIV increased risk</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Similar risk factors across nations</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Kumar et al. 2025 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0046">46</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Prospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Newly diagnosed abdominal TB patients; single‐center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">140</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">20</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT ≥ 5× ULN, or ALT ≥ 3× ULN with bilirubin &gt; 2× ULN, or ALP ≥ 2× ULN (with increased GGT) + RUCAM</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>Median: 12 days (IQR: 7–22.7)</p>
<p>90% DILI ≤ 8 weeks</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Clinical outcome, reintroduction success</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>LFT abnormalities‐50.7%; Median time (ATT to deranged LFT): 12 days (IQR: 7–22.7). Half recovered spontaneously (hepatic adaptation); median (deranged LFT to hepatic adaptation): 21 days (IQR: 14–42)</p>
<p>DILI‐27%; low albumin/Vit D predicted progression to DILI; ~66% rechallenge success</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Pattern of LFT changes under ATT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Sharma et al. 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0036">36</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Retrospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT tolerant and intolerant patients at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">346</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">56</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">LFT normalization after ATT withdrawal + ≥ 1: AST/ALT ≥ 5× ULN; or Bil. &gt; 1.5 mg/dL; or any rise in AST/ALT with hepatitis symptoms; or exclude viral hepatitis</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median (range): 4 weeks (1–72 days)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Clinical and genetic risk factors</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Increased risk‐alcohol, older age, low serum albumin, underlying liver disease, HLA‐DQA10102 absence, HLA‐DQB10201 presence</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Genetic risk profiling</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Devarbhavi et al. 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0006">6</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">India</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Retrospective</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI patients in tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">269</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">269</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Exclusion of other causes + ≥ 1: Bil. ≥ 2 mg/dL, or AST/ALT &gt; 3× ULN, or ALP &gt; 2× ULN + causality (RUCAM). ALF = jaundice + encephalopathy ≤ 8 weeks</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Median (range): 2 months (4 days‐16 months)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALF %, mortality, predictors</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>ALF ~25%, Overall mortality ~23%, ATT‐ALF mortality‐70%</p>
<p>5‐factor prognostic score (bilirubin, INR, creatinine, albumin and encephalopathy; AUROC ~0.97)</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Tool for triage and referral in ATT‐ALF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Abbara et al. 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0047">47</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">UK</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Retrospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Patient on ATT at tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1529</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">105</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT &gt; 3× ULN, or ALP &gt; 2× ULN + bilirubin &gt; 1× ULN, or Bil. &gt; 2× ULN + causality (RUCAM)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>53% DILI ≤ 2 weeks</p>
<p>88% DILI ≤ 8 weeks</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Clinical, DILI timing and outcomes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mortality‐5%, Only 1/4th‐DILI patients met ATS/BTS criteria for pre‐emptive monitoring</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Early monitoring strategy in all patients irrespective of risk factors</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Wang et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0089">89</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">China</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Retrospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI in‐patients in tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">155</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">155</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">AST/ALT &gt; 5× ULN, or ALP &gt; 2× ULN or Bil. &gt; 2× ULN, or INR &gt; 1.5× ULN with any AST/ALT/ALP elevation + causality (RUCAM)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">
<p>Median: 7 weeks (in ALF group)</p>
<p>Median: 3–4 weeks (in non‐ALF group)</p>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALF%, mortality, predictors</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALF‐35%, mortality ~10%. Predictors‐Bilirubin, AST, TLC, platelet, preexisting liver disease</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐ALF has high mortality and early detection is crucial</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Zhao et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0090">90</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">China</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Retrospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ATT‐DILI hospitalized patients in tertiary center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">140</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">140</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Symptoms + abnormal LFT + causality (RUCAM)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean (range): 24 days (7–90 days)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Clinical outcomes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mild to severe liver injury‐79%, ALF‐21%; mortality in ALF‐34%; Overall mortality‐7%; Risk factors for severity‐ Female, combination therapy, rechallenge</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Frequent LFT monitoring after rechallenge ATT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Shen and Liu 2025 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0091">91</xref>]</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">China</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Retrospective cohort</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">TB with MASLD on ATT; single‐center</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">120</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">28</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">ALT &gt; 3× ULN; or ALP &gt; 2× ULN</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Mean ± SD: 30.4 ± 17.6 days</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Incidence, risk factors</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">DILI‐ 23%; lean MASLD increase ATT‐DILI risk; high‐risk factors‐Low BMI and high FIB‐4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Close monitoring in Lean MASLD particularly with fibrosis</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot id="jgh370338-ntgp-0002"><fn id="jgh370338-note-0005"><p>Abbreviations: ALF, acute liver failure; ALP, alkaline phosphatase; ALT, alanine transaminase; AST, aspartate transaminase; ATS, American Thoracic Society; ATT, anti‐tubercular treatment; Bil., bilirubin; BTS, British Thoracic Society; CLD, chronic liver disease; CYP2E1, cytochrome P4502E1; DILI, drug‐induced liver injury; GGT, gamma glutamyl transferase; GST, glutathione S‐transferase gene; HBV, hepatitis B virus; HCV, hepatitis C virus; INR, international normalized ratio; LFT, liver function test; MASLD, metabolic dysfunction‐associated steatotic liver disease; NAC, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐acetylcysteine; NAT2, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐acetyltransferase 2 gene; RUCAM, Roussel Uclaf Causality Assessment Method (structured tool for causality assessment); ULN, upper limit of normal.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0027"><label>7.5</label><title>Role of <italic toggle="no">N</italic>‐Acetylcysteine (<styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">NAC</styled-content>)</title><p>Animal study has shown the protective role of NAC in isoniazid and rifampicin induced DILI. In a human study, 60 new TB patients were randomized into two groups. Group I received standard first‐line ATT, and Group II received the same regimen with NAC (1200 mg/day). ATT‐DILI occurred in 37.5% of patients in Group I and none in Group II. However, the mean duration of the study was very less, and larger studies are needed to reach a conclusion for guiding decisions related to the addition of NAC as a protective therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0092">92</xref>]. Another RCT explored the role of NAC in treating ATT‐DILI. A total of 102 ATT‐DILI hospitalized patients were randomized to NAC and placebo group. Although NAC significantly reduced length of stay, there was no difference in raised transaminases recovery and mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0066">66</xref>]. A recent network meta‐analysis found that NAC (1200 mg/day) significantly reduced the occurrence of ATT‐DILI as compared to placebo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0070">70</xref>]. However, this was based on a single prior RCT. A small prospective cohort with predominant ATT‐ALF showed significantly lower mortality with NAC as compared to controls (20% vs. 75%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0093">93</xref>]. A systematic review indicated possible advantages of NAC therapy in non‐acetaminophen‐related drug‐induced ALF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0094">94</xref>].</p><p>Therefore, for prevention of ATT‐DILI, evidence suggests possible benefits but it has not been adopted by any guidelines. In established ATT‐DILI, it is reasonable to start NAC if the patient gets hospitalized, expecting only a shorter stay. In ATT‐ALF, NAC should be started early. Transplant decisions should not be delayed in view of high mortality.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0028"><label>7.6</label><title>Role of Other Interventions</title><p>Besides NAC, various interventions have been used for preventing ATT‐DILI or as an adjunctive treatment. Ursodeoxycholic acid (UDCA) and some herbal formulations may improve cholestatic and mixed‐pattern enzyme abnormalities, but evidence is insufficient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0095">95</xref>]. There is no role of silymarin, l‐carnitine, Vit C/D/A, and glutathione [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0070">70</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0029"><label>8</label><title>Recent Advances in ATT‐DILI</title><p>Considering the fact that increasing age is the most important predisposing factor for ATT‐DILI, telomere can be a future potential biomarker to predict ATT‐DILI. According to a recent study, longer relative telomere length (RTL) is significantly associated with more susceptibility to ATT‐DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0096">96</xref>]. Elevation of RTL was also associated with increased levels of liver enzymes in patients with or without ATT‐DILI, suggesting that aberrant telomere length is an important mediator for hepatic injury.</p><p>Another study from China reported that combined 5‐hydroxymethylcytosine (5‐hmC) levels of HLA‐B and HLA‐DQB1 as diagnostic biomarkers of ATT‐DILI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0097">97</xref>]. This study was based on previous genome‐wide analysis which showed that DNA methylation levels of HLA‐B and HLA‐DQB1 genes were low in individuals with ATT‐DILI compared to those without. Thus, both telomere length and 5‐hmC levels of HLA‐B and HLA‐DQB1 genes can be future promising markers to diagnose ATT‐DILI.</p><p>Monitoring of ATT‐DILI still depends on transaminases which are neither always specific to liver nor sensitive to early injury. Emerging biomarkers such as microRNA‐122 (miR‐122) and cytokeratin‐18 (K18) are a liver‐specific microRNA and liver structural protein, respectively. In a study, patients who developed ATT‐DILI had markedly higher miR‐122 levels as compared to ATT tolerant patients, and levels remained unaffected by NAC infusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0086">86</xref>]. This highlights its diagnostic rather than monitoring role. Similarly, cytokeratin‐18 (K18, both total and caspase‐cleaved fragments) has been shown to increase in parallel with ALT during ATT‐DILI in African and European cohorts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0098">98</xref>]. Preliminary data show that microRNA‐192 (miR‐192), together with miR‐122, may lead to a multi‐miRNA signature for ATT‐DILI, but results are inconsistent and need confirmation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0099">99</xref>].</p><p>Beyond these, other mechanistic markers from the broader DILI field such as high‐mobility group box 1 (HMGB1), glutamate dehydrogenase (GLDH), and circulating mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) are emerging as more liver‐specific biomarkers and give information regarding pathogenic pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="jgh370338-bib-0100">100</xref>].</p><p>Future efforts should focus on developing biomarker panels with clear thresholds, validating them in prospective ATT cohorts, and building point‐of‐care assays. Integration with pharmacogenetics and omics data can enable high accuracy risk prediction leading to personalized ATT regimens.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0030" sec-type="conclusions"><label>9</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>DILI is unpredictable with ATT due to its idiosyncratic nature. It is important to be aware of its wide spectrum from asymptomatic raised transaminases to ALF because hepatic adaptation does not require any modification or cessation of ATT and early detection of clinically significant DILI by frequent monitoring results in better prognosis. Prompt withdrawal of all the potential hepatotoxic drugs is the key step in the management followed by sequential restart with incremental dosage of least hepatotoxic anti‐tubercular drug first, after raised transaminases settle. More studies are needed for proper positioning of newer anti‐tubercular drugs in modified ATT regimens. Future research is needed to identify specific biomarkers for diagnosing ATT‐DILI.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0031"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors have nothing to report.</p></sec><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0032" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="jgh370338-sec-0034" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="jgh370338-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0001" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Schaberg</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Rebhan</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Lode</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Risk Factors for Side‐Effects of Isoniazid, Rifampin and Pyrazinamide in Patients Hospitalized for Pulmonary Tuberculosis</article-title>,” <source>European Respiratory Journal</source>
<volume>9</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue> (<year>1996</year>): <fpage>2026</fpage>–<lpage>2030</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8902462</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.96.09102026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0002" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Kaplowitz</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source>
<volume>38</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2004</year>): <fpage>S44</fpage>–<lpage>S48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14986274</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/381446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0003" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Kaplowitz</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Biochemical and Cellular Mechanisms of Toxic Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Seminars in Liver Disease</source>
<volume>22</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2002</year>): <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12016545</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2002-30100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0004" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H. C.</given-names>
<surname>Devarbhavi</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
<surname>Andrade</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Natural History of Idiosyncratic Drug‐Induced Liver Injury and Prognostic Models</article-title>,” <source>Liver International</source>
<volume>45</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2025</year>): <elocation-id>e70138</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40364729</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/liv.70138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12076114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0005" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Devarbhavi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Dierkhising</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W. K.</given-names>
<surname>Kremers</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. S.</given-names>
<surname>Sandeep</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Karanth</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. K.</given-names>
<surname>Adarsh</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Single‐Center Experience With Drug‐Induced Liver Injury From India: Causes, Outcome, Prognosis, and Predictors of Mortality</article-title>,” <source>American Journal of Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>105</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2010</year>): <fpage>2396</fpage>–<lpage>2404</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20648003</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ajg.2010.287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0006" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Devarbhavi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Singh</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Patil</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Sheth</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. K.</given-names>
<surname>Adarsh</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Balaraju</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Outcome and Determinants of Mortality in 269 Patients With Combination Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</source>
<volume>28</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23020522</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1746.2012.07279.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0007" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Devarbhavi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A. K.</given-names>
<surname>Choudhury</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. K.</given-names>
<surname>Sharma</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Drug‐Induced Acute‐on‐Chronic Liver Failure in Asian Patients</article-title>,” <source>American Journal of Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>114</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>929</fpage>–<lpage>937</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31021832</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/ajg.0000000000000201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0008" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Scharer</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. P.</given-names>
<surname>Smith</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Serum Transaminase Elevations and Other Hepatic Abnormalities in Patients Receiving Isoniazid</article-title>,” <source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source>
<volume>71</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>1969</year>): <fpage>1113</fpage>–<lpage>1120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5361410</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-71-6-1113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0009" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>B. V.</given-names>
<surname>Shalimar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Khanal</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Antituberculosis Therapy‐Induced Acute Liver Failure: Magnitude, Profile, Prognosis, and Predictors of Outcome</article-title>,” <source>Hepatology</source>
<volume>51</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2010</year>): <fpage>1665</fpage>–<lpage>1674</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20196116</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.23534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0010" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
<surname>Acharya</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Dasarathy</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T. L.</given-names>
<surname>Kumer</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Fulminant Hepatitis in a Tropical Population: Clinical Course, Cause, and Early Predictors of Outcome</article-title>,” <source>Hepatology</source>
<volume>23</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>1996</year>): <fpage>1448</fpage>–<lpage>1455</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8675163</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.510230622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0011" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P. D.</given-names>
<surname>Bose</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. P.</given-names>
<surname>Sarma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Medhi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>B. C.</given-names>
<surname>Das</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. A.</given-names>
<surname>Husain</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Kar</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Role of Polymorphic <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐Acetyl Transferase 2 and Cytochrome P4502E1 Gene in Antituberculosis Treatment‐Induced Hepatitis</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</source>
<volume>26</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2011</year>): <fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21261721</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1746.2010.06355.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0012" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G. R.</given-names>
<surname>Sarma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Immanuel</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Kailasam</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A. S.</given-names>
<surname>Narayana</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Venkatesan</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Rifampin‐Induced Release of Hydrazine From Isoniazid. A Possible Cause of Hepatitis During Treatment of Tuberculosis With Regimens Containing Isoniazid and Rifampin</article-title>,” <source>American Review of Respiratory Disease</source>
<volume>133</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>1986</year>): <fpage>1072</fpage>–<lpage>1075</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3717759</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/arrd.1986.133.6.1072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0013" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Leiro</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Fernández‐Villar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Valverde</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Influence of Glutathione S‐Transferase M1 and T1 Homozygous Null Mutations on the Risk of Antituberculosis Drug‐Induced Hepatotoxicity in a Caucasian Population</article-title>,” <source>Liver International</source>
<volume>28</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2008</year>): <fpage>835</fpage>–<lpage>839</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397238</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1478-3231.2008.01700.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0014" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Nakajima</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Fukami</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Kobayashi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Watanabe</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Nakajima</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Yokoi</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Human Arylacetamide Deacetylase Is Responsible for Deacetylation of Rifamycins: Rifampicin, Rifabutin, and Rifapentine</article-title>,” <source>Biochemical Pharmacology</source>
<volume>82</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2011</year>): <fpage>1747</fpage>–<lpage>1756</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21856291</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2011.08.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0015" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. A.</given-names>
<surname>Jamis‐Dow</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A. G.</given-names>
<surname>Katki</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. M.</given-names>
<surname>Collins</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. W.</given-names>
<surname>Klecker</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Rifampin and Rifabutin and Their Metabolism by Human Liver Esterases</article-title>,” <source>Xenobiotica</source>
<volume>27</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue> (<year>1997</year>): <fpage>1015</fpage>–<lpage>1024</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9364739</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/004982597239994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0016" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Menzies</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. J.</given-names>
<surname>Dion</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Rabinovitch</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Mannix</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Brassard</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Schwartzman</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Treatment Completion and Costs of a Randomized Trial of Rifampin for 4 Months Versus Isoniazid for 9 Months</article-title>,” <source>American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine</source>
<volume>170</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2004</year>): <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15172892</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200404-478OC</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0017" publication-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="authors">Hong Kong Chest Service/Tuberculosis Research Centre, Madras/British Medical Research Council</collab>
, “<article-title>A Double‐Blind Placebo‐Controlled Clinical Trial of Three Antituberculosis Chemoprophylaxis Regimens in Patients With Silicosis in Hong Kong</article-title>,” <source>American Review of Respiratory Disease</source>
<volume>145</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>1992</year>): <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1731596</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm/145.1.36</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0018" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>O.</given-names>
<surname>Burk</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Koch</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Raucy</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>The Induction of Cytochrome P450 3A5 (CYP3A5) in the Human Liver and Intestine Is Mediated by the Xenobiotic Sensors Pregnane X Receptor (PXR) and Constitutively Activated Receptor (CAR)</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
<volume>279</volume>, no. <issue>37</issue> (<year>2004</year>): <fpage>38379</fpage>–<lpage>38385</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15252010</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M404949200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0019" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Kimchi‐Sarfaty</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. M.</given-names>
<surname>Oh</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>I. W.</given-names>
<surname>Kim</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>A “Silent” Polymorphism in the MDR1 Gene Changes Substrate Specificity</article-title>,” <source>Science</source>
<volume>315</volume>, no. <issue>26</issue> (<year>2007</year>): <fpage>525</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17185560</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1135308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0020" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Yimer</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Ueda</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Habtewold</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Pharmacogenetic &amp; Pharmacokinetic Biomarker for Efavirenz Based ARV and Rifampicin Based Anti‐TB Drug Induced Liver Injury in TB‐HIV Infected Patients</article-title>,” <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>, no. <issue>12</issue> (<year>2011</year>): <elocation-id>e27810</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22162992</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3232196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0021" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
<surname>Byrne</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. S.</given-names>
<surname>Strautnieks</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Mieli‐Vergani</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. F.</given-names>
<surname>Higgins</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K. J.</given-names>
<surname>Linton</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>The Human Bile Salt Export Pump: Characterization of Substrate Specificity and Identification of Inhibitors</article-title>,” <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>123</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2002</year>): <fpage>1649</fpage>–<lpage>1658</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12404239</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/gast.2002.36591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0022" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. J.</given-names>
<surname>Saukkonen</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D. L.</given-names>
<surname>Cohn</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. M.</given-names>
<surname>Jasmer</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>An Official ATS Statement: Hepatotoxicity of Antituberculosis Therapy</article-title>,” <source>American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine</source>
<volume>174</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2006</year>): <fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>952</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17021358</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200510-1666ST</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0023" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Hu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Yang</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Z. G.</given-names>
<surname>He</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Molecular Mechanism of the Synergistic Activity of Ethambutol and Isoniazid Against <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">
<italic toggle="no">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>
</styled-content>
</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
<volume>293</volume>, no. <issue>43</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>16741</fpage>–<lpage>16750</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30185616</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.RA118.002693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6204910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0024" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Gulliford</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A. D.</given-names>
<surname>Mackay</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Prowse</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Cholestatic Jaundice Caused by Ethambutol</article-title>,” <source>British Medical Journal</source>
<volume>292</volume>, no. <issue>6524</issue> (<year>1986</year>): <fpage>866</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3083914</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.292.6524.866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1339973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0025" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. C.</given-names>
<surname>Ho</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y. C.</given-names>
<surname>Chen</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>F. C.</given-names>
<surname>Hu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. J.</given-names>
<surname>Yu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P. C.</given-names>
<surname>Yang</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K. T.</given-names>
<surname>Luh</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Safety of Fluoroquinolone Use in Patients With Hepatotoxicity Induced by Anti‐Tuberculosis Regimens</article-title>,” <source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source>
<volume>48</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2009</year>): <fpage>1526</fpage>–<lpage>1533</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19400686</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/598929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0026" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Saigal</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. R.</given-names>
<surname>Agarwal</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H. P.</given-names>
<surname>Nandeesh</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
<surname>Sarin</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Safety of an Ofloxacin‐Based Antitubercular Regimen for the Treatment of Tuberculosis in Patients With Underlying Chronic Liver Disease: A Preliminary Report</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</source>
<volume>16</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>2001</year>): <fpage>1028</fpage>–<lpage>1032</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11595068</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1746.2001.02570.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0027" publication-type="book">
<collab collab-type="authors">Linezolid</collab>
, <source>LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</source> (<publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK548245/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK548245/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31643176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0028" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Nahid</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. R.</given-names>
<surname>Mase</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G. B.</given-names>
<surname>Migliori</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Treatment of Drug‐Resistant Tuberculosis. An Official ATS/CDC/ERS/IDSA Clinical Practice Guideline</article-title>,” <source>American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine</source>
<volume>200</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>e93</fpage>–<lpage>e142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31729908</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201909-1874ST</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6857485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0029" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H. M.</given-names>
<surname>Blumberg</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W. J.</given-names>
<surname>Burman</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. E.</given-names>
<surname>Chaisson</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>American Thoracic Society/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention/Infectious Diseases Society of America: Treatment of Tuberculosis</article-title>,” <source>American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine</source>
<volume>167</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2003</year>): <fpage>603</fpage>–<lpage>662</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12588714</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.167.4.603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0030" publication-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="authors">British Tuberculosis Association</collab>
, “<article-title>A Comparison of the Toxicity of Prothionamide and Ethionamide: A Report From the Research Committee of the British Tuberculosis Association</article-title>,” <source>Tubercle</source>
<volume>49</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>1968</year>): <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5243159</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0031" publication-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="authors">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>
, “<article-title>Provisional CDC Guidelines for the Use and Safety Monitoring of Bedaquiline Fumarate (Sirturo) for the Treatment of Multidrug‐Resistant Tuberculosis</article-title>,” <source>MMWR Recommendations and Reports</source>
<volume>62</volume>, no. <issue>25</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24157696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0032" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. R.</given-names>
<surname>Knowles</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Uetrecht</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N. H.</given-names>
<surname>Shear</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Idiosyncratic Drug Reactions: The Reactive Metabolite Syndromes</article-title>,” <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>356</volume>, no. <issue>9241</issue> (<year>2000</year>): <fpage>1587</fpage>–<lpage>1591</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11075787</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(00)03137-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0033" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Nanashima</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Mawatari</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Tahara</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Genetic Variants in Antioxidant Pathway: Risk Factors for Hepatotoxicity in Tuberculosis Patients</article-title>,” <source>Tuberculosis</source>
<volume>92</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2012</year>): <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22341855</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tube.2011.12.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0034" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y. S.</given-names>
<surname>Huang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W. J.</given-names>
<surname>Su</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y. H.</given-names>
<surname>Huang</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Genetic Polymorphisms of Manganese Superoxide Dismutase, NAD(P)H:Quinone Oxidoreductase, Glutathione S‐Transferase M1 and T1, and the Susceptibility to Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Hepatology</source>
<volume>47</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2007</year>): <fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17400324</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2007.02.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0035" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Dara</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Z. X.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Kaplowitz</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Mechanisms of Adaptation and Progression in Idiosyncratic Drug Induced Liver Injury, Clinical Implications</article-title>,” <source>Liver International</source>
<volume>36</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>158</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26484420</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/liv.12988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4718752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0036" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
<surname>Sharma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Balamurugan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P. K.</given-names>
<surname>Saha</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. M.</given-names>
<surname>Pandey</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N. K.</given-names>
<surname>Mehra</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Evaluation of Clinical and Immunogenetic Risk Factors for the Development of Hepatotoxicity During Antituberculosis Treatment</article-title>,” <source>American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine</source>
<volume>166</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2002</year>): <fpage>916</fpage>–<lpage>919</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12359646</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.2108091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0037" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
<surname>Fontana</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Pathogenesis of Idiosyncratic Drug‐Induced Liver Injury and Clinical Perspectives</article-title>,” <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>146</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>914</fpage>–<lpage>928</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24389305</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2013.12.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4031195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0038" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Murata</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Hamada</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Sugimoto</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Nakano</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>A Novel Mechanism for Drug‐Induced Liver Failure: Inhibition of Histone Acetylation by Hydralazine Derivatives</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Hepatology</source>
<volume>46</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2007</year>): <fpage>322</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17156885</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2006.09.017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0039" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. J.</given-names>
<surname>Hwang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. C.</given-names>
<surname>Wu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. N.</given-names>
<surname>Lee</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>A Prospective Clinical Study of Isoniazid‐Rifampicin‐Pyrazinamide‐Induced Liver Injury in an Area Endemic for Hepatitis B</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</source>
<volume>12</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>1997</year>): <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9076631</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1746.1997.tb00353.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0040" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A. L.</given-names>
<surname>Franks</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N. J.</given-names>
<surname>Binkin</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D. E.</given-names>
<surname>Snider</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W. M.</given-names>
<surname>Rokaw</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Becker</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Isoniazid Hepatitis Among Pregnant and Postpartum Hispanic Patients</article-title>,” <source>Public Health Reports</source>
<volume>104</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>1989</year>): <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2495549</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1580026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0041" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
<surname>Lee</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. Z.</given-names>
<surname>Mennone</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. C.</given-names>
<surname>Jones</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W. S.</given-names>
<surname>Paul</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Risk Factors for Hepatotoxicity Associated With Rifampin and Pyrazinamide for the Treatment of Latent Tuberculosis Infection: Experience From Three Public Health Tuberculosis Clinics</article-title>,” <source>International Journal of Tuberculosis and Lung Disease</source>
<volume>6</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2002</year>): <fpage>995</fpage>–<lpage>1000</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12475146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0042" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>F. F.</given-names>
<surname>Fountain</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Tolley</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. R.</given-names>
<surname>Chrisman</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T. H.</given-names>
<surname>Self</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Isoniazid Hepatotoxicity Associated With Treatment of Latent Tuberculosis Infection: A 7‐Year Evaluation From a Public Health Tuberculosis Clinic</article-title>,” <source>Chest</source>
<volume>128</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2005</year>): <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16002924</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.128.1.116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0043" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Walter‐Sack</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>U.</given-names>
<surname>Klotz</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Influence of Diet and Nutritional Status on Drug Metabolism</article-title>,” <source>Clinical Pharmacokinetics</source>
<volume>31</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>1996</year>): <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8827399</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00003088-199631010-00004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0044" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Warmelink</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N. H.</given-names>
<surname>ten Hacken</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T. S.</given-names>
<surname>van der Werf</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>van Altena</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Weight Loss During Tuberculosis Treatment Is an Important Risk Factor for Drug‐Induced Hepatotoxicity</article-title>,” <source>British Journal of Nutrition</source>
<volume>105</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2011</year>): <fpage>400</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20875187</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114510003636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0045" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. Y.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. H.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>F. C.</given-names>
<surname>Hu</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Risk Factors of Hepatitis During Anti‐Tuberculous Treatment and Implications of Hepatitis Virus Load</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Infection</source>
<volume>62</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2011</year>): <fpage>448</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21570123</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2011.04.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0046" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Patterns of Liver Injury and Adaptation in Patients With Abdominal Tuberculosis on Antituberculosis Treatment: A Prospective Cohort Study</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Clinical and Experimental Hepatology</source>
<volume>15</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2025</year>): <elocation-id>103124</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40893337</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jceh.2025.103124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12397937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0047" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Abbara</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Chitty</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. K.</given-names>
<surname>Roe</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Drug‐Induced Liver Injury From Antituberculous Treatment: A Retrospective Study From a Large TB Centre in the UK</article-title>,” <source>BMC Infectious Diseases</source>
<volume>17</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>231</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28340562</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-017-2330-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5366108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0048" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Rathi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Pipaliya</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Patel</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Ingle</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Phadke</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Sawant</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Drug Induced Liver Injury at a Tertiary Hospital in India: Etiology, Clinical Features and Predictors of Mortality</article-title>,” <source>Annals of Hepatology</source>
<volume>16</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>442</fpage>–<lpage>450</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28425415</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.5604/16652681.1235488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0049" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Patel</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Incidence and Risk Factors of Antituberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury in India: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis</article-title>,” <source>Indian Journal of Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>44</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2025</year>): <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39225936</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12664-024-01643-w</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0050" publication-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="authors">Joint T</collab>
, “<article-title>Chemotherapy and Management of Tuberculosis in the United Kingdom: Recommendations 1998. Joint Tuberculosis Committee of the British Thoracic Society</article-title>,” <source>Thorax</source>
<volume>53</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>1998</year>): <fpage>536</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9797751</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1745276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0051" publication-type="book">
<collab collab-type="authors">World Health Organization</collab>
, <source>Treatment of Tuberculosis: Guidelines</source> (<publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/44165" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/44165</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23741786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0052" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Devarbhavi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Aithal</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Treeprasertsuk</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Drug‐Induced Liver Injury: Asia Pacific Association of Study of Liver Consensus Guidelines</article-title>,” <source>Hepatology International</source>
<volume>15</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33641080</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12072-021-10144-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0053" publication-type="book">
<collab collab-type="authors">National Collaborating Centre for Chronic Conditions (UK), Centre for Clinical Practice at NICE (UK)</collab>
, <source>Tuberculosis: Clinical Diagnosis and Management of Tuberculosis, and Measures for Its Prevention and Control</source> (<publisher-name>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (UK)</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK97852/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK97852/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22720337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0054" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
<surname>Steele</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. F.</given-names>
<surname>Burk</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. M.</given-names>
<surname>DesPrez</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Toxic Hepatitis With Isoniazid and Rifampin. A Meta‐Analysis</article-title>,” <source>Chest</source>
<volume>99</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>1991</year>): <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>471</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1824929</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.99.2.465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0055" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. K.</given-names>
<surname>Dhiman</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>V. A.</given-names>
<surname>Saraswat</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Rajekar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Reddy</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y. K.</given-names>
<surname>Chawla</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>A Guide to the Management of Tuberculosis in Patients With Chronic Liver Disease</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Clinical and Experimental Hepatology</source>
<volume>2</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2012</year>): <fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25755442</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jceh.2012.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3940527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0056" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Mishra</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Taneja</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>De</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Tuberculosis in Cirrhosis—A Diagnostic and Management Conundrum</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Clinical and Experimental Hepatology</source>
<volume>12</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>286</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35535073</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jceh.2021.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9077226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0057" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. N.</given-names>
<surname>Cheng</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. W.</given-names>
<surname>Lin</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. C.</given-names>
<surname>Wu</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Early Linezolid‐Associated Lactic Acidosis in a Patient With Child's Class C Liver Cirrhosis and End Stage Renal Disease</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Infection and Chemotherapy</source>
<volume>24</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29503228</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2018.02.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0058" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. M.</given-names>
<surname>Hunt</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Mitochondrial and Immunoallergic Injury Increase Risk of Positive Drug Rechallenge After Drug‐Induced Liver Injury: A Systematic Review</article-title>,” <source>Hepatology</source>
<volume>52</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2010</year>): <fpage>2216</fpage>–<lpage>2222</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21105110</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.24022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0059" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
<surname>Sharma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Singla</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Sarda</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Safety of 3 Different Reintroduction Regimens of Antituberculosis Drugs After Development of Antituberculosis Treatment‐Induced Hepatotoxicity</article-title>,” <source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source>
<volume>50</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2010</year>): <fpage>833</fpage>–<lpage>839</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20156055</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/650576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0060" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Soni</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Kumar‐M</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Mishra</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Risk of Hepatitis With Various Reintroduction Regimens of Anti‐Tubercular Therapy: A Systematic Review and Network Meta‐Analysis</article-title>,” <source>Expert Review of Anti‐Infective Therapy</source>
<volume>18</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31923369</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14787210.2020.1714436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0061" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Tahaoğlu</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Ataç</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Sevim</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>The Management of Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug‐Induced Hepatotoxicity</article-title>,” <source>International Journal of Tuberculosis and Lung Disease</source>
<volume>5</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2001</year>): <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11263519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0062" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Azuma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Ohno</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Kubota</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>NAT2 Genotype Guided Regimen Reduces Isoniazid‐Induced Liver Injury and Early Treatment Failure in the 6‐Month Four‐Drug Standard Treatment of Tuberculosis: A Randomized Controlled Trial for Pharmacogenetics‐Based Therapy</article-title>,” <source>European Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source>
<volume>69</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>1091</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23150149</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-012-1429-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3641305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0063" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>B. F.</given-names>
<surname>Zuberi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>F. F.</given-names>
<surname>Zuberi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Bader</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Alvi</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Salahuddin</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Comparison of British Thoracic Society and American Thoracic Society Reintroduction Guidelines for Anti‐Tuberculous Therapy Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Journal of the Pakistan Medical Association</source>
<volume>64</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>896</fpage>–<lpage>899</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25252514</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0064" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Meena</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. K.</given-names>
<surname>Daga</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Kar</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Reintroduction Regimens in Anti‐Tubercular Therapy‐Induced Hepatitis in Extra‐Pulmonary Tuberculosis Patients—A Pilot Study</article-title>,” <source>Indian Journal of Medical Specialities</source>
<volume>8</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0065" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C. D.</given-names>
<surname>Tweed</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G. H.</given-names>
<surname>Wills</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
<surname>Crook</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Liver Toxicity Associated With Tuberculosis Chemotherapy in the REMoxTB Study</article-title>,” <source>BMC Medicine</source>
<volume>16</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>46</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29592805</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-018-1033-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5875008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0066" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. S.</given-names>
<surname>Moosa</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Maartens</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Gunter</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Intravenous <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐Acetylcysteine in the Management of Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source>
<volume>73</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>e3377</fpage>–<lpage>e3383</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32845997</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa1255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0067" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Cai</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Yi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>X.</given-names>
<surname>Shen</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Pharmacogenetic Study of Drug‐Metabolising Enzyme Polymorphisms on the Risk of Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury: A Meta‐Analysis</article-title>,” <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue> (<year>2012</year>): <elocation-id>e47769</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23082213</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3474796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0068" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P. Y.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. Y.</given-names>
<surname>Xie</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
<surname>Hao</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>B. F.</given-names>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>NAT2 Polymorphisms and Susceptibility to Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury: A Meta‐Analysis</article-title>,” <source>International Journal of Tuberculosis and Lung Disease</source>
<volume>16</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2012</year>): <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.5588/ijtld.11.0377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22409928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0069" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>X.</given-names>
<surname>Chen</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Hao</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Incidence and Temporal Trend of Antituberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Tropical Medicine</source>
<volume>2022</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <elocation-id>8266878</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36249736</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2022/8266878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9553535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0070" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Akkahadsee</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Sawangjit</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Phumart</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Chaiyakunapruk</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Sakloetsakun</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Systematic Review and Network Meta‐Analysis of Efficacy and Safety of Interventions for Preventing Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Scientific Reports</source>
<volume>13</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2023</year>): <elocation-id>19880</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37963954</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-46565-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10645982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0071" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Singh</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P. K.</given-names>
<surname>Garg</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. K.</given-names>
<surname>Tandon</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Hepatotoxicity due to Antituberculosis Therapy. Clinical Profile and Reintroduction of Therapy</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Clinical Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>22</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>1996</year>): <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8724260</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004836-199604000-00012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0072" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Agal</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Baijal</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Pramanik</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Monitoring and Management of Antituberculosis Drug Induced Hepatotoxicity</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</source>
<volume>20</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2005</year>): <fpage>1745</fpage>–<lpage>1752</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16246196</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1746.2005.04048.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0073" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Shang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Xia</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Incidence, Clinical Features and Impact on Anti‐Tuberculosis Treatment of Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug Induced Liver Injury (ATLI) in China</article-title>,” <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2011</year>): <elocation-id>e21836</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21750735</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3130045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0074" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Singanayagam</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Sridhar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Dhariwal</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>A Comparison Between Two Strategies for Monitoring Hepatic Function During Antituberculous Therapy</article-title>,” <source>American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine</source>
<volume>185</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2012</year>): <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22198973</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201105-0850OC</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0075" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>V. H.</given-names>
<surname>Gupta</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D. N.</given-names>
<surname>Amarapurkar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Singh</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Association of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐Acetyltransferase 2 and Cytochrome P450 2E1 Gene Polymorphisms With Antituberculosis Drug‐Induced Hepatotoxicity in Western India</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</source>
<volume>28</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>1368</fpage>–<lpage>1374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23875638</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgh.12194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0076" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. V.</given-names>
<surname>Rana</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
<surname>Sharma</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. P.</given-names>
<surname>Ola</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐Acetyltransferase 2, Cytochrome P4502E1 and Glutathione S‐Transferase Genotypes in Antitubercular Treatment‐Induced Hepatotoxicity in North Indians</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Clinical Pharmacy and Therapeutics</source>
<volume>39</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24188272</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpt.12105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0077" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Singla</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Gupta</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Birbian</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Singh</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Association of <italic toggle="yes">NAT2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">GST</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CYP2E1</italic> Polymorphisms and Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug‐Induced Hepatotoxicity</article-title>,” <source>Tuberculosis</source>
<volume>94</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24637014</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tube.2014.02.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0078" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Satyaraddi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Velpandian</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
<surname>Sharma</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Correlation of Plasma Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug Levels With Subsequent Development of Hepatotoxicity</article-title>,” <source>International Journal of Tuberculosis and Lung Disease</source>
<volume>18</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.5588/ijtld.13.0128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24429311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0079" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G. S.</given-names>
<surname>Gaude</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Chaudhury</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Hattiholi</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Drug‐Induced Hepatitis and the Risk Factors for Liver Injury in Pulmonary Tuberculosis Patients</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Family Medicine and Primary Care</source>
<volume>4</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2249-4863.154661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4408708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25949974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0080" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
<surname>Bright‐Thomas</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A. R.</given-names>
<surname>Gondker</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Morris</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>L. P.</given-names>
<surname>Ormerod</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Drug‐Related Hepatitis in Patients Treated With Standard Anti‐Tuberculosis Chemotherapy Over a 30‐Year Period</article-title>,” <source>International Journal of Tuberculosis and Lung Disease</source>
<volume>20</volume>, no. <issue>12</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>1621</fpage>–<lpage>1624</lpage>.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.5588/ijtld.16.0370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27931337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0081" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Latief</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W. R.</given-names>
<surname>Dar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Sofi</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Novel Risk Factors and Early Detection of Anti Tubercular Treatment Induced Liver Injury‐Looking Beyond American Thoracic Society Guidelines</article-title>,” <source>Indian Journal of Tuberculosis</source>
<volume>64</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28166913</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijtb.2016.11.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0082" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Bessone</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Hernandez</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. I.</given-names>
<surname>Lucena</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
<surname>Andrade</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>The Latin American DILI Registry Experience: A Successful Ongoing Collaborative Strategic Initiative</article-title>,” <source>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</source>
<volume>17</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <elocation-id>313</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26938524</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms17030313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4813176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0083" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Devarbhavi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Joseph</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Sunil Kumar</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Indian Network of Drug‐Induced Liver Injury: Etiology, Clinical Features, Outcome and Prognostic Markers in 1288 Patients</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Clinical and Experimental Hepatology</source>
<volume>11</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33994711</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jceh.2020.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8103312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0084" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Yan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Liang</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Incidence and Risk Factors of Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug Induced Liver Injury (DILI): Large Cohort Study Involving 4652 Chinese Adult Tuberculosis Patients</article-title>,” <source>Liver International</source>
<volume>41</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>1565</fpage>–<lpage>1575</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33866661</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/liv.14896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0085" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. S.</given-names>
<surname>Raj Mani</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Iyyadurai</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A. K.</given-names>
<surname>Mishra</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Predicting Antitubercular Drug‐Induced Liver Injury and Its Outcome and Introducing a Novel Scoring System</article-title>,” <source>International Journal of Mycobacteriology</source>
<volume>10</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34558461</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijmy.ijmy_15_21</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0086" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. S.</given-names>
<surname>Moosa</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Russomanno</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
<surname>Dorfman</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Analysis of Serum microRNA‐122 in a Randomized Controlled Trial of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐Acetylcysteine for Treatment of Antituberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source>
<volume>89</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2023</year>): <fpage>1844</fpage>–<lpage>1851</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639145</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.15661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10952339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0087"><label>87</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0087" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Lim</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J. S.</given-names>
<surname>Kim</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H. W.</given-names>
<surname>Kim</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Metabolic Disorders Are Associated With Drug‐Induced Liver Injury During Antituberculosis Treatment: A Multicenter Prospective Observational Cohort Study in Korea</article-title>,” <source>Open Forum Infectious Diseases</source>
<volume>10</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2023</year>): <elocation-id>ofad422</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37654787</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofad422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10468151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0088"><label>88</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0088" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Z.</given-names>
<surname>Petros</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Tamirat</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Assefa</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Antitubercular Drug Induced Liver Injury Among Tuberculosis Patients in Central Ethiopia</article-title>,” <source>Scientific Reports</source>
<volume>15</volume> (<year>2025</year>): <elocation-id>31309</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40854941</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-15855-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12378359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0089"><label>89</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0089" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Shangguan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Ding</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Risk Factors for Acute Liver Failure Among Inpatients With Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Journal of International Medical Research</source>
<volume>48</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <elocation-id>300060518811512</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30477373</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0300060518811512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7113480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0090"><label>90</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0090" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Xie</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Drug‐Induced Liver Injury From Anti‐Tuberculosis Treatment: A Retrospective Cohort Study</article-title>,” <source>Medical Science Monitor</source>
<volume>26</volume> (<year>2020</year>): <elocation-id>e920350</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32145061</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/MSM.920350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7077058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0091"><label>91</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0091" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Shen</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Liu</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Influence of Metabolic Dysfunction‐Associated Steatotic Liver Disease on Antituberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Medicine</source>
<volume>104</volume>, no. <issue>35</issue> (<year>2025</year>): <elocation-id>e44078</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40898548</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000044078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12401279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0092"><label>92</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0092" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Baniasadi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Eftekhari</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Tabarsi</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Protective Effect of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐Acetylcysteine on Antituberculosis Drug‐Induced Hepatotoxicity</article-title>,” <source>European Journal of Gastroenterology &amp; Hepatology</source>
<volume>22</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue> (<year>2010</year>): <fpage>1235</fpage>–<lpage>1238</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20461008</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MEG.0b013e32833aa11b</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0093"><label>93</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0093" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Nabi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Rafiq</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Q. A.</given-names>
<surname>Arifa</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>A Prospective Study of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐Acetylcysteine Treatment in Drug‐Induced Fulminant Hepatic Failure</article-title>,” <source>International Journal of Basic and Clinical Pharmacology</source>
<volume>8</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>1000</fpage>–<lpage>1006</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0094"><label>94</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0094" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Sanabria‐Cabrera</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Tabbai</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Niu</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>‐Acetylcysteine for the Management of Non‐Acetaminophen Drug‐Induced Liver Injury in Adults: A Systematic Review</article-title>,” <source>Frontiers in Pharmacology</source>
<volume>13</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <elocation-id>876868</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35656297</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.876868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9152180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0095"><label>95</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0095" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Bessone</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>G. L.</given-names>
<surname>Hillotte</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Tamagnone</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Arnedillo</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. G.</given-names>
<surname>Roma</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Ursodeoxycholic Acid for the Management of Drug‐Induced Liver Injury: Role of Hepatoprotective and Anti‐Cholestatic Mechanisms</article-title>,” <source>Journal of Clinical and Translational Hepatology</source>
<volume>13</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2025</year>): <fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39917470</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.14218/JCTH.2024.00325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11797819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0096"><label>96</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0096" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Udomsinprasert</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Chanhom</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Suvichapanich</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Leukocyte Telomere Length as a Diagnostic Biomarker for Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Scientific Reports</source>
<volume>10</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>5628</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32221362</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-62635-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7101399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0097"><label>97</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0097" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
<surname>Ren</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Wu</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Combined 5‐Hydroxymethylcytosine Content of Human Leucocyte Antigen‐B and Human Leucocyte Antigen‐DQB1 as Novel Biomarker for Anti‐Tuberculosis Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Basic &amp; Clinical Pharmacology &amp; Toxicology</source>
<volume>127</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32180347</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcpt.13401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0098"><label>98</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0098" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S. A. E.</given-names>
<surname>Rupprechter</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>D. J.</given-names>
<surname>Sloan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Oosthuyzen</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>MicroRNA‐122 and Cytokeratin‐18 Have Potential as a Biomarkers of Drug‐Induced Liver Injury in European and African Patients on Treatment for Mycobacterial Infection</article-title>,” <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source>
<volume>87</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>3206</fpage>–<lpage>3217</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33432705</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.14736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8629110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0099"><label>99</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0099" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Bakshi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Kaur</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Saini</surname>
</string-name>, et al., “<article-title>Altered Expressions of Circulating MicroRNAs 122 and 192 During Antitubercular Drug Induced Liver Injury Indicating Their Role as Potential Biomarkers</article-title>,” <source>Human &amp; Experimental Toxicology</source>
<volume>40</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>1474</fpage>–<lpage>1484</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33729026</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0960327121997975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="jgh370338-bib-0100"><label>100</label><mixed-citation id="jgh370338-cit-0100" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
<surname>McGill</surname>
</string-name> and <string-name name-style="western">
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Jaeschke</surname>
</string-name>, “<article-title>Biomarkers of Drug‐Induced Liver Injury</article-title>,” <source>Advances in Pharmacology</source>
<volume>85</volume> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31307588</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.apha.2019.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7351790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>