<article article-type="case-study" dtd-version="1.4" id="crhe4166844" xml:lang="en"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Case Reports Hepatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Case Reports Hepatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2587</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">crimhep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRHE</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Case Reports in Hepatology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-6587</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-6595</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12891432</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12891432.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12891432</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12891432</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41684667</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/crhe/4166844</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CRHE4166844</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome as an Uncommon Hepatic Paraneoplastic Syndrome in Hodgkin’s Lymphoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="cr-0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salman</surname><given-names initials="N">Natasha</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-5433-3138</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>natasha.salman@bswhealth.org</email></address></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="cr-0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petchpailin</surname><given-names initials="DS">Diana Sittirat</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-4777-8868</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="cr-0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seemann</surname><given-names initials="A">Amanda</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-4217-4782</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="cr-0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Modi</surname><given-names initials="A">Apurva</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7336-8787</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="cr-0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names initials="R">Rohan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="cr-0006"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names initials="S">Shovendra</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0002-8021-844X</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor" id="cr-0007"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dattachoudhury</surname><given-names initials="S">Sreeja</given-names></name><address><email>sdattachou@wiley.com</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Internal Medicine Residency Department</named-content>, <institution>Baylor Scott &amp; White All Saints Medical Center Fort Worth</institution>, <city>Fort Worth</city>, Texas, <country>USA</country>
</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>2026</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">505142</issue-id><elocation-id>4166844</elocation-id><history><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-13 09:25:14.800"><day>13</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">Copyright © 2026 Natasha Salman et al. Case Reports in Hepatology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref content-type="ccbylicense" specific-use="textmining" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="CRHE-2026-4166844.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:CRHE-2026-4166844.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><abstract><p>Vanishing bile duct syndrome (VBDS) is a rare form of liver injury caused by ischemia, drug reactions, autoimmune diseases, infections, or malignancy. VBDS involves the progressive disappearance of intrahepatic bile ducts, causing cholestasis and biliary cirrhosis, with high mortality if untreated. VBDS can also present as a paraneoplastic syndrome in Hodgkin’s lymphoma (HL). A 53‐year‐old female presented with jaundice, pruritus, diarrhea, and elevated liver function tests (LFTs). A liver biopsy demonstrated cholestasis with mild ductopenia, and imaging revealed enlarged para‐aortic lymph nodes. A bone marrow biopsy confirmed HL, and chemotherapy normalized symptoms and LFTs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd id="kwd-0001">bile duct</kwd><kwd id="kwd-0002">biliary cirrhosis</kwd><kwd id="kwd-0003">cholestasis</kwd><kwd id="kwd-0004">Hodgkin’s lymphoma</kwd><kwd id="kwd-0005">liver biopsy</kwd><kwd id="kwd-0006">liver cirrhosis</kwd><kwd id="kwd-0007">paraneoplastic syndrome</kwd><kwd id="kwd-0008">vanishing bile duct syndrome</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="0"/><ref-count count="11"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1547"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>2026</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.6.8 mode:remove_FC converted:11.02.2026</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation id="crhe4166844-cit-2001" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Salman</surname>, <given-names>Natasha</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Petchpailin</surname>, <given-names>Diana Sittirat</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Seemann</surname>, <given-names>Amanda</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Modi</surname>, <given-names>Apurva</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Gupta</surname>, <given-names>Rohan</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Gautam</surname>, <given-names>Shovendra</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<article-title>Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome as an Uncommon Hepatic Paraneoplastic Syndrome in Hodgkin’s Lymphoma</article-title>, 
<source>Case Reports in Hepatology</source>, <volume>2026</volume>, <elocation-id>4166844</elocation-id>, 3 pages, <year>2026</year>. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/crhe/4166844</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</p><fn-group><fn id="note-0001"><p>
<bold>Academic Editor:</bold> Sreeja Dattachoudhury</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec id="sec-0001"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Vanishing bile duct syndrome (VBDS) is a rare type of liver injury characterized by chronic cholestasis and progressive loss of intrahepatic bile ducts. VBDS develops following episodes of cholestatic hepatitis with immunologic features. Risk factors for VBDS include ischemia, neoplastic processes, graft‐versus‐host disease, autoimmune disorders, and infectious diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0001">1</xref>]. VBDS has been reported in approximately 40 cases of Hodgkin’s lymphoma (HL), arising from an imbalance between biliary epithelial cell apoptosis and regeneration, with apoptosis predominating due to increased B‐cell lymphoma‐2‐associated X‐protein (BAX) and tumor necrosis factor‐alpha (TNF‐α) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0002">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0004">4</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec-0002"><title>2. Case Presentation</title><p>A 53‐year‐old female with no preexisting liver disease presented with jaundice, pruritus, vomiting, and diarrhea after undergoing abdominoplasty and suction‐assisted lipectomy complicated by a postoperative infection treated with cephalexin, acetaminophen, and gabapentin. Labs revealed elevated alkaline phosphatase (ALP) (564), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (271), aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (287), and total bilirubin (6.4). Preoperative labs showed an ALP of 150. Abdominal imaging demonstrated multiple enlarged periaortic and periportal lymph nodes, considered reactive lymphadenopathy. Magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography (MRCP) showed no bile duct dilation or malignant strictures. A liver biopsy showed mild lobular inflammation and cholangitis with cholestasis, without fibrosis. A diagnosis of drug‐induced liver injury (DILI) secondary to cephalexin was favored, and the patient was started on prednisone.</p><p>Despite discontinuing cephalexin and receiving corticosteroids, the patient’s liver function tests (LFTs) worsened. Serologic testing revealed elevated Epstein–Barr virus (EBV) immunoglobulin G (IgG), indicating prior exposure, but was negative for active EBV infection, hepatitis A virus (HAV), hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), cytomegalovirus (CMV), herpes simplex virus (HSV), and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). Follow‐up MRCP demonstrated nonspecific left periaortic adenopathy, and CT imaging revealed enlarged left para‐aortic lymph nodes. A liver biopsy showed cholestasis and mild ductopenia. A CT‐guided lymph node biopsy demonstrated sclerosis without malignancy, and flow cytometry was unremarkable.</p><p>Three months later, the patient had persistently elevated ALP (&gt; 1000) and bilirubin (&gt; 12). Imaging revealed T2 hyperintense, enhancing lesions in the vertebrae, pelvis, and sacrum, along with widespread lymphadenopathy suggesting metastatic lymphoma. A bone marrow biopsy confirmed Stage IV BHL. An excisional lymph node biopsy confirmed nodular sclerosis HL.</p><p>The patient began pembrolizumab but, due to lack of improvement, was transitioned to hyperfractionated cyclophosphamide with dexamethasone, followed by R‐GemOx (gemcitabine–oxaliplatin + rituximab). After five cycles of adriamycin, bleomycin sulfate, vinblastine sulfate, and dacarbazine (ABVD), clinical remission was achieved, and LFTs improved significantly: AST decreased from 270 to 114, ALT from 105 to 61, ALP from 1943 to 507, and total bilirubin from 9.6 to 4.2. Given her clinical progression, lymphoma diagnosis, and liver biopsy findings of ductopenia, VBDS was diagnosed.</p><p>The patient underwent autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT) with single‐agent melphalan 200. At her most recent follow‐up, LFTs had normalized with AST 20, ALT &lt; 5, ALP 100, and bilirubin 0.5 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-0001">1</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" id="fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Vanishing bile duct syndrome in a patient with Hodgkin’s lymphoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0003">3</xref>]. These are liver biopsy specimens from patients with bile duct loss. (a) A portal tract with almost no bile ducts present. There is also necrosis and inflammatory infiltrates such as plasma cells present around the bile ducts. (b) Immunohistochemical staining with CK7 reveals ductal proliferation in response to chronic bile duct loss, a process that occurs as the liver attempts to regenerate bile duct structures to replace the lost or injured bile ducts. The hepatocytes (arrowhead) indicate cholangial metaplasia, the transformation of nonbile duct cells into cells resembling bile duct cells. This is an adaptive response to bile duct damage.</p></caption><graphic id="jats-graphic-1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="CRHE-2026-4166844-g001.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec-0003"><title>3. Discussion</title><p>VBDS is a rare liver injury caused by drugs, autoimmune diseases, infections, or malignancies. Medications such as sertraline, lamotrigine, trimethoprim–sulfamethoxazole (TMP–SMX), ibuprofen, levofloxacin, and more are commonly implicated, with patients often fully recovering after medication cessation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0005">5</xref>]. Infections such as HIV, CMV, and EBV are known to trigger VBDS, along with both HL and non‐HL and conditions such as primary biliary cholangitis, primary sclerosing cholangitis, sarcoidosis, and chronic graft‐versus‐host disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0006">6</xref>]. VBDS causes loss of bile ducts, leading to cholestasis and ductopenia, accounting for 0.5% of small duct biliary disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0007">7</xref>]. Ductopenia is defined as the absence of interlobular bile ducts in over 50% of small portal tracts on liver biopsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0005">5</xref>].</p><p>VBDS presentation varies, with symptoms such as weight loss, pruritus, and jaundice. The extent of bile duct damage can range from irreversible duct loss with extensive ductopenia, fibrosis, or cirrhosis, to clinical recovery within months to years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0008">8</xref>].</p><p>VBDS can occur without known risk factors, as shown in a 2022 case of a woman who presented with fever, jaundice, and elevated liver enzymes. A liver biopsy revealed significant bile duct loss, and treatment with ursodeoxycholic acid and prednisone normalized her liver enzymes, with stable liver function on follow‐up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0005">5</xref>]. Similarly, a 25‐year‐old woman developed VBDS after a weight loss regimen using various medications and herbal remedies. She presented with jaundice, pruritus, and elevated liver enzymes. After discontinuing hepatotoxic substances and starting ursodeoxycholic acid, her symptoms improved, but hyperbilirubinemia recurred. A liver biopsy revealed intrahepatic bile duct loss. Imaging revealed splenomegaly, and a lymph node biopsy confirmed nodular sclerosis HL. She was treated with prednisone and chemotherapy, resulting in clinical improvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0009">9</xref>].</p><p>Liver biopsy is essential for the diagnosis of VBDS, with ductopenia defined as the absence of interlobular bile ducts in at least 50% of small portal tracts. It is important to distinguish VBDS from idiopathic cholestasis where ductopenia is absent and liver function improves with therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0008">8</xref>]. There is no standardized treatment for VBDS. In medication‐induced VBDS, discontinuing the offending agent often resolves symptoms. Corticosteroids are effective in severe cases of VBDS, while ursodeoxycholic acid is frequently used to promote cholangiocyte survival by inhibiting intrinsic apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0005">5</xref>]. It is important to note that a component of DILI cannot be entirely excluded in this context. Drug‐induced VBDS may persist despite withdrawal of the offending agent, and hepatic injury can evolve into a chronic process lasting longer than 6 months after drug cessation. Although alternative etiologies such as paraneoplastic VBDS associated with HL are strongly supported, a medication‐related contribution cannot be definitively ruled out and remains an important consideration in the differential diagnosis.</p><p>Hepatic involvement occurs in up to 50% of HL patients, but cholestatic liver injury is seen in less than 4% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0010">10</xref>]. VBDS as a paraneoplastic manifestation of HL was first described in 1993, with initial cases progressing to liver failure. Hepatic injury can serve as an early indicator of HL, as seen in cases where patients initially presented with elevated LFTs and subsequent liver biopsy revealed cholestatic hepatitis prior to the diagnosis of HL. Although not all patients with VBDS develop liver failure, its presence in HL is associated with high mortality.</p><p>The pathogenesis of VBDS in HL is unclear but likely involves immune‐mediated mechanisms such as cytokine release from lymphoma cells causing ductopenia, or T‐cell–induced apoptosis of biliary epithelial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0006">6</xref>]. Increased expression of major histocompatibility complex (MHC) in response to HL cytokines suggests an immune‐mediated process driven by the production of autoantibodies by HL or T‐cell toxicity against the biliary epithelium.</p><p>In HL patients with VBDS, the goal is remission; however, chemoradiation can exacerbate liver dysfunction, sometimes necessitating liver transplantation. A multidisciplinary approach combining lymphoma treatment with liver transplant evaluation may improve survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0006">6</xref>]. Emerging therapies targeting immune mechanisms underlying VBDS, such as rituximab, have shown promise in improving outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib-0011">11</xref>].</p></sec><sec><def-list list-content="abbreviations" list-type="simple"><title>Nomenclature</title><def-item><term>ALP</term><def><p>Alkaline phosphatase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ALT</term><def><p>Alanine aminotransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AST</term><def><p>Aspartate aminotransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPI</term><def><p>Checkpoint inhibitor therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CMV</term><def><p>Cytomegalovirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p>Computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DILI</term><def><p>Drug‐induced liver injury</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EBV</term><def><p>Epstein–Barr virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HAV</term><def><p>Hepatitis A virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HBV</term><def><p>Hepatitis B virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCV</term><def><p>Hepatitis C virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HL</term><def><p>Hodgkin’s lymphoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HSV</term><def><p>Herpes simplex virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HIV</term><def><p>Human immunodeficiency virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IgG</term><def><p>Immunoglobulin G</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>INR</term><def><p>Internalized normalized ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TMP–SMX</term><def><p>Trimethoprim–sulfamethoxazole</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LFTs</term><def><p>Liver function tests</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRCP</term><def><p>Magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VBDS</term><def><p>Vanishing bile duct syndrome</p></def></def-item></def-list></sec><sec id="sec-0004"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding was received for this manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec-0005"><title>Disclosure</title><p>Portions of this case report were previously presented as an abstract at the SOHO 2024 Twelfth Annual Meeting and published in <italic toggle="yes">Clinical Lymphoma, Myeloma and Leukemia</italic>, Volume 24, Supplement 1, September 2024.</p></sec><sec id="sec-0006"><title>Consent</title><p>Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p></sec><sec id="sec-0007" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0001" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ballonoff</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Kavanagh</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Nash</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name> et al., <article-title>Hodgkin’s Lymphoma-Related Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome and Idiopathic Cholestasis: Statistical Analysis of all Published Cases and Literature Review</article-title>, <source>Acta Oncologica</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>47</volume>, no. 5, <fpage>962</fpage>–<lpage>970</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02841860701644078</pub-id>, 2-s2.0-45849125067.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17906981</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0002" publication-type="journal">
<article-title>LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury</article-title>, <source>Bethesda (MD): National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases; 2012-Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK548715/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK548715/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31643176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0003" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Aleem</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Al-Katari</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Alsaleh</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>AlSwat</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, and 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Al-Sheikh</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <article-title>Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome in a Hodgkin’s Lymphoma Patient With Fatal Outcome Despite Lymphoma Remission</article-title>, <source>Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>19</volume>, no. 6, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1319-3767.121037</pub-id>, 2-s2.0-84889823000.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3958977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24195983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0004" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Salman</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Petchpailin</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Seemann</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Modi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, and 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Gautam</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <article-title>Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome in the Setting of Stage 4 Hodgkin’s Lymphoma</article-title>, <source>Clinical Lymphoma, Myeloma and Leukemia</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>24</volume>, no. Suppl 1, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clml.2024.06.697</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0005" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Izzo</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Gallo</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Codacci Pisanelli</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> et al., <article-title>Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome in an Adult Patient: Case Report and Review of the Literature</article-title>, <source>Journal of Clinical Medicine</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>11</volume>, no. 12, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm11123253</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9225336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35743323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0006" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Bakhit</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>McCarty</surname>
<given-names>T. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> et al., <article-title>Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome in Hodgkin’s Lymphoma: A Case Report and Literature Review</article-title>, <source>World Journal of Gastroenterology</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>23</volume>, no. 2, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v23.i2.366</pub-id>, 2-s2.0-85009165934.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5236516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0007" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Björnsson</surname>
<given-names>E. S.</given-names>
</string-name> and 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Jonasson</surname>
<given-names>J. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <article-title>Idiosyncratic Drug-Induced Liver Injury Associated With Bile Duct Loss and Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome: Rare But Has Severe Consequences</article-title>, <source>Hepatology</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>65</volume>, no. 4, <fpage>1091</fpage>–<lpage>1093</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.29040</pub-id>, 2-s2.0-85014259996.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28073177</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0008" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Nakanuma</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tsuneyama</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, and 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Harada</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <article-title>Pathology and Pathogenesis of Intrahepatic Bile Duct Loss</article-title>, <source>Journal of Hepato-Biliary-Pancreatic Sciences</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>8</volume>, no. 4, <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s005340170002</pub-id>, 2-s2.0-0035230550.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11521175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0009" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Greca</surname>
<given-names>R. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Cunha-Silva</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Costa</surname>
<given-names>L. B.</given-names>
</string-name> et al., <article-title>Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome Related to DILI and Hodgkin Lymphoma Overlap: A Rare and Severe Case</article-title>, <source>Annals of Hepatology</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>19</volume>, no. 1, <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aohep.2019.06.010</pub-id>, 2-s2.0-85072209114.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31537508</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0010" publication-type="journal">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Levitan</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Diamond</surname>
<given-names>H. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, and 
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Craver</surname>
<given-names>L. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <article-title>Jaundice in Hodgkin’s Disease</article-title>, <source>Americas Journal of Medicine</source>. (<year>1961</year>) <volume>30</volume>, no. 1, <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-9343(61)90067-5</pub-id>, 2-s2.0-0002791137.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13761548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation id="cit-0011" publication-type="book">
<source>Precision Radiation Oncology Volume 5. Hodgkin’s Lymphoma‐Associated Vanishing Bile Duct Syndrome</source>, <year>2021</year>, <publisher-name>Wiley Online Library</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>