<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4" xml:lang="en"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pediatr Infect Dis J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pediatr Infect Dis J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2035</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">lwwopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">INF</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Pediatric Infectious Disease Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0891-3668</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-0987</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Lippincott Open Access</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12893148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12893148.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12893148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12893148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41177959</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000005037</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PIDJ-25-577</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version article-version-type="Version of Record" vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Studies</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Multicenter Analysis of Clinical Characteristics and Risk Factors for Liver Injury in Severe <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> Pneumonia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-4717-6579</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yang</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>Yy2024170187@163.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names initials="R">Rufeng</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>jirufeng@lsrmyy.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yu</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="F">Feng</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">From the <label>*</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Children’s Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Jiangsu</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>†</label>Department of Pediatric, Nanjing Lishui People’s Hospital, Zhongda Hospital Lishui Branch, Southeast University, Nanjing, China.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Address for correspondence: Feng Liu, MD, PhD, Department of Respiratory Medicine, Children’s Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, Jiangsu, China. E-mail: <email xlink:href="axsliu@njmu.edu.cn" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">axsliu@njmu.edu.cn</email> or Yu Xia, MD, Department of Pediatric, Nanjing Lishui People’s Hospital, Zhongda Hospital Lishui Branch, Southeast University, Nanjing, China. E-mail: <email xlink:href="xiayu@lsrmyy.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">xiayu@lsrmyy.com</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>45</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">507497</issue-id><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-12 10:25:12.877"><day>12</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref content-type="ccbyncndlicense" specific-use="textmining" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND)</ext-link>, where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="inf-45-236.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><self-uri xlink:href="inf-45-236.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><abstract><sec><title>Objective:</title><p>To elucidate the clinical characteristics and risk factors associated with liver injury in children with severe <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia (SMPP).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods and materials:</title><p>This 2-center retrospective study analyzed 1321 children with SMPP from Nanjing Medical University Affiliated Children’s Hospital (January–December 2023), divided into liver injury (alanine aminotransferase &gt; 80 IU/L) and nonliver injury groups. Medical records were used to compare clinical features and prognoses. External validation used data from 640 patients at Nanjing Lishui People’s Hospital.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Of the 1321 patients, 55 had liver injury. These patients were typically older, had more severe pulmonary manifestations (eg, pulmonary consolidation, atelectasis and pleural effusion), and higher levels of white blood cell count, neutrophil percentage, neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio, lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), D-dimer, alanine aminotransferase, and aspartate aminotransferase. They also had longer hospital stays, higher costs and greater need for intensive care and oxygen support, along with higher risks of pulmonary embolism, necrotizing pneumonia and refractory Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia. Multivariate logistic regression identified elevated LDH (odds ratio =1.040, 95% confidence interval: 1.027–1.055, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and D-dimer (odds ratio = 2.149, 95% confidence interval: 1.648–2.802, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) as independent risk factors. The combined prediction model showed an area under the curve of 0.811. External validation confirmed the reliability of LDH and D-dimer as predictive biomarkers.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>SMPP with liver injury shows distinct clinical features. Affected children are often older and exhibit severe pulmonary symptoms. These patients face prolonged hospitalization, higher medical costs and increased need for intensive care and oxygen support. They are also at greater risk of adverse outcomes such as pulmonary embolism, necrotizing pneumonia and refractory <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia. External validation confirms LDH and D-dimer as reliable predictive biomarkers.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>severe <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia</kwd><kwd>liver injury</kwd><kwd>lactate dehydrogenase</kwd><kwd>D-dimer</kwd><kwd>risk factors</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>SDC</meta-name><meta-value>T</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p><italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia (MPP) is a common form of community-acquired pneumonia and is the most prevalent type of pneumonia in pediatric patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup> The incidence of MPP has shown a global increase in 2023, with a notable resurgence reported by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, which documented a 50-fold rise in <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> infections compared with the previous 2 years.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> The epidemiology of pneumonia is characterized by cyclical outbreaks, typically occurring every 3 to 7 years, with a peak incidence observed between July and December in 2023.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> Approximately 86.4% of <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> infections manifest as pneumonia, predominantly affecting children.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup></p><p>The typical clinical manifestations of <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> infection in children include fever and cough, often presenting as moderate to high fever, although a small proportion of children may exhibit low-grade or no fever.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup> In addition to these symptoms, <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> infections can lead to a range of extrapulmonary complications, such as neurological disorders (encephalitis and meningitis), cardiovascular diseases (myocarditis and pericarditis), articular diseases and dermatological conditions. The pathogenesis of these extrapulmonary manifestations may involve direct invasion by <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic>, immune-mediated inflammatory responses and toxin effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup> Although most affected children experience mild illness,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> there has been an increasing incidence of severe <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia (SMPP) in recent years. SMPP is characterized by severe illness, rapid progression, vulnerability to extrapulmonary complications, limited efficacy of traditional anti-infective therapies and prolonged recovery periods.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> Despite undergoing multiple treatments, children may still develop conditions like necrotizing pneumonia (NP) and pulmonary atelectasis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup></p><p>Extrapulmonary complications associated with MPP have been widely documented, with skin rash and mucositis being the most common manifestations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup> However, gastrointestinal involvement, particularly liver injury, has received less attention. Liver injury in MPP is often asymptomatic and is typically diagnosed through elevated liver enzymes, especially alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup> The clinical characteristics and risk factors for liver injury in SMPP remain poorly understood. The aim of this study was to illustrate the clinical characteristics and risk factors of liver injury by retrospective analysis of clinical data from January to December 2023, and to aid in the diagnosis and management of severe <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> combined with liver injury.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Study Design and Population</title><p>This retrospective cross-sectional study included children 1 month to 14 years of age. The inclusion criteria were: (1) children diagnosed with <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia; (2) children meeting the diagnostic criteria for SMPP as defined in the <italic toggle="yes">Guidelines for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Mycoplasma pneumoniae Pneumonia in Children</italic> (2023 edition).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> SMPP was defined by persistent high fever, severe respiratory symptoms, extrapulmonary complications, low oxygen saturation, specific imaging manifestations, rapid symptom progression or elevated inflammatory markers.</p><p>Exclusion criteria included: (1) presence of other respiratory diseases (eg, bronchial asthma, bronchopulmonary dysplasia and pulmonary tuberculosis); (2) infections with human cytomegalovirus, Epstein-Barr virus, hepatitis viruses (A, B, C, D, E) or other pathogens confirmed by culture and nucleic acid testing; (3) history of long-term medication use or suspected drug-induced hepatitis; (4) presence of malignant tumors, immune dysfunction or organ insufficiency; (5) incomplete clinical records.</p><p>Liver injury was diagnosed based on fasting venous blood serum ALT levels &gt;80 U/L (normal range: 5–40 U/L).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Ethical Statement</title><p>This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Children’s Hospital of Nanjing Medical University (approval number: 201812257-1), and the research ethics committee of Lishui District People’s Hospital, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China (approval number: 2024KY0802-02; approval date: 2 August 2024). The study was conducted in accordance with local legislation and institutional requirements. Given the retrospective design and the use of only de-identified, anonymized participant information, the need for written informed consent was waived by the Institutional Review Board of Nanjing Lishui District People’s Hospital.</p></sec><sec><title>Microbiologic Diagnosis</title><p>The qualitative determination of Mp DNA that may be present in a sputum sample as detected using Mycoplasma Pneumoniae Real Time PCR Kit (Daan Gene Co. Ltd., Guangdong, China). Serology (paired sera) was used only when the polymerase chain reaction was negative; diagnosis required either a ≥ 4-fold rise in IgG titer (indirect immunofluorescence) or IgM seroconversion. Single-serum IgM positivity alone was not considered diagnostic.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Collection</title><p>Clinical data were extracted from Neusoft’s electronic health record system. Laboratory findings on admission included white blood cell count (WBC), neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio (NLR), platelet count, C-reactive protein (BC-7500[NR]CS; Mindray, Shenzhen, China), interleukin-6 (X8-Automatic Chemiluminescent Immunoassay Analyser; New Industries, China), D-dimer(EXC810; Mindray, Beijing, China), lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), creatine kinase (CK), CK-MB, ALT and AST (Au5800Automatic Biochemistry Instrument; Beckman Coulter, Inc., Brea, CA). Radiologic results (Definium6000; GE Medical System, Chicago, IL) (Brilliance iCT; Philips Medical System, Cleveland, OH) were obtained to assess the presence of pleuritis, pleural effusion, pulmonary consolidation and atelectasis.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS software (version 25.0; IBM Corporation, Armonk, NY). Continuous variables were presented as medians (interquartile ranges) or means ± standard deviations, and categorical variables as numbers (percentages). Differences between groups were assessed using the χ<sup>2</sup> test for categorical variables and the Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test for continuous variables. Initial screening for significant factors was conducted using one-way analysis of variance, followed by logistic regression analysis to identify risk factors associated with liver injury in SMPP. The area under the curve (AUC) was calculated using receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves to compare the prognostic values of the variables. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. To validate the robustness and generalizability of our findings, we conducted an external validation using data from 640 pediatric SMPP patients at Nanjing Lishui People’s Hospital, including 15 with liver injury. The validation followed the same inclusion/exclusion criteria and methods as the main study. Clinical and laboratory data were retrospectively collected and analyzed. Univariate and multivariate logistic regression analyses were performed to evaluate risk factors, with LDH and D-dimer analyzed as continuous variables (10 U/L and 100 ng/mL increments, respectively). An ROC curve analysis assessed the model’s predictive performance.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Clinical Characteristics</title><p>This study analyzed 1321 pediatric patients with SMPP, of whom 55 developed liver injury and 1266 did not (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). No statistically significant difference in gender distribution was observed between the liver injury and nonliver injury groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.338). Patients in the liver injury group were significantly older than those in the nonliver injury group (7.8 ± 2.6 years vs. 7.0 ± 2.7 years, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.034). The duration of fever did not differ significantly between the 2 groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.564). However, most patients in both groups presented with fever (98.2% vs. 98.1%) and cough (100% vs. 98.7%). No significant differences in past medical or allergy history were found between the 2 groups. Although there was no significant difference in the incidence of pleuritis between the liver injury group and the nonliver injury group, pleural effusion, lung consolidation and atelectasis were more common in the liver injury group with statistically significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.029 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.022, respectively).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1.</label><caption><p>Flowchart for the study population.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="inf-45-236-g001.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><p>The WBC, neutrophil percentage (N%), neutrophil count and NLR were significantly higher in the liver injury group compared with the nonliver injury group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values of 0.004, 0.008, 0.005 and 0.006, respectively). Lymphocyte count did not differ significantly between the 2 groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.996). Hemoglobin levels were higher in the liver injury group than in the nonliver injury group (129.5 ± 13.6 g/L vs. 126.1 ± 10.1 g/L, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.016). Regarding liver function tests, ALT and AST levels were significantly elevated in the liver injury group. LDH levels were also higher in the liver injury group (574.4 ± 383.7 U/L vs. 356.3 ± 136.5 U/L, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), whereas CK levels were lower than in the nonliver injury group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002). D-dimer levels were significantly higher in the liver injury group [718.0 (391.0, 1270.0) ng/mL vs. 231.0 (154.0, 382.8) ng/mL, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001]. However, interleukin-6 levels did not differ significantly between the 2 groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.076) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 1.</label><caption><p>Demographic and Baseline Clinical Characteristics of Patients with SMPP</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total SMPP (N = 1321)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liver Injury (N = 55)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nonliver Injury (N = 1266)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.338</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">637 (48.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (54.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">607 (47.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">684 (51.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (45.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">659 (52.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, year</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0 ± 2.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.8 ± 2.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0 ± 2.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.034</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of fever, days</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2 ± 5.1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.6 ± 4.3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2 ± 5.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.564</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fever, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1296 (98.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (98.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1242 (98.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (1.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (1.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cough, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1305 (98.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (100)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1250 (98.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (1.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (1.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Past-history, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0(0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0(0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0(0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1321 (100.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (100)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1266 (100)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Allergy history, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1321 (100.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (100)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1266 (100)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pleurisy, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1319 (99.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (100)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1264 (99.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pleural effusion, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79 (6.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (23.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (5.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1242 (94.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (76.4)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1200 (94.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pulmonary consolidation, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.029</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">163 (12.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (21.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151 (11.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1158 (87.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (78.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1115 (88.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pulmonary atelectasis, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.022</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114 (8.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (18.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104 (8.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1207 (91.4)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (81.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1162 (91.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CRP mg/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0 (0.7, 11.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7 (0.7, 14.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0 (0.7, 11.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.583</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WBC × 10<sup>9</sup>/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.0 ± 4.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.8 ± 5.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.9 ± 4.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.004</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>N%</bold>
</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.6 ± 14.1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.5 ± 12.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.3 ± 14.1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.008</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">L × 10<sup>9</sup>/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8 ± 1.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8 ± 1.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8 ± 1.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.996</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N × 10<sup>9</sup>/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3 ± 4.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.8 ± 4.3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2 ± 4.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.005</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NLR</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6 (1.6, 4.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6 (2.1, 5.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6 (1.6, 4.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.006</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hb g/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126.3 ± 10.3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129.5 ± 13.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126.1 ± 10.1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.016</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Platelets × 10<sup>9</sup>/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">363.1 ± 122.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">365.4 ± 119.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">363.0 ± 122.9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.884</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALT U/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0 (11.0, 23.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131.0 (101.0, 197.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0 (11.0, 22.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AST U/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.0 (20.0, 31.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0 (38.5, 92.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.0 (20.0, 30.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LDH U/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">365.4 ± 160.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">574.4 ± 383.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">356.3 ± 136.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CK U/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.0 (37.0, 90.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.0 (23.0, 76.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.5 (37.0, 90.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.002</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CK-MB U/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.0 (16.0, 26.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.0 (17.5, 34.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.0 (16.0, 26.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.006</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">D-dimer ng/mL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">236.0 (155.0, 414.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">718.0 (391.0, 1270.0)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">231.0 (154.0, 382.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IL-6 pg/ml</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5 (2.2, 7.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3 (2.2, 21.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5 (2.2, 7.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.076</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Data are presented as median (interquartile range) or n (%). Bold values indicate statistical significance (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>N, neutrophil; L, lymphocyte; CRP, C-reactive protein; Hb, haemoglobin; PCT, Procalcitonin; IL-6, Interleukin-6.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Prognosis Comparison</title><p>Patients in the liver injury group had a longer hospitalization duration (7.5 ± 3.8 days vs. 5.7 ± 2.3 days, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and higher hospitalization costs (14,498.2 ± 7622.6 yuan vs. 9822.9 ± 3680.7 yuan, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) compared with the nonliver injury group. The liver injury group had a significantly higher proportion of patients requiring intensive care unit (ICU) admission (9.1%), oxygen therapy (23.6%), pulmonary embolism (PE) occurrence (12.7%) and NP compared with the nonliver injury group (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values &lt; 0.001 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.004). However, the difference in the incidence of refractory <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia (RMPP) between the 2 groups was relatively small (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.013) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 2.</label><caption><p>Outcomes of Patients With Liver Injury and Nonliver Injury</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liver Injury (N = 55)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nonliver Injury (N = 1266)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Length of hospitalization, days</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.5 ± 3.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.7 ± 2.3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization costs, CNY</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14498.2 ± 7622.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9822.9 ± 3680.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ICU, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (9.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.2)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (90.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1262 (99.8)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inhale oxygen, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (23.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103 (8.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (76.4)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1163 (91.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PE, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (12.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (2.4)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (87.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1235 (97.6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NP, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.004</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (7.3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (92.7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1253 (99)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RMPP, n (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.013</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (90.9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">969 (76.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (9.1)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">297 (23.5)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation or n (%). CNY, Chinese Yuan.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2.</label><caption><p>Comparative analysis of the average hospitalization days and costs between patients with liver injury and nonliver injury. Note: Red represents the liver injury group, and blue represents the nonliver injury group. The average hospitalization days and costs were higher in the liver injury group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="inf-45-236-g002.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Multifactorial Logistic Regression Analysis</title><p>Univariate analysis revealed that several indicators, including LDH and D-dimer, were associated with liver injury. Multivariate logistic regression analysis further clarified that for every 10 U/L increase in LDH, the odds ratio (OR) of liver injury was 1.040 [95% confidence interval (CI): 1.027–1.055, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001]. Additionally, elevated D-dimer levels were independently associated with liver injury, with an OR of 2.149 (95% CI: 1.648–2.802, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3.</label><caption><p>Variables significantly associated with liver injury following multivariate analysis. Note: <sup>a</sup>LDH was entered as a continuous variable with each increment of 10 U/L <sup>b</sup>D-dimer has a skewed distribution, which was log(log) transformed in this study.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="inf-45-236-g003.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4.</label><caption><p>Scatter plot analysis of LDH and D-dimer levels in relation to ALT in SMPP Patients. Note: LDH and D-dimer showed strong positive correlations with ALT.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="inf-45-236-g004.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></sec><sec><title>ROC Curve Regression Analysis</title><p>ROC curve analysis showed that the composite LDH-plus-D-dimer predictor achieved the highest discriminative accuracy (AUC 0.811, 95 % CI: 0.759–0.863), outperforming either biomarker alone (LDH 0.799; D-dimer 0.760) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>A). Maximizing the Youden index in the primary cohort (n = 1321) yielded optimal dual thresholds of LDH ≥ 358 U/L and D-dimer ≥ 660 ng/mL. At these cutoffs, the combination reached 80% sensitivity and 73% specificity, producing a positive likelihood ratio of 3.0 and a negative likelihood ratio of 0.27.</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5.</label><caption><p>Relationship between LDH and D-dimer and liver injury in patients with SMPP. Note: ROC curves of LDH, D-dimer and the combined model for predicting SMPP-related liver injury. A: Main study; B: External Validation.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="inf-45-236-g005.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></sec><sec><title>External Validation</title><p>In the external validation cohort, patients with liver injury exhibited a longer duration of hospitalization (7.9 ± 1.1 days vs. 5.9 ± 2.0 days, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and higher hospitalization costs (5407.8 ± 800.9 yuan vs. 3798.7 ± 1519.9 yuan, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) compared with those without liver injury, which was consistent with the primary cohort’s findings. Moreover, the requirement for oxygen therapy was significantly higher in the liver injury group (20.0% vs. 6.4%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.042), and the incidence of RMPP was also substantially higher in the liver injury group (46.7% vs. 3.8%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Notably, no cases of ICU admission, PE, or NP were observed in either group within the external validation cohort (Table, Supplemental Digital Content 1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://links.lww.com/INF/G419" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://links.lww.com/INF/G419</ext-link>).</p><p>The external validation cohort mirrored the primary cohort in terms of the associations between elevated LDH and D-dimer levels and the risk of liver injury. Univariate analysis indicated that LDH (OR = 1.074, 95% CI: 1.035–1.115, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and D-dimer (OR = 1.063, 95% CI: 1.022–1.107, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003) were significantly associated with liver injury. After adjusting for potential confounders in the multivariate logistic regression model, the associations remained statistically significant, with LDH demonstrating an OR of 1.103 (95% CI: 1.020–1.194, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.015) and D-dimer an OR of 1.069 (95% CI: 1.003–1.139, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.040). (Table, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://links.lww.com/INF/G419" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://links.lww.com/INF/G419</ext-link>) The ROC curve analysis showed that the combined prediction model, incorporating LDH and D-dimer, had an AUC of 0.797, indicating acceptable predictive performance. The AUC values for LDH and D-dimer alone were 0.793 and 0.710, respectively (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>B).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The incidence of SMPP in children has been rising yearly, with extrapulmonary complications like liver injury becoming more common. Our study analyzed 1321 pediatric SMPP patients and found a 4.16% liver injury rate, in line with previous studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> Geographic, temporal factors and diagnostic criteria differences may explain the variations across studies. Liver injury in SMPP is marked by elevated liver enzymes, with varying severities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> Most patients (74.5%) had mild ALT elevations (within 5 times the normal range), while 21.8% had moderate and 3.6% severe elevations. This spectrum underscores the need for early detection and intervention.</p><p>Our findings revealed that older children with SMPP are more prone to liver injury, possibly due to their more mature immune systems mounting stronger immune responses to <italic toggle="yes">M. pneumoniae</italic> infection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup> Like prior research, we observed more severe pulmonary lesions in liver injury cases, such as higher rates of pulmonary atelectasis and consolidation. This implies that the systemic inflammatory response triggered by the infection may be intense enough to impact liver microcirculation, leading to ischemia, hypoxia and subsequent liver injury. Elevated WBC, N%, neutrophil count and NLR levels in the liver injury group further confirmed the significant inflammatory state and its close link to liver injury.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup> Notably, LDH and D-dimer were posited as independent risk factors for liver injury in SMPP. LDH, an oxidoreductase predominantly found in the liver, may reflect “Mycoplasma”-induced liver injury or immune-mediated release.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup> Elevated LDH levels have been shown to correlate with disease severity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup> Additionally, elevated D-dimer levels point to a hypercoagulable state, which may predispose patients to microthrombosis in the hepatic vasculature, potentially impairing liver function. These findings highlight the complex interplay between inflammation and coagulation in the development of liver injury.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup></p><p>In terms of outcomes, patients with liver injury experienced prolonged hospitalization and increased costs, and had a greater need for ICU care and oxygen support. They also showed higher incidences of thrombosis, NP, and RMPP than those without liver injury. These findings indicate that SMPP with liver injury is associated with increased disease severity and treatment complexity, posing a more serious threat to patients’ health and resulting in a heavier economic burden on families and society. Additionally, ROC curve analysis demonstrated that the prediction model based on multiple factors, including LDH and D-dimer, has relatively high predictive accuracy for liver injury. This suggests that early assessment of these key indicators could enable more accurate prediction of liver injury risk in SMPP patients, providing an opportunity for timely intervention.</p><p>To further validate our findings, we used data from 640 patients at Lishui People’s Hospital, including 15 with liver injury. The external validation confirmed the robust associations between LDH and D-dimer levels and liver injury risk, reinforcing their value as predictive biomarkers across different clinical settings. However, slight differences in model performance between the primary and validation cohorts highlight the need for further model refinement to account for variations in patient populations and clinical practices. Future research should expand validation to more diverse cohorts and explore additional biomarkers to enhance the model’s accuracy and applicability in clinical decision-making.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>This study provides a detailed analysis of liver injury in children with SMPP, identifying a set of distinctive clinical features. We found that liver injury is more prevalent in older children and is closely associated with severe pulmonary manifestations such as pulmonary consolidation, atelectasis and pleural effusion. Laboratory findings indicated elevated inflammatory and coagulation markers (WBC, N%, NLR, LDH and D-dimer) and increased liver enzymes (ALT and AST). The identification of elevated LDH and D-dimer as independent risk factors highlights the interplay between inflammation and coagulation in the development of liver injury in SMPP. The clinical course of SMPP with liver injury is marked by greater severity, as evidenced by longer hospital stays, higher medical costs and increased need for intensive care and oxygen support. These patients also face a higher risk of adverse outcomes like PE, NP and RMPP. External validation confirmed the reliability of LDH and D-dimer as predictive biomarkers for liver injury risk. This validation strengthens the robustness of our findings and supports the potential utility of these biomarkers in clinical practice for risk assessment and treatment decisions.</p><p>In summary, our study enhances the understanding of liver injury in children with SMPP, offering insights that may improve early diagnosis and intervention. This study is limited by its retrospective design and the inclusion of only 2 centers in Jiangsu Province, which may restrict the generalizability of the findings. Therefore, larger, prospective and multicenter studies are warranted to validate the proposed LDH/D-dimer thresholds and to explore additional biomarkers. Future research should also focus on elucidating the underlying mechanisms to further refine risk prediction models and improve clinical outcomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><media content-type="document" id="s1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="inf-45-236-s001.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>This is a retrospective observational study, and clinical trial registration was not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The study was approved by the Ethics Committees of Children’s Hospital of Nanjing Medical University (No. 201812257-1) and Nanjing Lishui People’s Hospital (No. 2024KY0802-02); written informed consent was waived for de-identified retrospective data. All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional research committee and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>This study was designed by all authors. Y.Y. will provide supervision throughout the study as the principal investigator. Y.Y. drafted the manuscript under the direct supervision of F.L. (Corresponding author). All authors read and approved the final manuscript. Y.X. and R.J. contributed to the literature search, data extraction and analysis.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>This study was approved by the Human Ethics Committee of Children’s Hospital of Nanjing Medical University (approval number: 201812257-1), and the research ethics committee of Lishui District People’s Hospital, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China (approval number: 2024KY0802-02; approval date: 2 August 2024).</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>Supplemental digital content is available for this article. Direct URL citations appear in the printed text and are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal’s website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pidj.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.pidj.com</ext-link>).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical features and biomarkers for early prediction of refractory mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia in children.</article-title>
<source>Emerg Med Int</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>2024</volume>:<fpage>9328177</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38222094</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2024/9328177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10787049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a scale for early prediction of refractory Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia in hospitalized children.</article-title>
<source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>6595</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33758243</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-86086-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7987979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>; <collab>CDC EPIC Study Team</collab>. <article-title>Community-acquired pneumonia requiring hospitalization among U.S. children.</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>372</volume>:<fpage>835</fpage>–<lpage>845</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25714161</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1405870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4697461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mycoplasma pneumoniae: a significant but underrated pathogen in paediatric community-acquired lower respiratory tract infections.</article-title>
<source>Indian J Med Res</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29749357</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijmr.IJMR_1582_16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5967212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clopper</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeVies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Notes from the field: reemergence of Mycoplasma pneumoniae infections in children and adolescents after the COVID-19 Pandemic, United States, 2018-2024.</article-title>
<source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38386615</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7307a3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10899077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mycoplasma pneumoniae outbreak in 2023: post-pandemic resurgence of an atypical bacterial pathogen.</article-title>
<source>Cureus</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e58757</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38779270</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.58757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11111095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mycoplasma pneumoniae infection outbreak in Guangzhou, China after COVID-19 pandemic.</article-title>
<source>Virol J</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39129001</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12985-024-02458-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11318190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The prevalence of Mycoplasma pneumoniae among children in Beijing before and during the COVID-19 pandemic.</article-title>
<source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>854505</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35573799</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2022.854505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9103471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pediatric respiratory infections by Mycoplasma pneumoniae.</article-title>
<source>Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18662117</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/14787210.6.4.509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowlands</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer Sauteur</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beeton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>; <collab>On Behalf Of The Escmid Study Group For Mycoplasma And Chlamydia Infections Esgmac</collab>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic>: not a typical respiratory pathogen.</article-title>
<source>J Med Microbiol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>001910</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39475213</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.001910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11523975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poddighe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Extra-pulmonary diseases related to Mycoplasma pneumoniae in children: recent insights into the pathogenesis.</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Rheumatol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29432224</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BOR.0000000000000494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical features and “early” corticosteroid treatment outcome of pediatric mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia.</article-title>
<source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1135228</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37082710</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2023.1135228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10110948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poddighe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demirkaya</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sazonov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mycoplasma pneumoniae infections and primary immune deficiencies.</article-title>
<source>Int J Clin Pract</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>2022</volume>:<fpage>6343818</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35855053</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2022/6343818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9286979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Methylprednisolone pulse therapy for refractory Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia in children.</article-title>
<source>J Infect</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18656264</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2008.06.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7112643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Case report and literature review: clinical characteristics of 10 children with mycoplasma pneumoniae-induced rash and mucositis.</article-title>
<source>Front Pediatr</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>823376</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35311047</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fped.2022.823376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8927760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poddighe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mycoplasma pneumoniae-related hepatitis in children.</article-title>
<source>Microb Pathog</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>103863</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31712120</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2019.103863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Subspecialty Group of Respiratory, the Society of Pediatrics, Chinese Medical Association; China National Clinical Research Center of Respiratory Diseases Editorial Board</collab>. <article-title>Guidelines for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Mycoplasma pneumoniae Pneumonia in Children (2023 edition).</article-title>
<source>Zhonghua Er Ke Za Zhi</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>1137</fpage>–<lpage>1144</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39563040</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3760/cma.j.cn112140-20240722-00503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of spleen aminopeptide oral lyophilized powder in ameliorating liver injury in infants and children with human cytomegalovirus infection: a single-center study in China.</article-title>
<source>Transl Pediatr</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33633945</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/tp-20-173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7882289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of common causes of liver injury among children 12 years and younger in Weifang.</article-title>
<source>J Int Med Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>3000605211006661</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33827321</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/03000605211006661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8040568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tchah</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hepatitis associated with Mycoplasma pneumoniae infection in Korean children: a prospective study.</article-title>
<source>Korean J Pediatr</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26213549</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3345/kjp.2015.58.6.211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4510354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flamm</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Bisceglie</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>; <collab>Public Policy Committee of the American Association for the Study of Liver Disease</collab>. <article-title>Serum activity of alanine aminotransferase (ALT) as an indicator of health and disease.</article-title>
<source>Hepatology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1363</fpage>–<lpage>1370</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18366115</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.22109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curreli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zella</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mycoplasmas-host interaction: mechanisms of inflammation and association with cellular transformation.</article-title>
<source>Microorganisms</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1351</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32899663</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8091351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7565387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhull</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Drug-induced liver injury and anti-hepatotoxic effect of herbal compounds: a metabolic mechanism perspective.</article-title>
<source>Phytomedicine</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>155142</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37913641</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2023.155142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Construction of a nomogram for early diagnosis of refractory <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia in children.</article-title>
<source>Transl Pediatr</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1119</fpage>–<lpage>1129</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39144443</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/tp-24-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11320014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tóthová</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical and diagnostic significance of lactate dehydrogenase and its isoenzymes in animals.</article-title>
<source>Vet Med Int</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2020</volume>:<fpage>5346483</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32607139</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/5346483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7313120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanhong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predictive value of lactate dehydrogenase for Mycoplasma pneumoniae necrotizing pneumonia in children based on decision curve analysis and dose-response analysis.</article-title>
<source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>9803</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38684810</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-60359-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11059402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical usefulness of serum lactate dehydrogenase levels in Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia in children.</article-title>
<source>Indian J Pediatr</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1003</fpage>–<lpage>1009</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35665905</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12098-022-04205-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okishio</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased lactate dehydrogenase reflects the progression of COVID-19 pneumonia on chest computed tomography and predicts subsequent severe disease.</article-title>
<source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1012</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36653462</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-28201-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9848045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical significance of D-dimer levels in refractory Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia.</article-title>
<source>BMC Infect Dis</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33407216</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-020-05700-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7787414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of levels of D-dimer and interferon-γ in pediatric patients with <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia and its clinical implication.</article-title>
<source>Exp Ther Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>5025</fpage>–<lpage>5030</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30546408</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/etm.2018.6873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6256836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The level of D-dimer is positively correlated with the severity of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia in children.</article-title>
<source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>687391</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34336714</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2021.687391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8319762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>