<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4" xml:lang="en"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2786</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">medicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12863884</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12863884.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12863884</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12863884</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41630200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000047483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-25-06764</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version article-version-type="Version of Record" vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>4200</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Clinical Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Vanishing bile duct syndrome induced by Psoraleae Fructus: A case report and literature review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="M">Min</given-names></name><degrees>MMed</degrees><email>18273663961@163.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names initials="C">Chuang</given-names></name><degrees>MMed</degrees><email>grk7788029@163.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names initials="HL">Hong-Ling</given-names></name><degrees>MMed</degrees><email>grk7788912@163.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="QH">Qing-Hai</given-names></name><degrees>MMed</degrees><email>739301450@qq.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-7272-4186</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names initials="XY">Xi-Yang</given-names></name><degrees>BM</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Infectious Diseases, Changde Hospital, Xiangya School of Medicine, Central South University (The First People’s Hospital of Changde City), Changde, China.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: Xi-yang Dong, Department of Infectious Diseases, Changde Hospital, Xiangya School of Medicine, Central South University (The First People’s Hospital of Changde City), Changde 415000, Hunan, China (e-mail: <email xlink:href="dxy7788912@163.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">dxy7788912@163.com</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>105</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">506713</issue-id><elocation-id>e47483</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-04 05:25:13.000"><day>04</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2026 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref content-type="ccbylicense" specific-use="textmining" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY)</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="medi-105-e47483.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><self-uri xlink:href="medi-105-e47483.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><abstract><sec><title>Rationale:</title><p>Certain drugs can trigger inflammatory responses and necrosis in the interlobular bile duct epithelial cells of the liver. Persistent damage may cause bile duct disappearance and biliary cirrhosis. When over 50% of bile ducts are lost, drug-induced vanishing bile duct syndrome (VBDS), a rare yet severe clinical condition, can be diagnosed.</p></sec><sec><title>Patient concerns:</title><p>A 67-year-old woman had a radius fracture and took Chinese herbal medicine containing Psoraleae Fructus (PF) for 1 week, then developed jaundice and pruritus.</p></sec><sec><title>Diagnoses:</title><p>Laboratory tests confirmed cholestatic liver injury, imaging studies ruled out biliary obstruction, and liver biopsy showed progressive disappearance of interlobular bile ducts, consistent with a VBDS diagnosis.</p></sec><sec><title>Interventions:</title><p>The patient received plasma exchange and hepatoprotective therapy.</p></sec><sec><title>Outcomes:</title><p>After treatment, her liver function gradually improved.</p></sec><sec><title>Lessons:</title><p>PF may induce VBDS via immune or toxic mechanisms.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Clinicians should maintain a high level of suspicion for PF-associated liver injury and enhance monitoring and risk assessment during its clinical use.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>drug-induced liver injury</kwd><kwd>liver biopsy</kwd><kwd>Psoraleae Fructus</kwd><kwd>vanishing bile duct syndrome</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="ID0E1TAG158956"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Department of Science and Technology of Hunan Province</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100002767</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2025JJ70698</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Chuang Lei</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Vanishing bile duct syndrome (VBDS) is a rare syndrome characterized by a reduction in intrahepatic bile ducts as the main pathological feature and cholestasis as the main clinical feature. It can be caused by various factors, including congenital anomalies, immune disorders, tumors, drugs, toxins, infections, graft-versus-host disease, and primary biliary cirrhosis.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]</sup> The incidence of VBDS is low, accounting for only 0.5% of small bile duct diseases. Among all VBDS, drug-induced vanishing bile duct syndrome (D-VBDS) accounts for 7%.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]</sup> Common drugs that cause VBDS include antibiotics, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, antidiabetic drugs, lipid-lowering drugs, anticancer drugs, biological agents, and Chinese herbal medicines (traditional Chinese medicine), especially those utilized for managing bone pain.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]</sup> Psoraleae Fructus (PF) has been widely used in the prescription of tonifying kidney and strengthening bones. Although clinical studies have demonstrated that psoralen exposure is associated with dose-dependent hepatotoxicity,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]</sup> the development of VBDS as a sequela of psoralen-induced liver injury remains seldom reported in the medical literature. Here, we report a typical case of VBDS caused by PF.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>2. Case report</title><p>A 67-year-old female presented to our hepatology department on November 29, 2021, complaining of generalized fatigue and reduced appetite persisting for over 2 months, along with jaundiced urine for over a month. She had previously been admitted to a local hospital on October 15, 2021, where liver function tests (LFTs) indicated markedly elevated bilirubin levels. Magnetic resonance imaging findings suggested hepatitis, gallstones, and gallbladder inflammation. The patient’s initial treatment regimen at the local hospital comprised magnesium isoglycyrrhizinate (150 mg daily) and reduced glutathione (2.4 g daily) for hepatoprotection, alongside ursodeoxycholic acid (UDCA, 250 mg b.i.d.) for cholestasis. Additionally, a 1-week course of prednisone (8 mg t.i.d.) was administered as anti-inflammatory therapy. Despite treatment, her symptoms persisted, and hyperbilirubinemia continued to worsen; the detailed trend in LFTs during prehospital is presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. She was subsequently transferred to our hospital for further management. Upon detailed inquiry, the patient reported a 10-year history of diabetes and had used a herbal decoction containing PF to relieve bone pain in September 2021. The dosage was 6 g per administration, twice daily, for a consecutive 1 week. There was no documented history of chronic liver disease, and previous routine LFTs had been within normal limits. Upon admission, physical examination revealed moderate jaundice of the skin and sclera, with no other notable findings. Considering her clinical history and presentation, a working diagnosis of drug-induced liver injury (mixed type, <italic toggle="yes">R</italic>-value 3.91, severity level 3) was made. To clarify the cause, several tests were conducted after admission. Viral hepatitis serology (hepatitis A, B, C, E) was negative. Epstein-Barr virus deoxyribonucleic acid and Cytomegalovirus deoxyribonucleic acid levels were within normal limits. Metabolic and tumor markers, autoantibody markers including anti-mitochondrial antibodies M2 type, anti-smooth muscle antibody, anti-liver-kidney microsome antibody, anti-soluble liver antigen antibody, and anti-glycoprotein-210 were negative. Abdominal computed tomography showed no significant intrahepatic or extrahepatic bile duct dilatation. Coagulation parameters were within normal range. A liver biopsy was performed to assess the underlying pathology. Histological analysis identified 16 portal areas, with small bile duct injury or interlobular bile duct loss observed in 10 of them; the portal areas showed prominent cholestasis, bile duct hyperplasia with marked dilatation, multiple micro-bile thrombi, and areas of focal multilobular necrosis. Immunohistochemical staining for cytokeratin 7 and CK19 revealed cholangiocytic metaplasia of numerous hepatocytes (70%), with loss of the majority of interlobular bile ducts. There was no evidence of steatosis or ballooning. Combined light and electron microscopy findings were consistent with cholestatic liver disease, most likely drug-induced (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Trend of LFTs during prehospital. ALP = alkaline phosphatase, ALT= alanine aminotransferase, AST= aspartate aminotransferse, DBIL = direct bilirubin, GGT = gamma-glutamyl transferase, LFT = liver function test, TBIL = total bilirubin.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="medi-105-e47483-g001.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>(A; HE × 200) A large number of hepatocytes showed cholestasis, with highly dilated capillary bile ducts and numerous small bile plugs. (B; CK7 × 200) Loss of interlobular bile ducts was observed in the portal tracts. Immunohistochemical staining for cytokeratin 7 (CK7) showed diffuse positivity in hepatocytes with varying staining intensity, presenting as acinar zone 1 to 3 cord-like distribution and single-cell scattered distribution. (C; HE × 200) Loss of bile duct structures in the portal tracts was observed. (D; CK19 × 200) Immunohistochemical staining for CK19 showed the absence of interlobular bile ducts in the portal tracts, with negative staining in hepatocytes.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="medi-105-e47483-g002.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><p>After admission, the patient received combination therapy for liver injury. The hepatoprotective regimen consisted of reduced glutathione (2.4 g daily) and magnesium isoglycyrrhizinate (200 mg daily). For cholestasis, the patient was prescribed ademetionine 1,4-butanedisulfonate (1000 mg daily) and UDCA (250 mg t.i.d). However, the jaundice failed to improve significantly. On December 8, 2021, therapeutic plasma exchange was performed with 2500 mL of fresh frozen plasma. This resulted in only a transient reduction in bilirubin levels, which rebounded shortly thereafter. Considering that the patient’s current condition is dominated by cholestasis, it was decided to streamline the medications. On December 15, 2021, her medication was changed to alprostadil (10 µg daily) to improve hepatic microcirculation, while UDCA (250 mg t.i.d.) was continued. The patient showed improvement in appetite, nausea, and pruritus, along with better overall mental status. Follow-up LFTs revealed a gradual reduction in bilirubin levels, and the detailed trend in LFTs during admission is presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>.</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Trend of LFTs during admission. ALP = alkaline phosphatase, ALT= alanine aminotransferase, AST= aspartate aminotransferse, DBIL = direct bilirubin, GGT = gamma-glutamyl transferase, LFT = liver function test, TBIL = total bilirubin.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="medi-105-e47483-g003.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><p>Before discharge, LFTs showed an albumin level of 30.2 g/L, total bilirubin at 151.2 µmol/L, direct bilirubin at 119.7 µmol/L, alkaline phosphatase (ALP) at 205 U/L, and gamma-glutamyl transferase (GGT) at 45 U/L. The patient was discharged on January 4, 2022, with a continued regimen of glutathione for hepatoprotection, alongside ursodeoxycholic acid (250 mg bid). Post-discharge monitoring was maintained. On April 9, 2022, LFTs indicated normalized levels of bilirubin and aminotransferases, although ALP and GGT were elevated at 436 and 497 U/L, respectively. By October 24, 2024, bilirubin and aminotransferase levels remained within the normal range, with ALP at 251 U/L and GGT at 173 U/L. The trend of LFTs during the follow-up period is presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Trend of LFTs during the follow-up period.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow-up period timepoint</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TBIL (μmol/L)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DBIL (μmol/L)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALT (U/L)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AST (U/L)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALP (U/L)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GGT (U/L)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">At Discharge<break/>(January 4, 2021)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">143</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-discharge follow-up</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">April 9, 2022</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">436</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">497</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">October 24, 2024</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">251</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">173</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>ALP = alkaline phosphatase, ALT= alanine aminotransferase, AST= aspartate aminotransferse, DBIL = direct bilirubin, GGT = gamma-glutamyl transferase, LFT = liver function test, TBIL = total bilirubin.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>3. Discussion</title><p>A study found that PF could speed up fracture healing by promoting osteoclast bone resorption and osteoblast bone diferentiation through the extracellular signal-regulated kinase pathway<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>]</sup>; there have been an increasing number of reports of liver damage in recent years with the increase of PF’s clinical use,<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]</sup> and the clinical features seen in these patients are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. Based on the analysis of these studies, we found that PF-induced liver injury predominantly manifests as cholestatic liver injury. Most cases tie liver injury to prolonged use (over 2 months) or high doses (above 15 g/d); discontinuing PF early and using cholestasis-targeted therapies usually leads to good recovery. However, PF-induced VBDS is rare, as seen in our case, PF-induced liver injury involves many mechanisms, such as oxidative damage, cholestasis, mitochondrial dysfunction, metabolic disorders, and aberrant liver regeneration.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]</sup> The drug can induce bile duct reduction through several postulated mechanisms, including: direct assault on bile duct cells by drugs or their toxic metabolites upon release into bile; continuous exposure to toxic bile salts when the protective defense barrier of bile duct epithelium is damaged; and drug-induced hypersensitivity of T lymphocytes to attack bile duct epithelial cells.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]</sup> Pathologically, histological diagnosis of ductopenia should be performed when the pathologist documents absence of interlobular bile ducts in at least 50% of 10 or more well-formed portal tracts. The extent of bile duct disappearance in D-VBDS can exhibit stability or progression, with certain cases demonstrating distinctive features of chronic gallbladder stasis within the hepatic parenchyma, as manifested by bile duct disappearance, such as gallbladder stasis with chrysanthemum accumulation and bile salt deposition with hepatocytes around the portal area.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]</sup> The prognosis of VBDS mainly depends on the etiology. Numerous studies<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]</sup> have confirmed that the prognosis of D-VBDS is closely related to the extent of bile duct disappearance and the level of bile duct injury. Patients with extensive damage and significant bile duct injury are associated with a poor prognosis, with severe cases potentially progressing to acute liver failure requiring liver transplantation.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]</sup> Notably, due to the regenerative capacity and reparative abilities of small bile ducts, the prognosis of patients with small bile duct injury and terminal bile duct injury is satisfactory.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of cases of liver injury caused by Psoraleae Fructus in the literature.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Author (yr)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (yr)/sex</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dosage</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chief features</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liver function normalization time (d)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prognosis</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nam SW et al 2005<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44/F</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A large dose</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 wk</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nausea, vomiting, and general weakness for 1 mo.</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cheung WI et al 2009 (Case 1)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39/M</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jaundice,anorexia, and abdominal<break/>discomfort for 1 wk</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Better</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cheung WI et al 2009 (Case 2)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22/M</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jaundice and tea-colored urine for 3 d</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cheung WI et al 2009 (Case 3)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20/F</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 wk</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fever, epigastric pain, and jaundice for 1 wk, and palpable liver edge on examination</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Better</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Teschke R et al 2009<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20/F</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jaundice in the sclera</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smith DA et al 2014<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52/F</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">/</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">/</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jaundice, vomiting, pruritus, and abdominal pain for 1 wk</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Li et al 2019<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53/F</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 mo</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weakness, nausea, and vomiting for 3 d; severe diffuse skin and scleral yellowing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Died 5 days after admission</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Poor<break/>(death)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rong JC et al 2020 (12 cases in cohort)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54–77/9F, 3M</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">/</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median 30 d</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jaundice (all cases); accompanied by fatigue (7cases), nausea/vomiting (6 cases), abdominal pain (5 cases), and hepatic encephalopathy (2 cases)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 cases recovered, median 61 d</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 cases: 8 good, 2 better, 2 poor (death)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The patient, a middle-aged and elderly female, presented clinical symptoms including weakness, decreased appetite, and pruritus. Liver function tests showed elevated bilirubin, mainly direct bilirubin. Oral Chinese herbs were taken to treat bone pain within 2 months before the onset of the disease, with no evidence for extrahepatic biliary obstructive diseases. Considering the high possibility of drug-induced liver damage, further refinement of liver biopsy through liver puncture was deemed necessary. Microscopic examination of the pathological findings revealed bile duct disappearance and cholestatic alterations, which can also be observed in the histopathology of common cholestatic liver conditions such as primary biliary cholangitis (PBC). However, the patient did not exhibit the characteristic pathology of PBC, such as peri-biliary granuloma.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]</sup> Moreover, anti-mitochondrial antibodies M2 type, anti-glycoprotein-210, and other antibodies were negative, suggesting insufficient evidence for a diagnosis of PBC. In contrast, congenital cholestasis diseases such as progressive familial intrahepatic cholestasis and Dubin-Johnson typically manifest at a younger age, lacking features of bile duct loss and hepatocyte injury on liver histopathology. These conditions are characterized by elevated direct bilirubin levels without abnormalities in other liver function markers and the absence of skin pruritus. Therefore, the possibility of congenital intrahepatic cholestasis was deemed low.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]</sup> The comprehensive analysis considered that the patient was highly likely to have drug-related liver function impairment, and the RACUM score was 5 points, indicating a likelihood of drug-related liver injury. The calculated <italic toggle="yes">R</italic>-value of 3.94 signified that the initial liver dysfunction in the patient primarily involved hepatocyte damage, progressively evolving into cholestatic features such as elevated direct bilirubin, bile acid levels, and skin pruritus.</p><p>The main treatment of D-VBDS involves discontinuation of suspected causative medications. Currently, there are no specific drugs to induce bile duct regeneration, and thus, management strategies mainly focus on liver protection, reduction of enzyme levels, enhancement of gallbladder function, immunosuppressive therapy, and implementation of artificial liver support when necessary. Immune dysregulation is widely acknowledged as a key pathogenic mechanism in D-VBDS.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]</sup> Therefore, immunosuppressants have significant effects on VBDS caused by multiple causes, particularly in cases where autoimmunity is involved. Glucocorticoids are the preferred drugs, with mycophenolate mofetil considered as an alternative if glucocorticoids prove ineffective. The patient used hormones when seeking medical treatment in other hospitals, but the regimen was non-standardized and yielded suboptimal results. Notably, the patient tested negative for autoimmune-related antibodies, exhibited normal serum globulin levels, and liver histopathology did not reveal features of spontaneous liver diseases characterized by interface inflammation with prominent lymphocytic and plasma cell infiltration. Furthermore, considering the patient’s existing diabetes condition, the use of hormones could complicate blood sugar control. Consequently, hormone therapy was not included in the patient’s subsequent treatment at our hospital. Meanwhile, analysis of previous case reports on <italic toggle="yes">Psoralea corylifolia</italic>-related liver injury shows that none of these cases received hormone therapy either.</p><p>The cholestasis indicators such as ALP and GGT increased significantly at the initial examination of the patient’s onset. However, as the disease progressed, the patient’s bilirubin levels gradually increased, while ALP and GGT gradually decreased. This trend could potentially be associated with the prior use of glucocorticoids and choleretic medications administered at other medical facilities during the onset of the patient’s illness. Meanwhile, relevant studies suggested that some patients with cholestatic liver disease had severe bile stasis in the later stage. Total bilirubin and TBA gradually increased, while ALP and GGT levels showed a declining trend. The decreased ALP and GGT levels did not mean the recovery of bile duct injury but indicated the aggravation of the lesions.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]</sup> Subsequent liver function evaluations post-discharge revealed a gradual reduction in jaundice to within normal limits. However, ALP and GGT levels gradually increased again, indicating that the small bile duct of the patient had significantly regenerated and the function of the small bile duct had recovered. Nevertheless, the regenerated small bile duct was insufficient to fully alleviate cholestasis. The patient subsequently developed chronic cholestasis, a common manifestation of chronic drug-induced liver damage. Over time, there remains a risk of progression to cirrhosis, underscoring the necessity for ongoing regular follow-up assessments. If warranted, a repeat liver puncture biopsy should be considered for further review.</p></sec><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We would like to thank Qin Jing from the Department of Pathology, Changde No.1 People’s Hospital, for her assistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Qing-Hai Wang, Xi-Yang Dong.</p><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Chuang Lei.</p><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Min Liu.</p><p><bold>Project administration:</bold> Xi-Yang Dong.</p><p><bold>Resources:</bold> Hong-Ling Tian.</p><p><bold>Software:</bold> Chuang Lei.</p><p><bold>Validation:</bold> Hong-Ling Tian.</p><p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> Min Liu.</p><p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> Xi-Yang Dong.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p><def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>ALP</term><def><p>alkaline phosphatase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CK19</term><def><p>Cytokeratin 19</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>D-VBDS</term><def><p>drug-induced vanishing bile duct syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GGT</term><def><p>gamma-glutamyl transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LFTs</term><def><p>liver function tests</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PBC</term><def><p>primary biliary cholangitis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PF</term><def><p>Psoraleae Fructus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UDCA</term><def><p>ursodeoxycholic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VBDS</term><def><p>vanishing bile duct syndrome</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This study was supported by the Hunan Provincial Natural Science Foundation (Grant No. 2025JJ70698).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>An ethical waiver approval (Approval No: 2025-480-01) was obtained from the Ethics Committee of Changde Hospital, Xiangya School of Medicine, Central South University, (The First People’s Hospital of Changde City); given that the patient had previously signed a broad informed consent form and all relevant personal information of the patient has been de-identified, the Ethics Committee approved our application for a waiver of informed consent.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article [and its supplementary information files].</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>How to cite this article: Liu M, Lei C, Tian H-L, Wang Q-H, Dong X-Y. Vanishing bile duct syndrome induced by Psoraleae Fructus: A case report and literature review. Medicine 2026;105:5(e47483).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reau</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vanishing bile duct syndrome.</article-title>
<source>Clin Liver Dis</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18242505</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cld.2007.11.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bessone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernández</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roma</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Erratum to: drug-induced vanishing bile duct syndrome: from pathogenesis to diagnosis and therapeutics.</article-title>
<source>Semin Liver Dis</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>e1</fpage>.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0041-1729972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34130334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonkovsky</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleiner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>; <collab>U.S. Drug Induced Liver Injury Network Investigators</collab>. <article-title>Clinical presentations and outcomes of bile duct loss caused by drugs and herbal and dietary supplements.</article-title>
<source>Hepatology</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>1267</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27981596</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.28967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5360519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>; <collab>Technology Committee on DILI Prevention, Management, Chinese Medical Biotechnology Association; Study Group on Drug-Induced Liver Disease, Chinese Society of Hepatology, Chinese Medical Association</collab>. <article-title>Chinese guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of drug-induced liver injury: an update.</article-title>
<source>Hepatol Int</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38402364</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12072-023-10633-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desmet</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vanishing bile duct syndrome in drug-induced liver disease.</article-title>
<source>J Hepatol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0168-8278(97)82330-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9138126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Psoralea corylifolia</italic> L.: a comprehensive review of its botany, traditional uses, phytochemistry, pharmacology, toxicology, quality control and pharmacokinetics.</article-title>
<source>Chin Med</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36627680</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13020-022-00704-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9830135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Psoralen accelerates bone fracture healing by activating both osteoclasts and osteoblasts.</article-title>
<source>FASEB J</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>5399</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30702934</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.201801797R</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A case of acute cholestatic hepatitis associated with the seeds of <italic toggle="yes">Psoralea corylifolia</italic> (Boh-Gol-Zhee).</article-title>
<source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16255343</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/clt-200068863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Liver injury associated with the use of Fructus Psoraleae (Bol-gol-zhee or Bu-gu-zhi) and its related proprietary medicine.</article-title>
<source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19640237</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15563650903059136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teschke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahre</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Severe hepatotoxicity by Indian Ayurvedic herbal products: a structured causality assessment.</article-title>
<source>Ann Hepatol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19841509</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A rare case of acute hepatitis induced by use of babchi seeds as an ayurvedic remedy for vitiligo.</article-title>
<source>BMJ Case Rep</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>bcr2013200958</fpage>.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bcr-2013-200958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4127755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25103314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Acute liver failure associated with fructus Psoraleae: a case report and literature review.</article-title>
<source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>84</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30975110</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-019-2493-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6458792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fructus psoraleae-induced severe liver injury and treatment with two artificial liver support systems: a case series study.</article-title>
<source>Ther Apher Dial</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31577858</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1744-9987.13438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Visentin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenggenhager</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kullak-Ublick</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Drug-induced bile duct injury.</article-title>
<source>Biochim Biophys Acta Mol Basis Dis</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>1864</volume>(<issue>4 Pt B</issue>):<fpage>1498</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28882625</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbadis.2017.08.033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Cortes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robles-Diaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega-Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucena</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Drug induced liver injury: an update.</article-title>
<source>Arch Toxicol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>3381</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32852569</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00204-020-02885-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scoazec</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Drug-induced bile duct injury: new agents, new mechanisms.</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34931623</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOG.0000000000000813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Histopathological features predicting long-term clinical outcomes in patients with vanishing bile duct syndrome.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Transl Hepatol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1161</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37577216</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.14218/JCTH.2022.00039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10412695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Björnsson</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term sequelae of drug-induced liver injury.</article-title>
<source>J Hepatol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34688732</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2021.10.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobreva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karagyozov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Drug-induced bile duct injury- A short review.</article-title>
<source>Curr Drug Metab</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32310045</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389200221666200420100129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sallapan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faragalla</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vanishing bile duct syndrome in drug-induced liver injury: clinical and pathologic perspectives.</article-title>
<source>Explor Med</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1001302</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faragalla</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cloxacillin-induced acute vanishing bile duct syndrome: a case study and literature review.</article-title>
<source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>4633</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35730139</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.15445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zubarev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiruvoipati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Meropenem-induced vanishing bile duct syndrome: a case report.</article-title>
<source>J Int Med Res</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>300060520937842</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32865076</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0300060520937842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7469751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shionoya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kako</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makazu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koizumi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Drug-induced liver injury considered steroid-resistant and histologically diagnosed with vanishing bile duct syndrome.</article-title>
<source>Intern Med</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>1719</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37952956</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.2427-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11239245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vierling</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Primary biliary cholangitis.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>404</volume>:<fpage>1053</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39216494</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01303-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones-Hughes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crathorne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology and burden of progressive familial intrahepatic cholestasis: a systematic review.</article-title>
<source>Orphanet J Rare Dis</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34082807</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13023-021-01884-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8173883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasuwanich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudry</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karnsakul</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vanishing bile duct syndrome after drug-induced liver injury.</article-title>
<source>Clin Res Hepatol Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>102015</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36067952</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinre.2022.102015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno-Torres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>López-Pascual</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rapisarda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Novel clinical phenotypes, drug categorization, and outcome prediction in drug-induced cholestasis: analysis of a database of 432 patients developed by literature review and machine learning support.</article-title>
<source>Biomed Pharmacother</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>116530</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38574623</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2024.116530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>