<article article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4" xml:lang="en"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Med Surg (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2638</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">amsu</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Medicine and Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-0801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12889334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12889334.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12889334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12889334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41675796</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MS9.0000000000004695</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AMSU-D-25-02131</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version article-version-type="Version of Record" vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prolonged transaminitis in typhoid hepatitis: a rare case report with a diagnostic dilemma from Nepal</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-3919-0298</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Paudyal</surname><given-names initials="A">Anish</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR0001">*</xref><email>anish.paudyal123@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8846-0500</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatta</surname><given-names initials="S">Sachin</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><email>sachinbhatta089@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-2146-7367</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Karki</surname><given-names initials="S">Sphurna</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><email>sphurnakarki7@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-9776-0361</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhungana</surname><given-names initials="S">Sanjay</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><email>sanjaydhungana2000@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names initials="M">Milan</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><email>gautammilan33@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0007-3250-1685</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Paudel</surname><given-names initials="S">Subhash</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref><email>masubhashpaudel@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-2349-5541</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Regmi</surname><given-names initials="SM">Sagar Mani</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref><email>sagarmaniregmi123@gmail.com</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Nepal Medical College and Teaching Hospital, Kathmandu University, Nepal</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Radiology, Nepal Medical College and Teaching Hospital, Kathmandu University, Nepal</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>B.P. Koirala Institute of Health Science, Dharan, Nepal</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR0001"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Nepal Medical College and Teaching Hospital, Kathmandu University, Nepal. E-mail: <email>anish.paudyal123@gmail.com</email> (A. Paudyal).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>88</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">507406</issue-id><fpage>2017</fpage><lpage>2022</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>21</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-12 09:25:12.830"><day>12</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2026 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref content-type="ccbyncndlicense" specific-use="textmining" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ms9-88-2017.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><self-uri xlink:href="ms9-88-2017.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction and importance</title><p>Typhoid fever, caused by Salmonella Typhi, is a common systemic infection in areas with poor sanitation. Liver involvement is usually mild but can sometimes mimic viral hepatitis, complicating diagnosis. This case highlights a rare pattern of delayed liver enzyme elevation despite appropriate antibiotic therapy and discusses the challenges in diagnosis and management.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 24-year-old woman presented with high-grade fever, body aches, and vomiting. Blood culture confirmed Salmonella Typhi, and ultrasound revealed mild hepatomegaly. Despite starting intravenous ceftriaxone, her liver enzymes peaked on the 10th day of illness, suggesting ongoing hepatic inflammation. She showed gradual clinical improvement, and her liver function normalized completely by the 30-day follow-up.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical discussion</title><p>Typhoid hepatitis can mimic viral hepatitis, especially when transaminitis occurs without jaundice. This case emphasizes that liver enzyme levels may worsen temporarily even after appropriate treatment due to toxin-mediated damage. A high index of suspicion, early imaging, and supportive care are key to effective management, especially in endemic areas.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In typhoid-endemic settings, clinicians should consider typhoid hepatitis in patients with persistent fever and elevated liver enzymes. Monitoring trends in liver function tests and continuing antibiotic therapy are often sufficient for full recovery.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>case report</kwd><kwd>ceftriaxone</kwd><kwd>Salmonella Typhi</kwd><kwd>transaminitis</kwd><kwd>typhoid fever</kwd><kwd>typhoid hepatitis (TH)</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Salmonella Typhi (S. Typhi), a serovar of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> subspecies enterica, is responsible for triggering typhoid fever. This systemic infection remains a significant contributor to disease and mortality in regions with limited resources<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>The most vulnerable to infection are those in areas with poor sanitation, where contaminated water and food pose constant exposure risks[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. Prompt administration of appropriate antibiotics is critical for avoiding severe complications like intestinal perforation and mortality. However, the growing threat of antimicrobial resistance in S. Typhi strains threatens to worsen treatment efficacy and patient prognosis[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. This challenge, coupled with the extended timeframe required for water and sanitation infrastructure development, has heightened interest in typhoid vaccination strategies. Currently, two World Health Organization (WHO)-prequalified vaccines are available for typhoid prevention: the injectable Vi capsular polysaccharide vaccine and the oral live-attenuated Ty21a vaccine[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]. Typhoid fever typically presents as a nonspecific systemic illness without initial focal symptoms, making it clinically indistinguishable from other febrile infections such as malaria, dengue, scrub typhus, and viral hepatitis. The disease exhibits multiorgan involvement, with hepatic manifestations being of particular clinical significance due to their potential association with increased relapse rates[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]. While typhoid fever commonly manifests with hepatomegaly and mild liver function abnormalities, progression to acute hepatitis represents an uncommon severe complication.<boxed-text id="UBT0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><sec><title>HIGHLIGHTS</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Marked liver enzyme elevation (Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) 712 U/L, AST 532 U/L) with an Aspartate Aminotransferase (AST): ALT ratio &lt;1 – a pattern classically associated with viral hepatitis – posed an initial diagnostic challenge, but in this case reflected Salmonella-mediated hepatocyte injury rather than viral etiology.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Transaminases peaked on Day 10 of illness despite early IV ceftriaxone, highlighting persistent toxin-driven injury even after microbiological clearance.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hepatomegaly on ultrasound preceded the marked transaminase peak, despite mild initial enzyme elevation. Early imaging should be considered in febrile patients with equivocal serology, even when liver function test abnormalities are initially modest.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Comprehensive exclusion of malaria, dengue, and viral hepatitis emphasized the need for combined clinical-serological evaluation in endemic areas, where the Widal test limitations persist.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Full recovery with IV ceftriaxone (7-day course) confirmed by 30-day follow-up, reinforcing its efficacy despite rising antibiotic resistance in Nepal.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text></p><p>This case provides three particularly valuable clinical insights. First, we observed a delayed transaminase peak (occurring on Day 10 of illness) despite appropriate antibiotic initiation, suggesting ongoing toxin-mediated injury even after bactericidal therapy. Second, the AST to ALT ratio of less than one represents the classic pattern seen in viral hepatitis[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>], making it more confusing for diagnosis. Third, although mild transaminase elevation was present at baseline, hepatomegaly was detected on early ultrasonography, which preceded the subsequent marked rise in liver enzymes and prompted closer hepatic monitoring, suggesting that early imaging may aid diagnostic suspicion in febrile patients when serological results are equivocal. Here we report a young female patient who presented with fever and vomiting, who was found to have acute hepatitis secondary to typhoid fever.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 24-year-old female, non-alcoholic and non-smoker, presented with a 7-day history of continuous high-grade fever with a maximum recorded temperature of 103°F, myalgia, arthralgia, and generalized weakness, followed by nausea and vomiting for the preceding 2 days. She reported no recent travel or sick contacts but had a family history of Sjögren’s syndrome in her mother. On examination, she was febrile (101°F), with a pulse rate of 90 bpm and blood pressure of 100/70 mmHg. Systemic examination was initially unremarkable.</p><p>Initial laboratory investigations revealed mild leukocytosis (9300 cells/μL) with neutrophilia (82%) and a normal hemoglobin (12.9 g/dL). The Widal test showed elevated titers, which were supportive of typhoid fever in an endemic setting when interpreted alongside the patient’s clinical presentation and laboratory findings. Blood culture confirmed S. Typhi infection, while tests for malaria (thick and thin blood smear), dengue (NS1/IgM), leishmaniasis (rK39 Rapid diagnostic test), and scrub typhus (IgM ELISA) were negative. An abdominal ultrasound performed due to persistent fever revealed mild hepatomegaly without biliary obstruction or focal lesions, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>.
<fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Abdominal ultrasonography demonstrating mild hepatomegaly (blue arrow) with increased echotexture. The early detection of hepatic enlargement supported suspicion of hepatic involvement despite only modest initial liver enzyme abnormalities and prompted closer biochemical monitoring during hospitalization.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="ms9-88-2017-g001.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig>
</p><p>She was diagnosed with typhoid fever with hepatic involvement. The patient was treated with intravenous ceftriaxone at a dose of 1 gram twice daily for 7 days. Supportive management included intravenous fluids, ondansetron 4 mg intravenously every 8 hours as needed for vomiting, and paracetamol 500 mg orally every 6 hours as required, not exceeding 3 g per day. No potentially hepatotoxic medications were administered beyond therapeutic dosing limits. By the third day of hospitalization (10th day of illness), she developed new-onset right hypochondriac tenderness but remained anicteric. Repeat liver function tests (LFTs) showed significant transaminitis (ALT: 712 U/L, AST: 532 U/L) and mild hyperbilirubinemia (total bilirubin: 1.54 mg/dL, direct: 0.61 mg/dL). Hepatitis serology (HAV IgM, HBsAg, HCV Ab, HEV IgM) and autoimmune markers (ANA, Anti-LKM-1) were negative. She completed a 7-day course of IV ceftriaxone, with resolution of fever and vomiting on discharge. Follow-up LFTs at discharge showed improving trends (ALT: 175 U/L, AST: 70 U/L, total bilirubin: 1 mg/dL). Baseline inflammatory markers revealed a markedly raised C-reactive protein (CRP) of 80 mg/L and an erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) of 40 mm/hr. On the third day of treatment, CRP remained elevated at 70 mg/L and ESR at 40 mm/hr, but both showed a downward trend by discharge (CRP 50 mg/L, ESR 38 mm/hr).</p><p>Trend of LFTs, the timeline of clinical events, hematological and serological profiles, and inflammatory markers are summarized in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>, respectively. The patient had a declining pattern of AST and ALT on weekly follow-ups. The patient remained asymptomatic at 30-day follow-up, with complete normalization of LFTs, confirming recovery without complications.
<table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Trend of liver function tests (LFTs) during illness, treatment, and follow-up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liver function tests</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALT (U/L)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AST (U/L)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total bilirubin (mg/dL)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total protein</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Albumin</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Direct bilirubin (mg/dL)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALP (U/L)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interpretation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal range</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7–35 U/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13–35 U/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2–1.2 mg/dL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0–8.3 g/dL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5–5 g/dL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–0.3 mg/dL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30–120 U/L</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">At admission (Day 7 of illness)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">345</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">247</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.24</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">175</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mild hepatocellular injury</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 10 of illness (Day 3 of treatment)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">712</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">532</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">206</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peak transaminitis despite therapy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">At discharge (Day 14 of illness)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">175</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Improving hepatic injury</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1-week post-discharge (Day 21 of illness)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Improving hepatic injury</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow-up (Day 30)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complete biochemical recovery</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Timeline of clinical events, investigations, management, and outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day of illness</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinical features</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Investigations</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Management</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcomes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 1–5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High-grade fever, myalgia, arthralgia</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symptomatic treatment at home</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Persistent fever</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 6–7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vomiting, generalized weakness</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baseline laboratory tests</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospital admission</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mild transaminitis detected</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Persistent fever</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Blood culture, abdominal ultrasound</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IV ceftriaxone initiated</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Salmonella Typhi isolated; mild hepatomegaly</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Right hypochondriac pain</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Repeat LFTs</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Continued antibiotics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peak ALT and AST levels</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Resolution of fever and vomiting</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Improving LFTs, CRP</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Completed 7-day ceftriaxone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinical improvement; discharged</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asymptomatic</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow-up LFTs</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complete normalization of liver enzymes</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Trend of hematological and serological markers during hospitalization in a patient with typhoid hepatitis (TH)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient’s value at baseline</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3rd day of treatment</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">At discharge</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal range</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complete blood count</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Hemoglobin</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.9 g/dL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12–15 g/dL (female)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Total leucocyte count</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9300 cells/μL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9000 cells/μL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6000 cells/μL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4000–11 000 cells/μL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Neutrophils</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40%–70%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Lymphocytes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12%</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20%–40%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Platelets</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">156 000/μL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150 000</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">157 000/μL</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150 000–450 000/μL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Serology (infectious)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Widal test (S. Typhi O and H antigen)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1:160</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;1:80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Blood culture</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Malaria (peripheral smear)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Dengue (NS1 antigen)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Scrub typhus (IgM ELISA)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Leishmaniasis (rK39 RDT)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hepatitis panel</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> HBsAg</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-reactive</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-reactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> HCV Ab</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-reactive</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-reactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> HAV IgM Ab</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-reactive</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-reactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> HEV IgM Ab</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-reactive</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-reactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autoimmune markers</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ANA panel</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-LKM-1 Ab</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Trend of inflammatory markers during hospitalization</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CRP (mg/L)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESR (mm/hr)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinical correlation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Normal range</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;5 mg/L</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;20 mm/hr</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">At admission</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active bacterial infection</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 3 of treatment</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Persistent inflammation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">At discharge</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Improving the inflammatory response</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Typhoid fever remains endemic in many developing nations. The hepatic manifestations of this disease were first documented clinically by Sir William Osler in his 1899 observations[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. Hepatomegaly and mild-to-moderate transaminitis are frequently observed in typhoid fever, occurring in 21%–60% of cases<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]</sup>. However, severe liver injury resembling acute viral hepatitis is rare. The current case, featuring marked transaminase elevations similar to viral hepatitis, corroborates earlier reports of this unusual presentation<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]</sup>. In the systematic review of Salmonella-related hepatitis, Pramoolsinsap <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>] noted that while typhoid fever frequently causes abnormal LFTs, severe hepatitis-like manifestations remain uncommon. Reported incidence rates of this complication range from &lt;1% to 26% among typhoid fever patients. The condition carries significant morbidity, with mortality reaching 20% in cases of delayed treatment or concurrent Salmonella-related complications.</p><p>The hepatic manifestations of typhoid fever result from both direct bacterial toxicity and host immune responses. S. Typhi produces typhoid toxin, which causes DNA damage within hepatocytes, leading to cellular apoptosis and necrosis. This direct cytotoxic effect contributes to the initial hepatocellular injury observed in infected patients[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. The host immune response further exacerbates liver damage through the proliferation of phagocytes and the formation of typhoid nodules[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. These granulomatous lesions consist of hyperplastic reticuloendothelial cells that obstruct hepatic sinusoids, compromising blood flow and resulting in ischemic necrosis of hepatocytes[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. The combination of toxin-mediated damage and immune-driven pathology explains the spectrum of hepatic involvement, ranging from mild transaminitis to rare cases of acute hepatitis-like presentations. The variability in hepatic injury severity may depend on factors such as bacterial load, host immune status, and genetic predisposition, though the exact mechanisms remain incompletely understood. This complex interplay between pathogen virulence factors and host defenses underlies the diverse clinical manifestations of typhoid-related liver involvement. Typhoid hepatitis (TH) often leads to diagnostic delays due to its nonspecific presentation – fever and elevated transaminases – which closely mimic viral or other tropical hepatitis. In typical viral hepatitis, fever tends to subside as jaundice appears, whereas in TH, fever often persists despite jaundice, a clinical clue that is frequently overlooked and contributes to misdiagnoses<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>In the present case, acute viral hepatitis was initially considered due to the hepatocellular pattern of injury and an AST:ALT ratio of less than one, a pattern classically associated with viral etiologies. However, the persistence of high-grade fever, markedly elevated inflammatory markers, and subsequent microbiological confirmation of S. Typhi infection made viral hepatitis unlikely, a conclusion further supported by negative viral serology.</p><p>Drug-induced liver injury was also considered, particularly in relation to paracetamol use for fever management. However, the medication was administered within recommended therapeutic dosing limits, and the temporal pattern of liver enzyme elevation was inconsistent with acetaminophen toxicity. Moreover, the absence of features such as acute hepatic failure or disproportionate aminotransferase elevation further argued against this diagnosis. Autoimmune hepatitis was briefly entertained due to a maternal history of Sjögren’s syndrome; nevertheless, negative autoimmune serological markers, the absence of hypergammaglobulinemia, and spontaneous biochemical resolution without immunosuppressive therapy made an autoimmune etiology unlikely. Collectively, these findings, along with the characteristic clinical course and treatment response, supported a diagnosis of TH.</p><p>The systematic exclusion of malaria, dengue, leptospirosis, and scrub typhus using relevant diagnostic modalities highlights the importance of a structured approach to the evaluation of tropical febrile illnesses. Emerging techniques like Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and urinary antigen detection show promise but remain largely inaccessible where most needed, emphasizing focus on practical diagnostic strategies for real-world settings[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. In endemic settings, other febrile illnesses such as dengue, malaria, and leptospirosis further complicate the diagnostic process, often resulting in inappropriate management if typhoid fever is not considered<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]</sup>. Blood culture is the conventional diagnostic method for typhoid fever; however, it detects only 40%–60% of cases, primarily during the early stages of illness. Stool and urine cultures, which may show positivity after the first week, have even lower detection rates. In many developing countries, the common use of antibiotics further reduces blood culture sensitivity. Bone marrow cultures, while more accurate, are invasive, technically challenging, and impractical for routine public health use[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. The century-old Widal test detects antibodies targeting S. Typhi’s O and H antigens. While cost-effective and technically simple, its poor sensitivity and specificity frequently yield unreliable results in endemic regions, often resulting in overdiagnosis when used as the sole diagnostic method[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>].</p><p>The management course offers several evidence-based insights. The transient LFT worsening post-ceftriaxone initiation mirrors experimental models showing persistent toxin activity for 72 hours after antibiotic administration. This challenges the assumption that clinical improvement should immediately follow antimicrobial therapy and supports current WHO recommendations for full 7–10-day courses, even in responsive cases[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>].</p><p>Ceftriaxone was selected as first-line therapy in this case due to increasing resistance to azithromycin reported in Nepal, with recent studies documenting resistance rates approaching 25%[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. Although a local hospital antibiogram was unavailable, national antimicrobial surveillance data and regional resistance patterns informed the treatment decision. Ceftriaxone remains highly effective against S. Typhi in this setting, and the patient’s favorable clinical and biochemical response supports its continued use in uncomplicated TH, though longer-term hepatic sequelae require further study.</p><p>CRP levels tend to be significantly higher in bacterial infections compared to viral infections, while ESR may be elevated in both but is less specific; thus, markedly raised CRP with moderate ESR often suggests a bacterial cause<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]</sup>. In our patient, the pattern of inflammatory markers helped differentiate bacterial from viral hepatitis. The markedly elevated CRP (80 mg/L) alongside a moderate ESR elevation (40 mm/hr) is more characteristic of bacterial infections such as S. Typhi. In contrast, viral hepatitis typically presents with normal or only mildly elevated CRP levels, reflecting its predominantly lymphocytic inflammatory response. The gradual decline in CRP following antibiotic therapy further supported the diagnosis of TH.</p><p>This case highlights several clinically relevant features. Notably, liver enzymes peaked after appropriate antimicrobial therapy had been initiated, underscoring that transient biochemical worsening in TH does not necessarily indicate treatment failure. In addition, early ultrasonographic detection of hepatomegaly preceded the marked rise in transaminases, and a viral hepatitis–like enzyme pattern (AST:ALT &lt;1) contributed to diagnostic uncertainty. Awareness of these atypical features is essential to guide monitoring and avoid unnecessary investigations or premature changes in management in endemic settings.</p><p>TH, though uncommon, should be considered in the differential diagnosis of febrile patients with hepatic dysfunction, particularly in endemic regions. Misdiagnosis as viral hepatitis or other tropical illnesses can lead to delayed or inappropriate management. Awareness of distinctive clinical patterns – such as fever that persists after the onset of jaundice – and knowledge of the limitations of commonly used diagnostic tools like the Widal test are essential for early recognition. This case underscores the importance of maintaining a high index of suspicion and initiating empirical antibiotic therapy promptly in febrile patients with unexplained transaminitis. Timely diagnosis and appropriate treatment of TH can prevent unnecessary investigations, reduce morbidity, and shorten hospital stay, especially in resource-limited settings.</p><p>A few limitations of our case are that a liver biopsy or advanced imaging to characterize hepatic histopathology was not performed, as the patient improved with medical therapy. The 30-day follow-up, while demonstrating biochemical resolution, may have missed subclinical fibrosis or metabolic complications. Being a single case report, this restricts generalizability, though consistency with regional data strengthens relevance for similar endemic settings.</p><p>This case report has been reported in accordance with CARE guidelines[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. This case report is compliant with the TITAN Guidelines 2025[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This report describes a severe case of TH in a Nepalese woman, marked by significant liver enzyme elevation, ALT and AST, with an AST:ALT &lt;1. Despite antibiotic treatment, her liver enzymes peaked on Day 10, highlighting the condition’s persistent inflammatory nature. This case emphasizes TH as a key differential for fever with transaminitis in endemic regions. Liver enzymes may continue rising post-treatment, requiring monitoring rather than changes in therapy. Timely ceftriaxone led to full recovery within 30 days.</p><p>These findings stress the need for better diagnostics in endemic areas like Nepal. Early recognition prevents unnecessary tests for other liver diseases, as TH typically resolves with proper treatment. The patient’s recovery confirms a favorable prognosis when managed appropriately.</p></sec><sec><title>Patient’s perspective</title><p>During my illness, the persistent fever, weakness, and vomiting were physically exhausting and emotionally distressing. When I was told that my liver test results had worsened despite starting treatment, I became anxious and feared that something serious was being overlooked. The uncertainty around the diagnosis and the need for repeated blood tests added to my confusion and worry. As the doctors explained the possible causes and continued to monitor my condition closely, I gradually felt reassured. With time, my symptoms improved, and my test results began to normalize. By the follow-up visit, I had returned to my usual daily activities, and this experience made me appreciate the importance of careful monitoring, clear communication, and patience during recovery.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>Ethical approval was not required for this case report, in accordance with local and national guidelines.</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and accompanying images.</p></sec><sec><title>Sources of funding</title><p>No funding or grant support.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors attest that they meet the current ICMJE criteria for authorship. Conceptualization; project administration; resources; writing – original draft; writing – review and editing: A.P.; conceptualization; project administration; resources; writing – review and editing: S.K.; writing – original draft; writing – review and editing: S.B.; writing – original draft; writing – review and editing: S.D.; original draft; writing – review and editing: S.P.; resources, writing – review and editing: S.M.R.; resources, writing – review and editing: M.G.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title><p>The authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</p></sec><sec><title>Research registration unique identifying number (UIN)</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>Anish Paudyal.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>KH</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and years lived with disability for 354 diseases and injuries for 195 countries and territories, 1990–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>392</volume>:<fpage>1789</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30496104</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32279-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6227754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global, regional, and national age-sex-specific mortality for 282 causes of death in 195 countries and territories, 1980–2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>392</volume>:<fpage>1736</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30496103</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32203-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6227606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchello</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global typhoid fever incidence: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>S105</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30845336</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciy1094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6405273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klemm</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shakoor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Emergence of an extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhi clone harboring a promiscuous plasmid encoding resistance to fluoroquinolones and third-generation cephalosporins</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e00105</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29463654</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00105-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5821095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anwar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Vaccines for preventing typhoid fever</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>2014</volume>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24385413/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24385413/</ext-link><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD001261.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24385413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karoli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Salmonella hepatitis: an uncommon complication of a common disease</article-title>. <source>J Family Med Prim Care</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24479030</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2249-4863.104992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3893978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandeya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shreevastva</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dhungana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of liver enzymes and calculation of AST to ALT ratio in patients with acute viral hepatitis</article-title>. <source>Europasian J Med Sci</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>83–86</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hepatic Complications of Typhoid Fever</article-title>. <source>Edinb Med J</source>. <year>1897</year>;2:423–39.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hinthorn</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zarafonetis</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The spectrum of hepatic injury in enteric fever</article-title>. <source>Am J Med Sci</source>
<year>1981</year>;<volume>281</volume>:<fpage>7–12</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The liver in typhoid fever: always affected, not just a complication</article-title>. <source>J Trop Pediatr</source>
<year>1991</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>221–23</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagpal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Unusual hepatic manifestations in typhoid fever</article-title>. <source>J Assoc Physicians India</source>
<year>1991</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>390–91</fpage>.1720434
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Newihi</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alamy</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Salmonella hepatitis: analysis of 27 cases and comparison with acute viral hepatitis</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>516–19</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8781316</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.510240308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaarthigeyan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Serum ALT: LDH ratio in typhoid fever and acute viral hepatitis</article-title>. <source>Indian Pediatr</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>339–41</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19671947</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13312-010-0064-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pramoolsinsap</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Viranuvatti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Salmonella hepatitis</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>1998</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>745–50</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9715430</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1746.1998.tb00726.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Suri</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rishi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Contribution of typhoid toxin in the pathogenesis of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella Typhi</italic></article-title>. <source>Microb Pathog</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>164</volume>:<fpage>105444</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35149176</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2022.105444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khosla</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Typhoid hepatitis</article-title>. <source>Postgrad Med J</source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>923–25</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2267203</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/pgmj.66.781.923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2429755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ghotekar</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Atypical manifestations of typhoid fever</article-title>. <source>J Postgrad Med</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>248–51</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11832640</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A fast and highly sensitive blood culture PCR method for clinical detection of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhi</article-title>. <source>Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20403166</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-0711-9-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2873252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhutta</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current concepts in the diagnosis and treatment of typhoid fever</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>333</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16825230</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.333.7558.78</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1489205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Typhoid fever: clinical management of typhoid fever</article-title>. <source>Wkly Epidemiol Rec</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>33–40</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karkey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thwaites</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The evolution of antimicrobial resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella Typhi</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>25–30</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29059070</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOG.0000000000000406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Largman-Chalamish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Silberman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Differentiating between bacterial and viral infections by estimated CRP velocity</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e0277401</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36477474</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0277401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9728869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zavarache</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Neamtu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Falup-Pecurariu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of C-Reactive Protein with leukocytes and ESR for differentiation between bacterial and viral infections</article-title>. <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>A267</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagnier</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kienle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The CARE guidelines: consensus-based clinical case reporting guideline development</article-title>. <source>BMJ Case Rep</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>bcr2013201554</fpage>.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-1947-7-223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3844611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24228906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agha</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Transparency in the reporting of artificial intelligence – the TITAN guideline</article-title>. <source>Premier J Sci</source>
<year>2025</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>100082</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>