<article article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4" xml:lang="en"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">IDCases</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">IDCases</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2866</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">idcases</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>IDCases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2214-2509</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12828734</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12828734.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12828734</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12828734</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41585543</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idcr.2025.e02479</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2214-2509(25)00336-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e02479</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mycobacterium avium complex causing transverse pericardial sinus infection: A case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="T">Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">a</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">a</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">a</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuhan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0010">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhiyin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0015">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenyong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0020">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="N">Nana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0040"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names initials="H">Hangming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0045"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="W">Weizhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0050"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names initials="Y">Ying</given-names></name><email>nfyymengy@163.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">a</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">⁎</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>The Second School of Clinical Medicine, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Huiqiao Medical Center, Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China</aff><aff id="aff0020"><label>d</label>Department of Emergency Medicine, Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Correspondence to: Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University, No.1838 Guangzhou North Road, Guangzhou 510515, China. <email>nfyymengy@163.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntp0005">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>43</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503239</issue-id><elocation-id>e02479</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-26 15:25:12.620"><day>26</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2026 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref content-type="ccbyncndlicense" specific-use="textmining" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><abstract id="ab0010"><p>Nontuberculous mycobacteria (NTM) are increasingly recognized as significant opportunistic pathogens in humans, yet they remain rarely implicated in cardiac conditions. Here, we report a rare case of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium avium</italic> complex (MAC) infection in the transverse pericardial sinus, an unusual site previously undocumented for NTM infection. The patient, a 68-year-old male with prior cardiac surgery, presented with recurrent fever lasting for over 10 days. Positron emission tomography/computed tomography demonstrated a hypermetabolic mass-like lesion within the transverse pericardial sinus, radiologically suggestive of an infectious process. Empirical broad-spectrum antimicrobial therapy failed to achieve clinical response. Following surgical intervention to remove lesion tissue from the transverse pericardial sinus, histopathological analysis revealed granulomatous inflammation and acid-fast bacilli, indicating NTM infection. Metagenomic next-generation sequencing (mNGS) identified MAC in the tissue sample. After starting antimycobacterial therapy, the patient's body temperature gradually returned to normal, and no recurrence was noted during a 7-month follow-up via serial surveillance imaging. This case suggests that, in patients with a history of cardiac surgery who present with unexplained pericardial or mediastinal lesions and non-diagnostic routine cultures and examinations, atypical pathogens such as NTM may warrant consideration within a broad differential diagnosis. It also illustrates the potential value of surgical intervention and mNGS in diagnosing and managing such rare infections.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium avium</italic> complex</kwd><kwd>Nontuberculous mycobacteria</kwd><kwd>Transverse pericardial sinus</kwd><kwd>Case report</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Nontuberculous mycobacteria (NTM) refer to mycobacterial species other than those belonging to the Mycobacterium tuberculosis complex and Mycobacterium leprae, which are omnipresent in the natural environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">[1]</xref>. They are increasingly thought as important opportunistic pathogens of humans, with <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium avium</italic> complex (MAC) being the most frequently isolated species, primarily represented by <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium avium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium intracellulare</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">[3]</xref>. MAC can cause pulmonary and extrapulmonary disease, with the respiratory system being most common and well-known site <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">[2]</xref>. Extrapulmonary diseases usually occur in immunosuppressed patients, commonly involving lymph nodes, skin, soft tissues, and musculoskeletal system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">[4]</xref>. NTM infections in cardiovascular system mostly occurred after cardiac surgery, which were mainly associated with the use of contaminated heater-cooler devices (HCDs) during cardiac surgery <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">[5]</xref>. These cases commonly suffered endocarditis, implanted prosthetic material infection or disseminated infection caused by <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium chimaera</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium abscessus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">[7]</xref>. Additionally, there have been a few reported cases of MAC pericarditis in immunocompetent individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">[8]</xref>. However, MAC infection in transverse pericardial sinus has not been reported. This case highlights the importance of considering atypical pathogens as NTM in patients with transverse pericardial sinus infection, particularly when traditional diagnostic methods fail to identify the causative organism.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="p0015">A 68-year-old man was admitted to our hospital for an over-10-day recurring fever (up to 38.3 °C), accompanied by chills and cough. He primarily experienced fevers in the afternoon and at night. He underwent aortic valve and ascending aortic replacement as well as pericardiectomy for aortic stenosis seven years ago. He had no history of hypertension, diabetes, immunodeficiency, or other significant medical comorbidities. He denied recent sick close contacts and travel. His vital signs on admission included a pulse rate of 95 beats/min, respiratory rate of 18 breaths/min, blood pressure of 120/76 mmHg, and temperature of 36.5°C. Auscultation found cardiac murmurs in the aortic valve area. No skin rashes were seen on inspection.</p><p id="p0020">Initial laboratory evaluation showed only mild inflammatory changes, with slightly elevated C-reactive protein (26.35 mg/L; reference range, 0.00–6.00 mg/L) and procalcitonin (0.256 ng/mL; reference value, &lt;0.05 ng/mL), and otherwise unremarkable infection markers. Sputum Gram stains, acid-fast stains and cultures, multiple blood cultures, 1–3-β-<sc>D</sc>-glucan and galactomannan (GM) were all negative. Tumor markers, an autoimmunity screening panel, and bone marrow examination revealed no significant abnormalities. Blood shotgun metagenomic next-generation sequencing (mNGS) revealed the presence of Epstein-Barr virus (EBV). Chest computed tomography showed scattered patchy shadows in both lungs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig0005">Fig. 1</xref>A). Transthoracic echocardiogram (TTE) showed no valvular vegetations, intracardiac masses, or pericardial effusion. Initially, empirical antimicrobial and antiviral agents, such as meropenem, doxycycline and baloxavir marboxil, were administered; however, the patient continued to experience fever. Due to the poor response to routine treatment and unclear diagnosis, the patient underwent whole-body positron emission tomography/computer tomography (PET/CT), revealing a mass mimicker in transverse pericardial sinus (adjacent to the posterior margin of the ascending aorta) with increased 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) uptake, suggestive of an infectious lesion, and patchy shadows with diffuse distribution in both lungs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig0005">Fig. 1</xref>D).<fig id="fig0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Selected relevant clinical data of the patient. (A) Initial lung computed tomography during hospitalization showed several scattered inflammatory lesions in both lungs. (B, C) Enhanced lung computed tomography during disease progression showed patchy shadows with diffuse distribution in both lungs, and lesions with increased density surrounding the ascending aorta (arrow). (D) The PET/CT revealed an increased 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose uptake adjacent to the posterior margin of the ascending aorta (arrow). (E, F) Lung computed tomography during follow-up showed a significant improvement in bilateral pneumonia, and a reduction in the size of lesions at the surgical site (arrow). (G) Intraoperative view showed abundant caseous material within the transverse pericardial sinus (circle). (H, I) The results of pathological examination. H&amp;E staining showed granulomatous inflammation with coagulative necrosis. Acid-fast staining found acid-fast bacilli (arrow).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic id="lk0005" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="gr1.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></p><p id="p0025">Therefore, infectious disorders became the most likely diagnosis, however, deserving a microbiological diagnosis as well. At first, a minimally invasive approach was attempted by a bronchoscopy; mNGS identified EBV, pneumocystis jirovecii, gram-positive bacteria in the bronchoalveolar lavage fluid. Despite the antibiotic agents were switched to piperacillin/tazobactam, vancomycin, doxycycline, trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole (TMP-SMZ), caspofungin and baloxavir marboxil, the patient still had recurrent fever with an increase in the highest temperature, and the condition progressed to severe pneumonia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig0005">Fig. 1</xref>B, C), accompanied by type I respiratory failure and shock.</p><p id="p0030">Ultimately, an open-chest surgery with excision of the lesion was performed, revealing abundant caseous material within the transverse pericardial sinus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig0005">Fig. 1</xref>G). Histology showed granulomatous inflammation with coagulative necrosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig0005">Fig. 1</xref>H). Acid-fast staining of the surgical specimens showed acid-fast bacilli (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig0005">Fig. 1</xref>I). Furthermore, surgical specimens were subjected to mNGS twice, revealing the presence of MAC and <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium avium</italic> respectively, as indicated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl0005">Table 1</xref>. As conventional culture-based molecular speciation was not available at our institution, a portion of the resected tissue was sent to a regional reference mycobacteriology laboratory for NTM culture and drug-susceptibility testing. Before these culture and susceptibility results became available, empiric antimycobacterial therapy with amikacin, azithromycin, ethambutol and rifampin had been initiated on the basis of histopathology and tissue mNGS. After prolonged incubation, culture from this specimen yielded MAC, and the treatment regimen was subsequently adjusted in accordance with the susceptibility pattern. After receiving treatment, the patient's body temperature gradually returned to normal. Two months after initiation of anti-MAC treatment, the follow-up computed tomography showed a significant improvement in bilateral pneumonia, and an obvious reduction in the size of lesions in the transverse pericardial sinus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig0005">Fig. 1</xref>E, F). No signs of recurrence were observed during the seven-month follow-up. However, anti-mycobacterial therapy was discontinued seven months later due to drug-induced liver injury, and regrettably the patient did not return for regular scheduled follow-up.<table-wrap id="tbl0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Results of mNGS in surgical specimen of patient.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0010">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genus Type</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Name</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequence number</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Species name</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sequence number</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">G<sup>+</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium</italic></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium avium</italic></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">G<sup>+</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium</italic></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">667</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium avium complex</italic></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">188</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>mNGS = metagenomic next-generation sequencing (MGISEQ 2000 Platform).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0015"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0035">Cardiovascular NTM infections are increasingly reported and usually manifests as endocarditis, pericarditis, or prosthetic-device infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">[11]</xref>. This case presents a unique instance of MAC infection within the transverse pericardial sinus, an area not previously documented in the literature.</p><p id="p0040">The patient presented with over ten days of recurring fever, chills, and cough, with no identifiable source of infection through traditional diagnostic methods such as sputum cultures, blood cultures, and imaging. The initial investigation suggested a viral etiology due to the detection of EBV through mNGS. However, the persistent fever and respiratory symptoms, coupled with the inconclusive results of various empirical treatments, prompted further investigation into possible infectious causes, leading to the discovery of an infectious lesion in the transverse pericardial sinus.</p><p id="p0045">Notably, the PET/CT scan provided crucial insights in this case, identifying an underlying infectious site of transverse pericardial sinus. Such imaging techniques are also invaluable for guiding further invasive diagnostics. PET/CT imaging characteristics in NTM cardiovascular infections are diverse. Nearly all cases had elevated metabolic activity and 18F-FDG uptake at the infectious sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">[12]</xref>. Soft tissue thickening, sinus tract formation, peristernal/perigraft fluid collections and osteolysis were considered as the most common imaging features of localized infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">[12]</xref>. Isolated mass-like lesions within transverse pericardial sinus as in this case are rare.</p><p id="p0050">The utilization of mNGS also proved pivotal in this case, enabling the identification of atypical pathogens that traditional methods failed to reveal. The diagnosis of MAC infection was confirmed through histological examination and mNGS of surgical specimens, underscoring the importance of advanced diagnostic techniques in cases with atypical presentations.</p><p id="p0055">This case underscores the potential risk of NTM infections in patients who have undergone cardiac surgery, particularly those who have been exposed to contaminated HCDs, known reservoirs for <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium chimaera</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium abscessus</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">[6]</xref>. While these species are often associated with endocarditis and prosthetic infections, the identification of MAC in this case suggests that it may also pose a risk for localized infections in areas such as the transverse pericardial sinus.</p><p id="p0060">After surgical intervention and identification of MAC as the causative agent, the patient was placed on a targeted antimycobacterial therapy regimen. The initiation of treatment led to a significant clinical improvement, reflected in the normalization of body temperature and the reduction of lesions in subsequent imaging studies. This outcome reinforces the necessity of prompt and accurate identification of NTM infections to facilitate timely and appropriate therapy. Meanwhile, surgical intervention should be considered in patients with localized lesion.</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0065">In conclusion, this case illustrates that NTM can present with a localized infection of the transverse pericardial sinus after cardiac surgery and may manifest primarily with non-specific systemic symptoms. In such situations, comprehensive diagnostic strategies that combine advanced imaging, histopathology, and, where feasible, surgical sampling with mNGS test can be valuable for establishing an etiologic diagnosis and guiding targeted antimicrobial therapy. Given increasing prevalence of NTM in post-surgical settings, maintaining high clinical suspicion is essential. Further studies are warranted to better understand the risk factors, clinical manifestations, and optimal management strategies for this population.</p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><title>Author agreement</title><p id="p0070">All authors meet the authorship criteria and have contributed through study design, data analysis, drafting, or critical revision. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0075"><bold>Ting Li:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Resources, Investigation, Data curation. <bold>Qi Wang:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Writing – original draft, Formal analysis, Conceptualization. <bold>Yuying Lin:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Visualization, Resources, Investigation, Data curation. <bold>Yuhan Li:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Visualization, Data curation. <bold>Zhiyin Luo:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Visualization, Investigation. <bold>Wenyong Zhang:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Investigation, Data curation. <bold>Nana Sun:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Investigation, Data curation. <bold>Hangming Dong:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Conceptualization. <bold>Weizhen Zhang:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Conceptualization. <bold>Ying Meng:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Visualization, Resources, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec id="sec0035"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="p0080">The study was designed and conducted following the Helsinki Declaration and the ethical standards of the responsible committee on human experimentation. Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and</p><p id="p0085">accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal on request.</p></sec><sec id="sec0040"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0090">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="spnsr1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (<award-id award-type="grant" rid="spnsr1">82270089</award-id>, <award-id award-type="grant" rid="spnsr1">82070063</award-id>, <award-id award-type="grant" rid="spnsr1">81900066</award-id>), <funding-source id="spnsr2">National College</funding-source> Students’ Innovation and Entrepreneurship Training Program (<award-id award-type="grant" rid="spnsr2">202312121006</award-id>), Southern Medical University <funding-source id="spnsr3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100010112</institution-id><institution>Nanfang Hospital</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> Education Research (<award-id award-type="grant" rid="spnsr3">22NJ-YB03</award-id>), <funding-source id="spnsr4">Guangzhou Science and Technology Plan Project</funding-source> (<award-id award-type="grant" rid="spnsr4">202201010990</award-id>), Clinical Research Special Project of Nanfang Hospital (<award-id award-type="grant" rid="spnsr3">2024CR016</award-id>), Directed Project of Ganzhou Hospital of Nanfang Hospital, <funding-source id="spnsr5"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100010096</institution-id><institution>Southern Medical University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>-Science and Technology Innovation Talent Project-Young Talent Project (<award-id award-type="grant" rid="spnsr5">GZ2024YLJ029</award-id>) and Science and Technology Plan Project of the <funding-source id="spnsr6">Jiangxi Provincial Administration of Traditional Chinese Medicine</funding-source> (<award-id award-type="grant" rid="spnsr6">2024B0416</award-id>).</p></sec><sec id="coi0005" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="p0095">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibliog0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation id="sbref1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loebinger</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nontuberculous mycobacterial pulmonary disease: clinical epidemiologic features, risk factors, and diagnosis: the nontuberculous mycobacterial series</article-title><source>Chest</source><volume>161</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2021.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34627854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation id="sbref2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycobacterium avium Complex Disease</article-title><source>Microbiol Spectr</source><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.TNMI7-0045-2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28429679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation id="sbref3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>V.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mølhave</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fløe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Ingen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schön</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillebaek</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global trends of pulmonary infections with nontuberculous mycobacteria: a systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><volume>125</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2022.10.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36244600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation id="sbref4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiselinova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naesens</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huis</surname><given-names>I.T.V.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boelens</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Braeckel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vande</surname><given-names>W.Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>management challenges of extrapulmonary nontuberculous mycobacterial infection: a single-center case series and literature review</article-title><source>Pathogens</source><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens13010012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10819148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38276158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation id="sbref5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Ingen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kranzer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasse</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katarzyna</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global outbreak of severe Mycobacterium chimaera disease after cardiac surgery: a molecular epidemiological study</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>17</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30324-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28711585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation id="sbref6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wetzstein</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diricks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mas-Peiro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holubec</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics and outcome of Mycobacterium chimaera infections after cardiac surgery: systematic review and meta-analysis of 180 heater-cooler unit-associated cases</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><volume>29</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1008</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2023.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36918144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation id="sbref7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedland</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maziarz</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milano</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology, management, and clinical outcomes of extrapulmonary Mycobacterium abscessus complex infections in heart transplant and ventricular assist device recipients</article-title><source>Am J Transpl</source><volume>23</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1048</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajt.2023.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10330292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37059177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation id="sbref8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haemorrhagic Mycobacterium avium complex pericarditis presenting with cardiac tamponade in an immunocompetent woman</article-title><source>BMJ Case Rep</source><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bcr-2023-255237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10335403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37407234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation id="sbref9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Case Report: Mycobacterium kansasii causing infective endocarditis explored by metagenomic next-generation sequencing</article-title><source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source><volume>13</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1227537</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2023.1227537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10482420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37680745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation id="sbref10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jinah</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibbald</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Case of Pericarditis and Pericardial Masses Associated with Mycobacterium Paragordonae</article-title><source>Clin Med Insights Cardiol</source><volume>17</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>1977688623</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/11795468231189039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10460162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37637260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation id="sbref11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shabi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haldane</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycobacterium fortuitum pacemaker infection: A case report</article-title><source>J Assoc Med Microbiol Infect Dis Can</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3138/jammi-2021-0003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36340848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9603015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation id="sbref12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shorey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velagapudi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>radiologic manifestations of Mycobacterium Chimaera infection after open heart surgery</article-title><source>J Thorac Imaging</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/RTI.0000000000000779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38662632</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="da0005" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0005">The datasets generated and analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0100">The authors thank Dr. Haiping Dong (The second tuberculosis department, Guangzhou Chest Hospital, Guangzhou, China) for her invaluable help in providing information from the Guangzhou Chest Hospital. We also appreciate Dr. Bihong Xu (Department of Pathology, Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China) for giving expert guidance in pathological diagnosis.</p></ack></back></article>