<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4" xml:lang="en"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12800040</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12800040.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12800040</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12800040</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41526406</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-31085-z</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">31085</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Potent LeuBAT inhibitors designed in silico as next-generation duloxetine analogs for enhanced major depressive disorder treatment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoosefian</surname><given-names initials="M">Mehdi</given-names></name><address><email>myoosefian7@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayramzadeh</surname><given-names initials="H">Hedieh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abass</surname><given-names initials="KS">Kasim Sakran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mokhtari</surname><given-names initials="T">Tahmineh</given-names></name><address><email>tmokhtari@ucdavis.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0451xdy64</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.448905.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 4910 146X</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemistry, </institution><institution>Graduate University of Advanced Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Kerman, Iran </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01pk8rb11</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442850.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1788 6709</institution-id><institution>Department of Physiology, Biochemistry, and Pharmacology, College of Veterinary Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Kirkuk, </institution></institution-wrap>Kirkuk, 36001 Iraq </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05rrcem69</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27860.3b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9684</institution-id><institution>Department of Entomology and Nematology and UCD Comprehensive Cancer Center, </institution><institution>University of California, </institution></institution-wrap>Davis, CA USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503847</issue-id><elocation-id>1622</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-15 00:25:14.200"><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref content-type="ccbyncndlicense" specific-use="textmining" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41598_2025_Article_31085.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par9">Major Depressive Disorder (MDD), a leading global health challenge, urgently requires advanced therapeutics to mitigate its widespread impact. In this study, a series of duloxetine (DLX) analogs were designed and evaluated using a comprehensive in silico workflow incorporating quantum chemical calculations, ADMET profiling, molecular docking, and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations. Density Functional Theory (DFT) calculations at the B3LYP/6-311G level were performed to assess electronic properties such as the HOMO–LUMO energy gap, dipole moment, electronegativity, and chemical softness. Among the designed compounds, DLX48 demonstrated superior quantum descriptors while retaining the electronic characteristics of the parent molecule. ADMET predictions using ADMETlab 3.0 and ProTox-II revealed that DLX48 complies with major drug-likeness rules (Lipinski, Pfizer), exhibits improved aqueous solubility (Log S = − 3.21), optimal lipophilicity (Log <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 2.87), and shows no predicted hepatotoxicity or genotoxicity. Molecular docking against the LeuBAT (Δ13 mutant) transporter revealed a significant increase in binding affinity for DLX48 (–12.45 kcal/mol), with an inhibition constant (Ki) of 742.09 pM—indicating markedly enhanced target engagement compared to DLX. Long-timescale MD simulations (300 ns) confirmed the thermodynamic stability and favorable dynamic behavior of the DLX48–LeuBAT complex, supported by lower RMSD/RMSF values, persistent hydrogen bonding, reduced solvent exposure, and constrained conformational fluctuations. Collectively, these in silico findings nominate DLX48 as a promising central nervous system (CNS)-active lead compound with enhanced pharmacological efficacy and a reduced toxicity profile, warranting further preclinical investigation for the treatment of depression and anxiety disorders.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Duloxetine hydrochloride</kwd><kwd>Drug design</kwd><kwd>Molecular dynamics simulation</kwd><kwd>ADMET prediction</kwd><kwd>Serotonin and noradrenaline reuptake inhibitors</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Chemistry</kwd><kwd>Computational biology and bioinformatics</kwd><kwd>Drug discovery</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Nature Limited 2026</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par10">Major depressive disorder (MDD) is one of the most prevalent and debilitating psychiatric disorders worldwide, contributing substantially to global disease burden and healthcare costs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Historically, therapeutic strategies in the 19th century relied on chemical agents such as ferrous iodide, arsenic, ergot alkaloids, and cinchona extracts, complemented by physical interventions including massage and hydrotherapy. Modern pharmacotherapy emerged in the mid‑20th century with the introduction of the first antidepressants around 1956<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Current treatment options primarily consist of tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs), and selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), alongside serotonin–norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">Among SNRIs, duloxetine (DLX) has gained widespread use due to its efficacy in treating MDD, neuropathic pain, and generalized anxiety disorder. Although DLX targets both serotonin (SERT) and norepinephrine transporters (NET), it exhibits substantially higher affinity for SERT, potentially limiting its dual reuptake inhibition efficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Compared to TCAs, DLX and related SNRIs display reduced anticholinergic, antihistaminic, and α‑adrenergic adverse effects, contributing to improved tolerability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Since its FDA approval in 2004, DLX has been prescribed for various psychiatric and somatic conditions, including OCD, PTSD, social anxiety disorder, and panic disorder<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, DLX therapy is often associated with adverse outcomes such as serotonin syndrome, hepatotoxicity, manic switching, and increased suicidal ideation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par12">Hepatotoxicity remains a critical limitation of DLX, ranging from mild transaminase elevations to severe hepatic failure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Because DLX is primarily metabolized by CYP1A2 and CYP2D6, its toxicity profile is influenced by genetic polymorphisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, age, sex, and chronic alcohol consumption, which further induces CYP activity and oxidative stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. At the molecular level, its binding interactions are driven by hydrogen‑bond–accepting ether moieties and a secondary amine group, which modulate both receptor affinity and oral bioavailability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. However, poor aqueous solubility is one of DLX’s most significant drawbacks, often necessitating higher therapeutic doses that inadvertently increase toxicity risks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. To address these pharmacokinetic and safety limitations, in silico drug design has emerged as an efficient strategy enabling rapid optimization of lead structures before experimental validation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Recent computational studies have demonstrated the utility of integrating cheminformatics, quantum chemical modeling, molecular docking, MD simulations, and ADMET prediction tools in rational drug development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Such multidisciplinary frameworks have been successfully applied to identify improved analogs in diverse therapeutic areas, including antiviral, antileishmanial, and antiparasitic agents.</p><p id="Par13">In this study, we adopted a comprehensive structure‑based drug design (SBDD) workflow to design and evaluate novel DLX analogs with improved solubility, reduced toxicity, and enhanced CNS activity. The LeuBAT (Δ13 mutant) transporter, a validated surrogate for human SERT and NET due to its conserved ligand‑binding architecture, was used as the structural template for interaction profiling. By integrating DFT‑based quantum chemical analysis, ADMET prediction, molecular docking, and 300‑ns MD simulations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, the study aims to identify optimized DLX analogs with superior stability, binding affinity, and pharmacokinetic performance for potential therapeutic advancement in MDD and related CNS disorders.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Ligand preparation</title><p id="Par14">The 2D structure of Duloxetine (DLX) was retrieved from the PubChem database (PubChem CID: 60835; Direct link: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/60835" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/60835</ext-link>). A series of DLX analogs were designed by manual structural modification using ChemDraw Professional. The generated 2D structures were then converted to 3D format by exporting them as PDB files and subsequently optimizing their geometries in GaussView 6.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Quantum mechanics calculations</title><p id="Par15">To investigate the structural, electronic, and reactivity-related properties of DLX and its analogs, quantum chemical calculations were carried out using the DFT method as implemented in the Gaussian 09 suite of programs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. A total of 14 analogs were initially designed based on structural modifications of DLX. Geometry optimizations for all compounds were conducted at the B3LYP/6-311G(d, p) level of theory. The hybrid B3LYP functional, combining Becke’s three-parameter exchange with the Lee–Yang–Parr correlation functional, has been extensively validated for predicting thermochemical, electronic, and structural properties of small to medium-sized organic molecules, particularly CNS-active drugs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. The 6-311G(d, p) basis set offers a good balance between computational cost and accuracy by including polarization functions on all atoms, which is essential for capturing noncovalent interactions and conformational flexibility critical in ligand–protein recognition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. This method has been employed successfully in previous studies involving antidepressants and neurotransmitter analogs to provide reliable frontier molecular orbital energies and global reactivity descriptors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Following geometry optimization, frontier molecular orbital (FMO) analysis was performed to calculate the highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) and lowest unoccupied molecular orbital (LUMO) energies. These values were subsequently used to derive key global reactivity descriptors, including: chemical hardness (η), chemical softness (S), electrophilicity index (ω), and chemical potential (µ). These parameters offer insights into molecular stability, electronic reactivity, and potential interactions with biological targets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. All calculations were performed under gas-phase conditions, assuming a default convergence criterion for energy and gradient thresholds as per Gaussian default protocols. The computed descriptors were used to compare electronic behavior across the designed compounds, with the goal of identifying analogs possessing optimal reactivity and stability for downstream docking and pharmacokinetic studies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Pharmacokinetic prediction and drug-likeness evaluation</title><p id="Par16">To assess the pharmacokinetic properties and drug-likeness of the designed DLX analogs, a comprehensive in silico screening was conducted using ADMETlab 3.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://admetlab3.scbdd.com/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://admetlab3.scbdd.com/</ext-link>), a robust AI-driven platform for predicting absorption, distribution, metabolism, excretion, and toxicity (ADMET) parameters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Key ADME-related features were evaluated, including blood–brain barrier (BBB) permeability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, P-glycoprotein (P-gp) substrate/inhibitor status, and plasma protein binding (PPB), offering insights into compound distribution and membrane transport potential. Metabolic stability was assessed by predicting each compound’s likelihood to inhibit or serve as a substrate for major cytochrome P450 (CYP450) isoenzymes, namely CYP1A2, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D6, and CYP3A4—a critical step in anticipating metabolic liabilities and potential drug–drug interactions. Solubility and lipophilicity were evaluated via predicted aqueous solubility (Log S) and partition coefficient (Log P), which serve as key indicators of oral bioavailability. ADMETlab 3.0 classifies these properties using ensemble machine learning models, aiding early-stage selection of compounds with optimal pharmacokinetic traits. Drug-likeness was further examined through medicinal chemistry filters, including Lipinski’s Rule of Five and the Pfizer rule, to evaluate structural compliance with orally active drug standards. For toxicity risk refinement, SMILES representations of each compound were submitted to ProTox-II (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tox.charite.de/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://tox.charite.de/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, which estimated the median lethal dose (LD₅₀), assigned toxicity classes (I–V) based on the Globally Harmonized System (GHS), and predicted organ-specific toxicity profiles—classifying compounds as <italic toggle="yes">Active</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Inactive</italic> for major organs such as the liver, kidneys, heart, and nervous system. This multi-parameter, integrative computational pipeline enabled the rational prioritization of DLX analogs with improved ADMET characteristics, minimized toxicity liabilities, and enhanced drug-likeness, forming a solid basis for their progression to subsequent molecular docking and dynamics simulations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Molecular docking studies</title><p id="Par17">Molecular docking was conducted to assess the binding affinity and interaction modes of Duloxetine (DLX) and its designed analogs with the LeuBAT (Δ13 mutant) transporter. The high-resolution crystal structure of LeuBAT complexed with DLX was retrieved from the Protein Data Bank (PDB ID: 4MM6) and used as the receptor model. The active site of the LeuBAT transporter was identified based on the co-crystallized duloxetine molecule in the 4MM6 structure. Visual inspection in PyMOL confirmed that the ligand occupies the conserved S1 substrate-binding pocket, previously described for NET homologs. Key pocket-forming residues—including Asp24, Tyr108, Ser254, and Phe259—were used to define the binding cavity and guide the positioning of the docking grid. Preprocessing steps included the removal of all crystallographic water molecules, ions, and co-crystallized ligands, followed by the addition of polar hydrogen atoms and Kollman charges using AutoDock Tools (v1.5.6)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. All ligands were pre-optimized using DFT (B3LYP/6-311G) and prepared in PDBQT format with flexible torsions enabled. Docking simulations were performed using AutoDock 4.2.6, applying the Lamarckian Genetic Algorithm (LGA) with the following parameters: a population size of 150, 200 GA runs, 2,500,000 energy evaluations, a mutation rate of 0.02, and default crossover and elitism settings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The grid box was carefully defined to encompass the known binding site of DLX within the LeuBAT pocket. Specifically, the grid center was set to coordinates X = 174.533, Y = − 12.594, Z = 180.481, and the grid dimensions were 40 × 40 × 40 points with a spacing of 0.375 Å. This provided a search volume large enough to allow the ligands to explore all relevant conformational spaces within the binding pocket<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Each docking run generated a ranked list of binding poses based on the predicted binding free energy (ΔG). The lowest-energy pose for each compound was selected for downstream interaction analysis using LigPlot+ (v2.2) to identify key hydrogen bonds and hydrophobic interactions, and PyMOL (v2.5) for visual inspection and structural alignment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. This docking protocol ensured reproducibility, specificity for the DLX-binding site, and a reliable basis for selecting candidate analogs for further MD simulations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Molecular dynamics studies</title><p id="Par18">To assess the dynamic stability and conformational behavior of the protein-ligand complexes, MD simulations were performed using the GROMACS 2022.4 package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>, employing the CHARMM36 all-atom force field for both bonded and non-bonded interactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. The initial protein-ligand complex structures were derived from the most favorable docking poses. Prior to simulation, the complexes were preprocessed by removing crystallographic water molecules, optimizing protonation states, and adding missing hydrogen atoms. The system was then embedded in a cubic simulation box with a minimum margin of 1.0 Å between the complex and the box edge. To model a realistic biological environment, the box was solvated using the explicit TIP3P water model, and counterions were added to neutralize the net system charge. Energy minimization was carried out using the steepest descent algorithm until the maximum force on any atom dropped below 1000 kJ/mol/nm, ensuring elimination of steric clashes and bad contacts. Subsequently, two equilibration steps were performed under periodic boundary conditions:</p><p id="Par19">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par20">NVT ensemble (constant number of particles, volume, and temperature): The system was gradually heated to 300 K using a V-rescale thermostat over 100 ps while restraining the heavy atoms.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par21">NPT ensemble (constant number of particles, pressure, and temperature): Pressure was equilibrated at 1 bar using the Parrinello–Rahman barostat, also for 100 ps<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par22">After equilibration, an unrestrained production MD run was conducted for 300 ns with a 2-fs time step. Long-range electrostatic interactions were treated using the Particle Mesh Ewald (PME) method, and LINCS constraints were applied to all covalent bonds involving hydrogen atoms. Trajectory snapshots were saved every 10 ps for subsequent analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Quantum mechanical analysis</title><p id="Par23">The optimized geometries of DLX (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab1">1</xref>) and its designed analogs, along with their calculated electronic energy levels and dipole moments, are presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab2">2</xref>. Notably, DLX48 exhibited a more favorable total electronic energy and a higher dipole moment compared to the parent compound, suggesting improved molecular polarity. The observed narrowing of the HOMO–LUMO energy gap, combined with improvements in orbital distribution, suggests enhanced potential for target binding—an essential feature for drug–target interaction efficiency. These modifications directly impact molecular stability, reactivity, biological activity, and intramolecular charge transfer behavior. DLX48 demonstrated a HOMO–LUMO energy gap (Eg) of 4.81 eV, identical to that of the parent compound DLX, confirming that the core electronic characteristics of the reference structure are preserved (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1</xref>). Despite this electronic similarity, subtle variations in softness (S), hardness (η), Electrophilicity Index (ω), and chemical potential (µ) point to similar molecular flexibility and binding adaptability in DLX48 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab3">3</xref>). These parameters reflect a well-balanced electronic profile, potentially leading to more favorable interactions with biological targets. Furthermore, molecular electrostatic potential (MEP) mapping indicated that DLX48 exhibits a more favorable electrostatic distribution than DLX. The MEP contour plots (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig1">1</xref>) reveal broader regions of negative potential around electronegative atoms, which may facilitate stronger electrostatic interactions and hydrogen bonding within the binding site. Such characteristics are associated with increased binding affinity and specificity, supporting DLX48’s promise as a viable drug candidate. In summary, the quantum mechanical properties of DLX48 validate its structural integrity and suggest that the analog not only retains the desirable features of DLX but may also offer improved interaction profiles and pharmacological performance due to its optimized electronic configuration.</p><p id="Par24">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>General scaffold of DLX and structural variations introduced at R1 and R2 positions for the design of novel analogs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Structure</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e488" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figa_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Compounds</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> R1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> R2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DLX</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NH-C = NH-NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH2-NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH2-NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH2-CH2-NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH-OH-NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NH-CH2-CH2-OH</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NH-CH-OH–NH-NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CF3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH2-C–CH3–CH3-O-CH3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N = N-NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH = N-NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O-C = N</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NH-C = NH = NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N-CH3-CH3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-OH-CH3-CH3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C = O-NH2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH-OH-NH2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par25">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Optimized 3D molecular structures, total electronic energy (in Hartree) and dipole moment (in Debye) of DLX and its analogs, calculated at the B3LYP/6-311G(d, p) level using Gaussian 09.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Compounds</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total energy</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dipole moment</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Structure</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DLX</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1225.45</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e660" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figb_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx47</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1320.10</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e673" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figc_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx48</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1449.51</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e686" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figd_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx49</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1390.27</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e699" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fige_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx29</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1429.58</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e712" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figf_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx23</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1395.33</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e725" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figg_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx41</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1562.52</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e738" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figh_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx39</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1497.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e751" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figi_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx37</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1390.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e764" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figj_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx32</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1374.21</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e777" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figk_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx27</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1418.60</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e790" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figl_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx28</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1359.38</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e804" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figm_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx25</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1280.80</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e817" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fign_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx46</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1320.10</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e830" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figo_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par26">
<fig id="Fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Molecular electrostatic potential (MEP) maps and frontier molecular orbital diagrams (HOMO and LUMO) of duloxetine (Dlx) and selected designed analogs. Red regions indicate areas of high electron density (nucleophilic potential), blue regions represent electron-deficient zones (electrophilic potential), and yellow/green regions correspond to neutral or less reactive surfaces.</p></caption><graphic id="d33e841" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fig1a_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><graphic id="d33e842" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fig1b_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><graphic id="d33e843" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fig1c_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><graphic id="d33e844" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fig1d_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par27">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Quantum chemical descriptors of DLX and its analogs, including EHOMO, ELUMO, Eg, µ(eV), η(eV), S(eV<sup>− 1</sup>), and ω, calculated to assess molecular stability and reactivity.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Compounds</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E<sub>HOMO</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E<sub>LUMO</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Eg</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">µ(eV)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">η(eV)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">S(eV<sup>− 1</sup>)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ω</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.7</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.92</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.81</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.32</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.40</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx49</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−10.5</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.63</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.87</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−8.06</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx48</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.68</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.87</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.81</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.27</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.40</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx47</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.38</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.84</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.54</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.11</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.27</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx46</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.68</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.92</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.76</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.30</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx29</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.63</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.97</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.66</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.30</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.33</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx23</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.65</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.78</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.87</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.21</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx42</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.63</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.76</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.87</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.19</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx41</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.79</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.92</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.87</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.35</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx39</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.33</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.97</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.36</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.15</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.18</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx37</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.82</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.97</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.85</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.39</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.42</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx32</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.54</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.81</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.73</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.17</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.36</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx28</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.54</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.87</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.67</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.33</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx27</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.73</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.89</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.84</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.31</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.42</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx25</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.65</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.78</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.87</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.21</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.12</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>ADMET prediction</title><p id="Par28">To comprehensively assess the pharmacokinetic, physicochemical, and toxicological profiles of DLX and its designed analogs, a multi-parametric in silico evaluation was performed using ADMETlab 3.0 and ProTox-II. These platforms facilitate early-stage drug discovery by predicting key ADME/T properties, enabling the selection of compounds with enhanced bioavailability, reduced toxicity, and favorable drug-likeness—thus minimizing attrition rates during preclinical and clinical development. All designed analogs were evaluated against established drug-likeness filters, including Lipinski’s Rule of Five and the Pfizer rule, in addition to core molecular descriptors such as log P (lipophilicity), log S (aqueous solubility), and molecular weight (MW) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab4">4</xref>). Among these, DLX48 emerged as the most promising candidate, meeting both drug-likeness rules, and exhibiting a balanced physicochemical profile. With a log P of 2.88, DLX48 falls within the optimal range for oral drug absorption, indicating good membrane permeability without exceeding hydrophobicity thresholds. Furthermore, DLX48 demonstrated enhanced solubility compared to the parent compound, with a log S of − 3.21 versus − 3.70 for DLX, implying improved dissolution and bioavailability potential. Its molecular weight (312.43 Da) lies well within the recommended range for drug-like molecules, reinforcing its suitability for oral administration. Beyond its physicochemical advantages, DLX48 also displayed superior ADME characteristics (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab5">5</xref>). It exhibited high plasma protein binding (PPB: 97.6%) and retained the ability to cross the blood–brain barrier (BBB), a critical feature for CNS therapeutics (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab5">5</xref>). Unlike DLX, which inhibits P-glycoprotein (P-gp), DLX48 was identified as a strong substrate (+++) but not an inhibitor, suggesting it can be transported without disrupting efflux mechanisms, thereby reducing the risk of transporter-related drug interactions. In terms of excretion, DLX48 showed a moderate plasma clearance rate (5.82 mL/min/kg) and a shorter half-life (T<sub>1/2</sub> = 0.48 h) compared to DLX (0.69 h), indicating faster systemic elimination, which may reduce the potential for bioaccumulation and long-term toxicity. Metabolic profiling revealed a distinct advantage for DLX48. While DLX strongly inhibited several key cytochrome P450 isoforms (CYP1A2, CYP2C19, CYP2C9, and CYP2D6), DLX48 exhibited only weak to moderate inhibition toward CYP1A2 (+) and CYP2C19 (++), and showed no significant interaction with CYP2C9, CYP2D6, or CYP3A4 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab5">5</xref>). This suggests a lower likelihood of drug–drug interactions, enhancing its clinical safety profile. Toxicity analysis using ProTox-II further confirmed the favorable safety attributes of DLX48 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab6">6</xref>). Both DLX and DLX48 were classified under toxicity class 4, with an estimated LD₅₀ of 1800 mg/kg, indicating low acute oral toxicity. Crucially, DLX48 was predicted to be inactive across all major toxicity endpoints, including hepatotoxicity, carcinogenicity, immunotoxicity, mutagenicity, and cytotoxicity—comparable to DLX, but without any signs of additional risk introduced by structural modification. Taken together, these findings highlight DLX48 as a pharmacologically enhanced and toxicologically safe analog of DLX, featuring improved bioavailability, reduced interaction with metabolic enzymes, efficient CNS penetration, and a benign toxicity profile. These properties support its potential as a superior candidate for further preclinical development as a CNS-active therapeutic agent.</p><p id="Par29">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of key drug − likeness parameters for DLX and its analog Dlx47, including compliance with Lipinski and Pfizer rules, lipophilicity (log P), solubility (log S), molecular weight (MW), and 2D chemical structures.</p></caption><graphic id="d33e1178" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Tab4a_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><graphic id="d33e1180" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Tab4b_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par30">
<table-wrap id="Tab5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Predicted ADME and metabolism profiles of DLX and its structural analogs, including blood–brain barrier (BBB) permeability, plasma protein binding (PPB), P-glycoprotein (Pgp) interaction, plasma clearance (Cl), elimination half-life (T<sub>1/2</sub>), and cytochrome P450 enzyme Inhibition profiles. Data were generated using admetlab 3.0.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Distribution</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Absorption</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Excretion</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BBB</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPB</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pgp substrate</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pgp inhibitors</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cl plasma</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">T<sub>1/2</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DLX</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90.4%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.21</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88.7%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.74</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.9%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.40</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.82</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.93</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.93</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96.9%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.15</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96.9%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.75</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.1%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.22</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.9%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.38</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.4%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.26</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.2%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.98</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.8%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.49</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.1%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.46</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90.9%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.02</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.63</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Metabolism</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP1A2 inhibitor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2C19 inhibitor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2C9 inhibitor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2D6 inhibitor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP3A4 inhibitor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2B6 inhibitor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CYP2C8 inhibitor</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DLX</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">---</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">+++</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par31">
<table-wrap id="Tab6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Predicted toxicity profiles of DLX and its analogs based on ProTox-II analysis, including toxicity class, estimated oral LD₅₀ (mg/kg), and organ-specific toxicities: hepatotoxicity, carcinogenicity, immunotoxicity, mutagenicity, and cytotoxicity.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Toxicity class</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LD50 mg/kg</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hepatotoxicity</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Carcinogenicity</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Immunotoxicity</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mutagenicity</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cytotoxicity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DLX</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx46</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx47</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx48</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx49</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">2050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx29</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx23</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx42</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx41</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx39</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1625</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx37</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx32</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1190</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx28</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Active</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx27</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">220</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx25</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx23</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">1800</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inactive</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Molecular docking simulations</title><p id="Par32">Molecular docking analyses were performed to evaluate the binding affinity and interaction patterns of DLX and its structural analogs toward the LeuBAT (Δ13 mutant) transporter. Among all candidates, DLX48 demonstrated the most favorable docking performance, indicating substantial improvement in ligand–receptor interactions compared to the parent compound. Quantitative docking results revealed a binding energy (BE) of − 12.45 kcal/mol for DLX48, compared to − 9.43 kcal/mol for DLX, representing approximately a 32% enhancement in binding affinity (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab7">7</xref>). Additionally, DLX48 exhibited a remarkably lower inhibition constant (Ki) of 742.09 pM, compared to 121.98 nM for DLX, indicating a 164-fold increase in predicted potency. A corresponding improvement was also observed in intermolecular energy (IE) values (–14.84 kcal/mol for DLX48 vs. − 11.22 kcal/mol for DLX), confirming stronger non-bonded interactions within the active site. Detailed interaction mapping revealed that DLX48 formed an extensive network of stabilizing contacts within the LeuBAT binding pocket. Key residues involved in hydrophobic and polar interactions include Val104, Phe253, Phe259, Tyr108, Tyr21, Asp24, Ser355, Gly359, Pro101, Val261, Ser356, and Ala105, which contribute to van der Waals stabilization and π–π stacking. Most notably, DLX48 established strong hydrogen bonds with Ala22 (2.70 Å and 3.07 Å) and Ser254 (2.73 Å) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tab7">7</xref>). In contrast, DLX exhibited a less complex interaction network and notably lacked hydrogen bonding interactions, which are critical for stabilizing high-affinity ligand–receptor complexes. The binding was predominantly mediated through van der Waals and hydrophobic interactions with surrounding residues, including Tyr107, Val104, Thr408, Ser355, Tyr108, Val261, Pro101, Ser356, Ala105, Gly359, Tyr21, Phe259, Ala22, Asp24, Ser254, Gly256, and Phe253. Despite engaging a broad range of residues, the absence of strong polar contacts and hydrogen bonds likely limited the overall binding strength and specificity. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig2">2</xref>, three‑dimensional visualization using PyMOL, confirmed the spatial orientation of DLX48 within the active site and clearly illustrated the formation of stabilizing hydrogen bonds as well as close‑range hydrophobic contacts with key residues, consistent with the interaction pattern observed for the parent drug. This comparatively sparse and less optimized interaction landscape may underlie the lower binding affinity of DLX, relative to more structurally refined analogs such as DLX48. The increased interaction density and structural complementarity of DLX48 within the binding cavity suggest improved conformational fitting and target selectivity, which may translate into enhanced therapeutic efficacy at lower doses, thereby reducing the risk of systemic side effects.</p><p id="Par33">
<table-wrap id="Tab7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Binding affinity and molecular interaction parameters of DLX and its designed analogs docked to the LeuBAT (Δ13 mutant) transporter.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BE</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IE</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hydrogen bond</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bond length (Å)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Structure</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DLX</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−9.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121.98 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−11.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2113" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figae_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx46</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">725.58 pM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−15.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tyr21(A)</p><p>Ala22(A)</p><p>Ser254(A)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.69</p><p>2.96</p><p>2.67</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2136" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figaf_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx47</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−11.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.95 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13.72</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asp24(A)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2155" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figag_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx48</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">742.09 pM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−14.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Ala22(A)</p><p>Ala22(A)</p><p>Ser254(A)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.7</p><p>3.07</p><p>2.73</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2178" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figah_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx49</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−11.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.26 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13.88</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Phe253(A)</p><p>Ala22(A)</p><p>Tyr21(A)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.99</p><p>2.79</p><p>2.65</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2201" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figai_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx29</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−11.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.68 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−11.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Asp24(A)</p><p>Asp24(A)</p><p>Ala22(A)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.70</p><p>2.54</p><p>3.05</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2224" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figaj_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx23</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−11.55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.22nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−11.40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Phe253(A)</p><p>Asp24(A)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.70</p><p>2.50</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2245" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figak_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx42</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−10.25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.79 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tyr107(A)</p><p>Asp404(A)</p><p>Asp404(A)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.06</p><p>2.66</p><p>2.84</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2268" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figal_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx41</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−9.48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112.23 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−11.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tyr107(A)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2287" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figam_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx39</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−10.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.57 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2304" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figan_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx37</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−10.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.31 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tyr107(A)</p><p>Asp404(A)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.79</p><p>2.94</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2325" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figao_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx32</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−10.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.64 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tyr107(A)</p><p>Asp404(A)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.66</p><p>2.66</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2347" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figap_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx28</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−9.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.07 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−11.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2366" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figaq_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx27</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−10.87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.77 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−13.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tyr21(A)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2385" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figar_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dlx25</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−10.28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.17 nM</td><td align="char" char="." colspan="1" rowspan="1">−12.37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Tyr107(A)</p><p>Tyr21(A)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.40</p><p>3.03</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-graphic id="d33e2406" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Figas_HTML.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par34">
<fig id="Fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of binding interactions of the parent drug duloxetine (DLX) and the designed analog DLX48 within the LeuBAT (Δ13) transporter active site, visualized using PyMOL. (Left) DLX establishes predominantly hydrophobic interactions with key pocket residues, including Val104, Ala105, Phe259, Tyr108, and Val261, with interaction distances ranging from 3.3–3.9 Å, indicating van der Waals–dominated stabilization. (Right) DLX48 forms multiple strong hydrogen bonds with essential residues within the binding site—most notably Ala22 (2.30 and 2.68 Å) and Ser254 (2.73 Å)—demonstrating improved polar complementarity and enhanced binding specificity compared to DLX.</p></caption><graphic id="d33e2417" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fig2_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Molecular dynamic simulations</title><p id="Par35">To gain deeper insight into the conformational flexibility, structural stability, and long-term interaction dynamics of the ligand–receptor complexes, all-atom MD simulations were conducted for both DLX and its optimized analog DLX48 in complex with the LeuBAT (Δ13 mutant) transporter. Each system was simulated for a 300 ns production run in an explicitly solvated environment using the TIP3P water model under periodic boundary conditions. These extended simulations were designed to capture the dynamic evolution of the complexes over time, allowing for the assessment of key parameters such as binding persistence, structural adaptability, and energy stability under near-physiological conditions. This approach offers a more comprehensive and realistic evaluation of ligand behavior compared to static docking analyses alone.</p><sec id="Sec13"><title>System stabilize</title><p id="Par36">To evaluate the stability and reliability of the MD simulations, the total energy and potential energy profiles of the protein–ligand complexes were monitored over a 300 ns production run (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref>). These energy parameters are essential indicators of system equilibration and physical stability under simulated physiological conditions. As illustrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref>A, the total energy of both the DLX and DLX48 complexes remained relatively stable throughout the trajectory, with only minor fluctuations observed. The DLX48 complex exhibited slightly lower average total energy values, indicative of a more energetically favorable and compact system configuration.</p><p id="Par37">
<fig id="Fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Energy profile analyses from molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of the Duloxetine (DLX) and Dlx48 complexes with LeuBAT over 300 ns. (<bold>A</bold>) Total energy plot showing consistent energetic stability throughout the simulation for both systems, (<bold>B</bold>) Potential energy plot indicating improved thermodynamic favorability and enhanced system stability in the Dlx48 (red) complex relative to the parent DLX (black).</p></caption><graphic id="d33e2448" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fig3_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par38">Similarly, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig3">3</xref>B shows the potential energy profile across the same simulation period. The DLX48 complex consistently demonstrated lower potential energy values than the parent compound, reflecting stronger internal interactions and improved system stabilization. These findings suggest that DLX48 forms a more energetically stable complex with the LeuBAT transporter, likely due to enhanced non-covalent interactions observed in docking analysis.</p><p id="Par39">Overall, the absence of significant energy drifts in both total and potential energy plots confirms that the MD simulations for both systems reached equilibrium and maintained structural integrity over time. This energetic stability supports the robustness of subsequent dynamic and structural analyses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>RMSD analysis</title><p id="Par40">To evaluate the conformational stability of the protein–ligand complexes during the MD simulations, the root mean square deviation (RMSD) of the Cα atoms of LeuBAT was monitored over a 300 ns trajectory for both the parent compound (DLX) and its optimized analog (DLX48) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>A). Both complexes reached equilibration within the first ~ 25 ns, after which the RMSD trajectories stabilized, indicating that no major structural perturbations occurred during the simulation period. Notably, the DLX48–LeuBAT complex displayed a lower and more uniform RMSD profile, maintaining average values between 0.23 and 0.25 nm, with minimal fluctuations throughout the simulation. In contrast, the DLX–LeuBAT complex showed slightly higher RMSD values, ranging from 0.26 to 0.30 nm, particularly exhibiting greater fluctuation after 200 ns. These observations suggest that DLX48 binding confers enhanced structural stability to the LeuBAT transporter compared to DLX. The reduced atomic deviations and narrower RMSD range for DLX48 likely reflect its improved geometric complementarity and stronger intermolecular interactions within the binding site, as previously identified during docking. Overall, the lower RMSD values and reduced fluctuation amplitude of the DLX48-bound complex support its greater dynamic stability and structural integrity, reinforcing its potential as a more stable and efficacious candidate for therapeutic development.</p><p id="Par41">
<fig id="Fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Molecular dynamics analyses of the LeuBAT–ligand complexes over a 300 ns simulation. (<bold>A</bold>) RMSD profile representing the overall structural deviation of the protein backbone. (<bold>B</bold>) RMSF plot illustrating residue-level atomic fluctuations across the protein. (<bold>C</bold>) Center-of-mass distance between ligand and protein binding site. (<bold>D</bold>) Number of atomic contacts between the ligand and receptor over time. The black line represents DLX and the red line represents Dlx48 in all plots.</p></caption><graphic id="d33e2485" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fig4_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>RMSF analysis</title><p id="Par42">To further explore the local flexibility of protein residues in response to ligand binding, the root mean square fluctuation (RMSF) of the backbone atoms was computed for each residue in the LeuBAT transporter across the 300 ns MD simulation. RMSF provides a quantitative measure of atomic mobility and helps identify regions of structural flexibility or rigidity upon ligand interaction. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>B, both complexes—DLX–LeuBAT and DLX48–LeuBAT—exhibited a broadly similar fluctuation profile, indicating conserved structural dynamics throughout the majority of the protein. However, the DLX48-bound complex showed consistently lower RMSF values across several regions, particularly in flexible loop segments and binding site-adjacent residues. The most pronounced difference was observed near residues ~ 120–140, where DLX induced higher local fluctuations, suggesting reduced conformational restraint compared to DLX48. Notably, terminal regions (especially after residue 500) naturally displayed elevated fluctuations in both systems, a common feature of unstructured or solvent-exposed termini. Overall, the reduced local fluctuations in the DLX48 system suggest that this analog confers greater structural rigidity and stabilizing effects, particularly around the active site, thereby enhancing the overall stability of the complex. These findings support the notion that DLX48 not only maintains global stability (as seen in RMSD) but also minimizes local flexibility, which may contribute to its higher binding affinity and improved pharmacological profile.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Distance and contact analysis</title><p id="Par43">To further characterize the dynamic stability and persistence of ligand–protein interactions during the 300 ns MD simulation, two complementary metrics were examined: (i) the center-of-mass (COM) distance between the ligand and the active site residues of LeuBAT, and (ii) the total number of atomic contacts between the ligand and the surrounding protein residues (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>C and D, respectively). As depicted in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>C, DLX48 maintained a consistently lower and more stable COM distance relative to the DLX parent compound. The average COM distance for DLX48 was ~ 0.18 nm, exhibiting minimal fluctuations over the entire trajectory, whereas DLX fluctuated more widely, averaging ~ 0.21 nm. This tighter spatial anchoring of DLX48 within the binding cavity strongly suggests a more centralized and stable binding pose, indicative of higher binding affinity and reduced conformational drift. Such spatial retention is crucial for ensuring sustained engagement with key active-site residues and maintaining pharmacological potency during target engagement.</p><p id="Par44">In parallel, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig4">4</xref>D illustrates the temporal profile of atomic contacts between each ligand and the protein. DLX48 exhibited a markedly higher and more consistent number of contacts, ranging between 60 and 90 throughout the simulation, while DLX maintained a lower and more variable contact count (approximately 30–70). The enhanced contact persistence for DLX48 highlights the formation of a denser and more resilient interaction network, likely encompassing both hydrophobic and polar contacts across the LeuBAT binding pocket. This robust and sustained contact landscape not only contributes to the thermodynamic stabilization of the DLX48–LeuBAT complex but also correlates with the reduced local flexibility observed in RMSF analysis. Such interaction density is often linked to increased residence time and favorable kinetic binding properties, both of which are essential features for CNS-active ligands targeting neurotransmitter transporters. Together, these quantitative analyses underscore the superior binding characteristics of DLX48 over the parent compound. The tighter COM proximity and elevated contact frequency strongly support its enhanced structural and dynamic stability. These findings are consistent with its improved docking profile and reinforce its potential as a more efficacious therapeutic analog with favorable pharmacokinetic and binding properties.</p><p id="Par45">Hydrogen bond analysis</p><p id="Par46">Hydrogen bonding represents a fundamental non-covalent interaction critical for the stabilization and specificity of protein–ligand complexes. To evaluate the strength and persistence of polar interactions during the MD simulation, we quantified the number of hydrogen bonds formed between each ligand (DLX and DLX48) and the LeuBAT transporter over a 300 ns simulation period. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5</xref>A, the DLX48–LeuBAT complex consistently maintained a higher number of hydrogen bonds, with an average ranging between 2 and 3 H-bonds across the trajectory. These interactions were both temporally stable and spatially conserved, suggesting the establishment of strong and persistent polar contacts with key active site residues. Notably, DLX48 frequently engaged in hydrogen bonding with Ser254, Asp24, and Ser355, which are critically positioned within the binding cavity. These residues were also identified as primary interaction partners in the molecular docking stage, indicating a robust overlap between static (docking) and dynamic (MD) interaction profiles. In contrast, the DLX–LeuBAT complex exhibited a more transient and weaker hydrogen bonding pattern. Typically, only a single hydrogen bond was observed at any given time, with sporadic formation of secondary bonds that lacked persistence throughout the simulation. This suggests that DLX binds in a less optimal orientation and may suffer from reduced polar interaction potential compared to its analog. The enhanced hydrogen bonding profile of DLX48 reflects a more favorable conformational alignment and electrostatic complementarity with the binding pocket. Moreover, the continuity and multiplicity of these hydrogen bonds are indicative of an energetically stable complex, which supports the improved thermodynamic stability and binding affinity observed in prior analyses. Collectively, these results confirm that DLX48 achieves superior interaction strength, conformational retention, and binding site stabilization, reinforcing its potential as a promising lead compound with enhanced pharmacological characteristics.</p><p id="Par47">
<fig id="Fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>molecular dynamics analyses over a 300 ns simulation: (<bold>A</bold>) Time-dependent hydrogen bond analysis showing the number of protein–ligand hydrogen bonds. (<bold>B</bold>) Solvent Accessible Surface Area (SASA) illustrating the degree of solvent exposure of the complex. (<bold>C</bold>) Radius of Gyration (Rg) plot showing the conformational compactness and structural stability of the complexes. (<bold>D</bold>) Principal Component Analysis (PCA) projecting the motion of atoms along the first two eigenvectors to visualize dominant conformational changes. In all plots, the black line represents DLX and the red line represents Dlx48.</p></caption><graphic id="d33e2537" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="41598_2025_31085_Fig5_HTML.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>SASA analysis</title><p id="Par48">Solvent Accessible Surface Area (SASA) is a key structural descriptor that reflects the degree of solvent exposure and compactness of macromolecular complexes. It serves as an indirect measure of binding-site burial and the thermodynamic stability of protein–ligand interactions during MD simulations. In this study, the SASA of both the DLX–LeuBAT and DLX48–LeuBAT complexes was monitored over a 300 ns MD simulation trajectory. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5</xref>B, the DLX48–LeuBAT complex consistently exhibited lower SASA values, fluctuating within a range of 205–215 nm², whereas the DLX–LeuBAT complex maintained slightly elevated values, averaging 215–225 nm² throughout the simulation. The reduced SASA observed for DLX48 suggests that the ligand adopts a more deeply buried and tightly packed conformation within the binding cavity, resulting in decreased solvent exposure. This tighter accommodation is indicative of improved molecular complementarity and contributes to enhanced entropic and enthalpic stabilization of the complex. These findings are in agreement with previous observations from RMSD, hydrogen bonding, and contact analyses, collectively supporting the superior structural integration and retention of DLX48 within the LeuBAT binding pocket. Moreover, the lower solvent-exposed surface area may reduce unfavorable desolvation penalties and enhance the pharmacokinetic stability of the ligand. Thus, the SASA profile of DLX48 further reinforces its favorable binding characteristics, confirming that it forms a compact, persistent, and energetically stable interaction interface with the target transporter.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Radius of gyration analysis</title><p id="Par49">The radius of gyration (Rg) was computed over a 300 ns MD simulation to evaluate the overall structural compactness and conformational stability of the LeuBAT–ligand complexes. As illustrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5</xref>C, both DLX (black) and DLX48 (red) exhibited relatively stable Rg trajectories over the course of the simulation. Notably, DLX48 demonstrated a more compact and less fluctuating profile compared to the parent DLX molecule. The Rg values for DLX48 consistently remained within a narrower range (~ 2.28–2.31 nm), suggesting enhanced conformational stability of the ligand–protein complex. In contrast, DLX showed higher fluctuations, with Rg values spanning a broader range (~ 2.29–2.34 nm), indicating a relatively looser binding conformation. This comparative analysis supports the hypothesis that DLX48 forms a more rigid and conformationally stable complex with the LeuBAT transporter. Such compactness may reflect tighter binding and improved compatibility of DLX48 within the transporter’s active site, which aligns with the hydrogen bonding and docking data presented earlier.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Principal component analysis</title><p id="Par50">Principal Component Analysis (PCA) is a powerful multivariate statistical tool that enables decomposition of complex MD trajectories into orthogonal motion vectors, thereby capturing the dominant conformational dynamics of biomolecular systems. By projecting the atomic displacements onto principal eigenvectors derived from the covariance matrix of backbone atom fluctuations, PCA facilitates the interpretation of large-scale collective motions that underlie protein function and ligand-induced conformational changes. In the present study, PCA was employed to characterize the global dynamical behavior of the DLX–LeuBAT and DLX48–LeuBAT complexes over the 300 ns MD simulation. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fig5">5</xref>D, the conformational space sampled by each complex was visualized by plotting the first two principal components (PC1 vs. PC2). The DLX48-bound system (red) exhibited a tightly clustered trajectory, indicative of restricted motion and high conformational stability. This limited dispersion suggests that the DLX48–LeuBAT complex remained confined to a narrow conformational basin, reflecting a well-defined and stable binding mode throughout the simulation. Conversely, the DLX–LeuBAT complex (black) demonstrated a broader and more scattered distribution, implying increased conformational variability and reduced dynamical restraint. This expanded sampling of the conformational space may indicate greater flexibility or local instability within the binding site or adjacent structural elements when complexed with the parent compound. These PCA results are consistent with prior structural descriptors, including lower RMSD and RMSF values, greater hydrogen bond persistence, and more extensive residue contacts observed in the DLX48 system. Collectively, the compact principal component distribution further supports the hypothesis that DLX48 induces less global conformational fluctuation, promoting enhanced structural fidelity, tighter binding, and potentially improved pharmacological performance.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par51">The quantum mechanical (QM) analysis of the designed duloxetine analogs provided essential insights into their electronic configurations and reactive behavior. Among the candidates, DLX48 notably retained the HOMO–LUMO gap (4.81 eV) of the parent compound duloxetine (DLX), indicating preserved kinetic stability and balanced chemical reactivity. However, its higher dipole moment and improved electrostatic potential distribution suggest enhanced molecular polarity, which could translate into better aqueous solubility and more efficient pharmacokinetic properties. Global reactivity descriptors such as softness, chemical hardness, electrophilicity index, and chemical potential also point to greater molecular flexibility and electronic adaptability—factors often associated with optimized drug–target complementarity. Notably, MEP analysis revealed enriched negative electrostatic regions around heteroatoms (O, N), potentially facilitating stronger and more directional hydrogen bonding with biological targets. These findings align with previous QM studies linking optimized dipole moments and MEP profiles to improved CNS drug performance and binding specificity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. From a pharmacokinetic and toxicity standpoint, DLX48 also demonstrated a more favorable ADMET profile compared to DLX. Its balanced lipophilicity (log <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 2.88) and improved solubility (log S = − 3.21) are consistent with good oral absorption<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Additionally, DLX48 retained BBB permeability, avoided P-glycoprotein inhibition, and showed weaker inhibition of major CYP450 isoenzymes, suggesting a lower likelihood of adverse drug–drug interactions. Predicted toxicity endpoints indicated no increase in mutagenicity, cardiotoxicity, or hepatotoxicity, supporting the analog’s structural safety. These computational predictions are consistent with findings from other CNS drug development projects that employed in silico ADMET filtering to optimize lead compounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. In terms of molecular docking and dynamics, DLX48 demonstrated markedly improved binding performance at the LeuBAT transporter, a structurally validated model for the human norepinephrine transporter (hNET). The lower binding energy (–12.45 kcal/mol) and significantly reduced inhibition constant (Ki = 742.09 pM) compared to DLX underscore a meaningful enhancement in binding affinity. These results strongly suggest that rational scaffold modifications can optimize ligand–transporter interactions and improve pharmacodynamic outcomes. These findings are corroborated by the study of Góral et al. (2020)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, which used homology modeling of hNET and identified critical residues such as Asp75, Tyr152, and Phe317 in mediating binding with SNRIs like duloxetine. Similarly, our docking studies using LeuBAT identified Asp24, Ser254, Tyr108, and Phe259 as key interaction points for DLX48, reinforcing the conserved nature of monoamine transporter binding pockets. This validates the use of LeuBAT as a reliable surrogate for hNET in computational drug discovery. Moreover, DLX48 exhibited a more complex and diverse interaction network compared to DLX. The analog formed multiple hydrogen bonds in addition to hydrophobic and π–π stacking interactions—features absent or limited in the DLX–LeuBAT complex. This increased interaction density is in line with the findings of Abdi et al. (2025)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, who showed that duloxetine could form durable and energetically favorable interactions with non-transporter targets such as pSTAT3, involving complementary electrostatic features. The enhanced MEP-derived polarity and improved electronic configuration of DLX48 likely contributed to the stability of these interactions. MD simulations over 300 ns further validated the docking predictions, demonstrating high structural stability of the DLX48–LeuBAT complex with minimal RMSD fluctuations and consistent hydrogen bonding. Collectively, the integration of quantum mechanical, pharmacokinetic, docking, and dynamics analyses demonstrates that DLX48 not only replicates the essential interaction profile of duloxetine but also exceeds it in terms of binding affinity, electrostatic compatibility, and complex stability. These improvements substantiate DLX48 as a structurally optimized analog with enhanced therapeutic potential and encourage its experimental validation as a next-generation SNRI candidate.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par52">This study employed an integrative in silico approach combining quantum chemical (DFT) calculations, pharmacokinetic and toxicity predictions, molecular docking, and long-timescale molecular dynamics (MD) simulations to rationally design and evaluate novel duloxetine analogs. Among the tested compounds, DLX48 demonstrated superior performance across all evaluated parameters. DFT calculations confirmed that DLX48 maintains the electronic stability of the parent molecule while improving polarity and solubility—features that favor CNS penetration and oral bioavailability. ADMET modeling indicated a lower risk of cytochrome P450 inhibition, absence of toxicophores, and acceptable BBB permeability, highlighting its safety and drug-likeness. Molecular docking revealed enriched hydrogen bonding and hydrophobic interactions with key LeuBAT transporter residues, suggesting stronger binding affinity. These findings were reinforced by MD simulations over 300 ns, which showed that the DLX48–LeuBAT complex maintained higher structural stability, compactness, and persistent hydrogen bonding compared to the parent drug. The ligand remained tightly bound, with reduced conformational drift and improved interaction density. Together, these results underscore the potential of DLX48 as a promising next-generation SNRI candidate with enhanced efficacy and safety. The conclusion now avoids repetition and provides a forward-looking perspective, emphasizing the need for future in vitro and in vivo studies to experimentally validate DLX48’s pharmacological potential and to assess its applicability in CNS drug development pipelines.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Mehdi Yoosefian and Tahmineh Mokhtari contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>M.Y.: Supervision, Conceptualization, Methodology, Software, Formal Analysis, Writing—Original Draft. H.B.: Data Curation, Visualization, Investigation. K.S.A: Validation, Writing—Review &amp; Editing. T.M.: Project Administration, Writing—Review &amp; Editing, Funding Acquisition. All authors approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the NIEHS RIVER Award R35 ES030443.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets generated during this study, including optimized molecular structures, docking results, and molecular dynamics simulation trajectories, are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar8" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par53">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar10"><title><bold>Ethical approval</bold></title><p id="Par54">As an in silico study, no human or animal subjects were involved. All computational work complied with ethical standards, using publicly available data (e.g., PDB: 4MM6) and licensed software.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global prevalence of depression, anxiety, and stress in cardiac patients: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J. Affect. Disord.</source><year>2023</year><volume>324</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2022.12.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36584710</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Karami, N. et al. Global prevalence of depression, anxiety, and stress in cardiac patients: A systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic toggle="yes">J. Affect. Disord.</italic><bold>324</bold>, 175–189 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36584710</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2022.12.055</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unraveling the prefrontal cortex-basolateral amygdala pathway’s role on schizophrenia’s cognitive impairments: a multimodal study in patients and mouse models</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><year>2024</year><volume>50</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>923</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbae063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38811350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11283200</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Liang, J. et al. Unraveling the prefrontal cortex-basolateral amygdala pathway’s role on schizophrenia’s cognitive impairments: a multimodal study in patients and mouse models. <italic toggle="yes">Schizophr. Bull.</italic><bold>50</bold> (4), 913–923 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38811350</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbae063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11283200</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovich</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quaste</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacologic treatment of depression</article-title><source>Am. Family Phys.</source><year>2023</year><volume>107</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36791444</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Kovich, H., Kim, W. &amp; Quaste, A. M. Pharmacologic treatment of depression. <italic toggle="yes">Am. Family Phys.</italic><bold>107</bold> (2), 173–181 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36791444</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deciphering and targeting the ESR2–miR-10a-5p–BDNF axis in the prefrontal cortex: advancing postpartum depression Understanding and therapeutics</article-title><source>Research</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>0537</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.34133/research.0537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39588356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11586475</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Luo, F. et al. Deciphering and targeting the ESR2–miR-10a-5p–BDNF axis in the prefrontal cortex: advancing postpartum depression Understanding and therapeutics. <italic toggle="yes">Research</italic><bold>7</bold>, 0537 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39588356</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.34133/research.0537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11586475</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues-Amorim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of efficacy, safety, and tolerability of Duloxetine</article-title><source>Front. Psychiatry</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>554899</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.554899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33192668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7644852</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Rodrigues-Amorim, D. et al. A systematic review of efficacy, safety, and tolerability of Duloxetine. <italic toggle="yes">Front. Psychiatry</italic>. <bold>11</bold>, 554899 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33192668</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.554899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7644852</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pexidartinib (PLX3397) through restoring hippocampal synaptic plasticity ameliorates social isolation-induced mood disorders</article-title><source>Int. Immunopharmacol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>109436</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2022.109436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36395673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9661988</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Wang, L. et al. Pexidartinib (PLX3397) through restoring hippocampal synaptic plasticity ameliorates social isolation-induced mood disorders. <italic toggle="yes">Int. Immunopharmacol.</italic><bold>113</bold>, 109436 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36395673</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2022.109436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9661988</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Beneficial and harmful effects of Duloxetine versus placebo,‘active placebo’or no intervention for adults with major depressive disorder: a systematic review with meta-analysis and trial sequential analysis of randomised clinical trials</article-title><source>BMJ open.</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e082853</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-082853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39920066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12056638</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Siddiqui, F. et al. Beneficial and harmful effects of Duloxetine versus placebo,‘active placebo’or no intervention for adults with major depressive disorder: a systematic review with meta-analysis and trial sequential analysis of randomised clinical trials. <italic toggle="yes">BMJ open.</italic><bold>15</bold> (2), e082853 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39920066</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-082853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12056638</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs) for treatment of fibromyalgia: A comprehensive clinical review</article-title><source>Psychopharmacol. Bull.</source><year>2025</year><volume>55</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.64719/pb.4519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39935669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11809501</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Malik, A. et al. Serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs) for treatment of fibromyalgia: A comprehensive clinical review. <italic toggle="yes">Psychopharmacol. Bull.</italic><bold>55</bold> (2), 24–40 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39935669</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.64719/pb.4519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11809501</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Filocco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hidden withdrawal epidemic of cymbalta (Duloxetine): the inequities of the learned intermediary doctrine in cymbalta litigation and the necessity of an FDA Re-Evaluation</article-title><source>Seton Hall Legis J.</source><year>2023</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>122</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Filocco, M. The hidden withdrawal epidemic of cymbalta (Duloxetine): the inequities of the learned intermediary doctrine in cymbalta litigation and the necessity of an FDA Re-Evaluation. <italic toggle="yes">Seton Hall Legis J.</italic><bold>47</bold>, 122 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microglial activation in the medial prefrontal cortex after remote fear recall participates in the regulation of auditory fear extinction</article-title><source>Eur. J. Pharmacol.</source><year>2024</year><volume>978</volume><fpage>176759</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2024.176759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38901527</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Zou, G. J. et al. Microglial activation in the medial prefrontal cortex after remote fear recall participates in the regulation of auditory fear extinction. <italic toggle="yes">Eur. J. Pharmacol.</italic><bold>978</bold>, 176759 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38901527</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2024.176759</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansbauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe serotonin syndrome under Duloxetine in a patient with coeliac disease—is there a connection? A case report</article-title><source>Eur. J. Psychiatry</source><year>2021</year><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejpsy.2020.10.001</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Hansbauer, M. &amp; Strauss, C. Severe serotonin syndrome under Duloxetine in a patient with coeliac disease—is there a connection? A case report. <italic toggle="yes">Eur. J. Psychiatry</italic>. <bold>35</bold> (3), 193–196 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiongko</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sedky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Duloxetine and hepatic injury: A case presentation</article-title><source>Psychiatric Annals</source><year>2023</year><volume>53</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3928/00485713-20230105-02</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Soal, V., Tiongko, J. L. &amp; Sedky, K. Duloxetine and hepatic injury: A case presentation. <italic toggle="yes">Psychiatric Annals</italic>. <bold>53</bold> (1), 47–51 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S4301 Duloxetine dilemma: unmasking the hidden threat of liver injury</article-title><source>Official J. Am. Coll. Gastroenterology| ACG</source><year>2024</year><volume>119</volume><issue>10S</issue><fpage>S2765</fpage><lpage>S2766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/01.ajg.0001046572.84038.03</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Mohammadi, A. S4301 Duloxetine dilemma: unmasking the hidden threat of liver injury. <italic toggle="yes">Official J. Am. Coll. Gastroenterology| ACG</italic>. <bold>119</bold> (10S), S2765–S2766 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Peptide-based system for sensing Pb2 + and molecular logic computing</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><year>2021</year><volume>630</volume><fpage>114333</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2021.114333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34400145</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Lu, J. Y. et al. Peptide-based system for sensing Pb2 + and molecular logic computing. <italic toggle="yes">Anal. Biochem.</italic><bold>630</bold>, 114333 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34400145</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2021.114333</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuppalanchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Duloxetine hepatotoxicity: a case-series from the drug‐induced liver injury network</article-title><source>Aliment. Pharmacol. Ther.</source><year>2010</year><volume>32</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1174</fpage><lpage>1183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2036.2010.04449.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20815829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3773985</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Vuppalanchi, R. et al. Duloxetine hepatotoxicity: a case-series from the drug‐induced liver injury network. <italic toggle="yes">Aliment. Pharmacol. Ther.</italic><bold>32</bold> (9), 1174–1183 (2010).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20815829</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2036.2010.04449.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3773985</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hole, K. et al. <italic toggle="yes">Effect of CYP2D6 Genotype on Duloxetine Serum Concentration</italic> Vol. 134, p. 186–192 (Basic &amp; Clinical Pharmacology &amp; Toxicology, 2024). 1.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcpt.13954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37864290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Indicator regularized non-negative matrix factorization method-based drug repurposing for COVID-19</article-title><source>Front. Immunol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>603615</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.603615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33584672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7878370</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Tang, X. et al. Indicator regularized non-negative matrix factorization method-based drug repurposing for COVID-19. <italic toggle="yes">Front. Immunol.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 603615 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33584672</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.603615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7878370</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdi</surname><given-names>SAH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Duloxetine, an SNRI, targets pSTAT3 signaling: In-Silico, RNA-Seq and In-Vitro evidence for a pleiotropic mechanism of pain relief</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2025</year><volume>26</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>10432</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms262110432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41226470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12609430</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Abdi, S. A. H. et al. Duloxetine, an SNRI, targets pSTAT3 signaling: In-Silico, RNA-Seq and In-Vitro evidence for a pleiotropic mechanism of pain relief. <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Mol. Sci.</italic><bold>26</bold> (21), 10432 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41226470</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms262110432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12609430</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glycerosomal thermosensitive in situ gel of Duloxetine HCl as a novel nanoplatform for rectal delivery: in vitro optimization and in vivo appraisal</article-title><source>Drug Delivery Translational Res.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3083</fpage><lpage>3103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13346-022-01172-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9636110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35622235</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Salem, H. F. et al. Glycerosomal thermosensitive in situ gel of Duloxetine HCl as a novel nanoplatform for rectal delivery: in vitro optimization and in vivo appraisal. <italic toggle="yes">Drug Delivery Translational Res.</italic><bold>12</bold> (12), 3083–3103 (2022).<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13346-022-01172-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9636110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35622235</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sadashivaiah, R. <italic toggle="yes">Development and Evaluation of Transdermal Drug Delivery Systems for Anti Parkinsons and Antipsychotic Drugs</italic> (Rajiv Gandhi University of Health Sciences (India), 2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edache</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular phylogeny, Sequence-based drug design, Docking built virtual screening, dynamics simulations, and ADMET properties of Thiazolino 2-pyridone amide derivatives as an inhibitor of chlamydia trachomatis and SARS-CoV-2 protein</article-title><source>Turkish Comput. Theoretical Chem.</source><year>2024</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33435/tcandtc.1196019</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Edache, E. et al. Molecular phylogeny, Sequence-based drug design, Docking built virtual screening, dynamics simulations, and ADMET properties of Thiazolino 2-pyridone amide derivatives as an inhibitor of chlamydia trachomatis and SARS-CoV-2 protein. <italic toggle="yes">Turkish Comput. Theoretical Chem.</italic><bold>8</bold> (1), 10–39 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Góral</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Łątka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bajda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure modeling of the norepinephrine transporter</article-title><source>Biomolecules</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>102</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom10010102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31936154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7022499</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Góral, I., Łątka, K. &amp; Bajda, M. Structure modeling of the norepinephrine transporter. <italic toggle="yes">Biomolecules</italic><bold>10</bold> (1), 102 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31936154</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom10010102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7022499</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Esmaeili</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoosefian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular dynamics simulation of Lenalidomide interaction with cRBN protein: a target for Immunomodulatory drugs</article-title><source>S. Afr. J. Chem.</source><year>2023</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>162</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Esmaeili, A., Yoosefian, M. &amp; Mahani, M. Molecular dynamics simulation of Lenalidomide interaction with cRBN protein: a target for Immunomodulatory drugs. <italic toggle="yes">S. Afr. J. Chem.</italic><bold>77</bold>, 157–162 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoosefian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moghani</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silico evaluation of Atazanavir as a potential HIV main protease inhibitor and its comparison with new designed analogs</article-title><source>Comput. Biol. Med.</source><year>2022</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>105523</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2022.105523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35585735</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Yoosefian, M., Moghani, M. Z. &amp; Juan, A. Silico evaluation of Atazanavir as a potential HIV main protease inhibitor and its comparison with new designed analogs. <italic toggle="yes">Comput. Biol. Med.</italic><bold>145</bold>, 105523 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35585735</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2022.105523</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yoosefian, M. <italic toggle="yes">Designing new pharmaceutical derivatives for potential Inhibition of human immunodeficiency virus protease enzyme Inhibition; a comprehensive in Silico study</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">J. Biomol. Struct. Dynamics</italic>, : pp. 1–22. (2025).<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07391102.2025.2490791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40215336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gheidari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Computational studies on structural aspects of Pyrazolo [3, 4-b] pyridine derivatives as TRKA inhibitors in cancer therapy</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>27367</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-08370-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40717129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12301433</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Gheidari, D. et al. Computational studies on structural aspects of Pyrazolo [3, 4-b] pyridine derivatives as TRKA inhibitors in cancer therapy. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold> (1), 27367 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40717129</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-08370-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12301433</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ugbe</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cheminformatics-based discovery of new organoselenium compounds with potential for the treatment of cutaneous and visceral leishmaniasis</article-title><source>J. Biomol. Struct. Dynamics</source><year>2024</year><volume>42</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>13830</fpage><lpage>13853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07391102.2023.2279269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37937770</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Ugbe, F. A. et al. Cheminformatics-based discovery of new organoselenium compounds with potential for the treatment of cutaneous and visceral leishmaniasis. <italic toggle="yes">J. Biomol. Struct. Dynamics</italic>. <bold>42</bold> (24), 13830–13853 (2024).<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07391102.2023.2279269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37937770</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edache</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation of Salicylidene acylhydrazides derivatives: molecular Docking, ADMET, and molecular dynamic simulations were used in conjunction towards the design of new yersinia pseudotuberculosis inhibitors</article-title><source>Turkish Comput. Theoretical Chem.</source><year>2022</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33435/tcandtc.1003157</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Edache, E. et al. Investigation of Salicylidene acylhydrazides derivatives: molecular Docking, ADMET, and molecular dynamic simulations were used in conjunction towards the design of new yersinia pseudotuberculosis inhibitors. <italic toggle="yes">Turkish Comput. Theoretical Chem.</italic><bold>6</bold> (1), 9–30 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orujova</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vitro, in silico, and DFT evaluation of antimicrobial imidazole derivatives with insights into mechanism of action</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37723</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-24847-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41152498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12569038</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Orujova, N. S. et al. In vitro, in silico, and DFT evaluation of antimicrobial imidazole derivatives with insights into mechanism of action. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold> (1), 37723 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41152498</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-24847-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12569038</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gheidari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, molecular docking, Pharmacological evaluation, MD simulation, and DFT calculations of quinazolin-12-one derivatives as PDK1 inhibitors</article-title><source>Nanoscale Adv.</source><year>2025</year><volume>7</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>5760</fpage><lpage>5783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D5NA00182J</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40808821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12341467</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Sadeghian, Z., Bayat, M. &amp; Gheidari, D. Synthesis, molecular docking, Pharmacological evaluation, MD simulation, and DFT calculations of quinazolin-12-one derivatives as PDK1 inhibitors. <italic toggle="yes">Nanoscale Adv.</italic><bold>7</bold> (18), 5760–5783 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40808821</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d5na00182j</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12341467</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadzadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoosefian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezayi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive experimental and theoretical investigations on chromium (III) trace detection in biological and environmental samples using polymeric membrane sensor</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Anal. Chem.</source><year>2021</year><volume>101</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1461</fpage><lpage>1476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03067319.2019.1685664</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Ahmadzadeh, S., Yoosefian, M. &amp; Rezayi, M. Comprehensive experimental and theoretical investigations on chromium (III) trace detection in biological and environmental samples using polymeric membrane sensor. <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Environ. Anal. Chem.</italic><bold>101</bold> (10), 1461–1476 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd-Almutalib</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naser</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational and molecular Docking analysis of a novel Azo compound and its nanocomposite biopolymer synthesized via a single-pot method</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>38668</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-96866-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41193856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12589532</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Abd-Almutalib, M. G. &amp; Naser, N. Computational and molecular Docking analysis of a novel Azo compound and its nanocomposite biopolymer synthesized via a single-pot method. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold> (1), 38668 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41193856</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-96866-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12589532</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Masoumi, Z., Bayat, M. &amp; Gheidari, D. <italic toggle="yes">In Silico Study of Bis (6-Amino‐1, 3‐Dimethylpyrimidine‐2, 4 (1H, 3H)‐Diones) as EGFR Inhibitors: Synthesis, DFT, Molecular Docking, and MD Simulation Studies.</italic> Cellular Microbiology, 2025(1): p. 5585552. (2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoosefian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the effect of Sofosbuvir as an inhibitor of hepatitis C virus and an in-depth comparative analysis with advanced analogues</article-title><source>J. Mol. Liq.</source><year>2025</year><volume>426</volume><fpage>127304</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molliq.2025.127304</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Yoosefian, M. et al. Evaluation of the effect of Sofosbuvir as an inhibitor of hepatitis C virus and an in-depth comparative analysis with advanced analogues. <italic toggle="yes">J. Mol. Liq.</italic><bold>426</bold>, 127304 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edache</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>QSAR, homology modeling, and Docking simulation on SARS-CoV-2 and Pseudomonas aeruginosa inhibitors, ADMET, and molecular dynamic simulations to find a possible oral lead candidate</article-title><source>J. Genetic Eng. Biotechnol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s43141-022-00362-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9205150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35730025</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Edache, E. I. et al. QSAR, homology modeling, and Docking simulation on SARS-CoV-2 and Pseudomonas aeruginosa inhibitors, ADMET, and molecular dynamic simulations to find a possible oral lead candidate. <italic toggle="yes">J. Genetic Eng. Biotechnol.</italic><bold>20</bold> (1), 88 (2022).<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s43141-022-00362-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9205150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35730025</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ganiev, B., Mardonov, U. &amp; Kholikova, G. <italic toggle="yes">Molecular structure, HOMO-LUMO, MEP-–Analysis of triazine compounds using DFT (B3LYP) calculations.</italic> Materials Today: Proceedings, (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabry</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Electronic structure, global reactivity descriptors and nonlinear optical properties of Glycine interacted with ZnO, MgO and CaO for bacterial detection</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22801</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-72846-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39353963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11445471</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Sabry, N. M. et al. Electronic structure, global reactivity descriptors and nonlinear optical properties of Glycine interacted with ZnO, MgO and CaO for bacterial detection. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>14</bold> (1), 22801 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39353963</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-72846-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11445471</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoosefian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ultra-low concentration protein detection based on phenylalanine–Pd/SWCNT as a high sensitivity nanoreceptor</article-title><source>RSC Adv.</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2650</fpage><lpage>2660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C9RA09243A</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35496082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9048758</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Yoosefian, M. et al. Ultra-low concentration protein detection based on phenylalanine–Pd/SWCNT as a high sensitivity nanoreceptor. <italic toggle="yes">RSC Adv.</italic><bold>10</bold> (5), 2650–2660 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35496082</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c9ra09243a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9048758</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Edache, E. I. et al. <italic toggle="yes">Pharmacophore modeling, 2D-QSAR, Drug likeness and toxicity prediction of 2-aziridinyl-and 2, 3-bis (aziridinyl)-1, 4-naphthoquinonyl sulfonate and acylate derivatives as multifunctional agents for the treatment of malaria parasite, Plasmodium falciparum.</italic> NAM Journal, : p. 100019. (2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Research progress of Apelin in acute ischemic brain injury</article-title><source>Am. J. Translational Res.</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>7260</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9641465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36398257</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Luo, H. et al. Research progress of Apelin in acute ischemic brain injury. <italic toggle="yes">Am. J. Translational Res.</italic><bold>14</bold> (10), 7260 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9641465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36398257</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ProTox-II: a webserver for the prediction of toxicity of chemicals</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><issue>W1</issue><fpage>W257</fpage><lpage>W263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29718510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6031011</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Banerjee, P. et al. ProTox-II: a webserver for the prediction of toxicity of chemicals. <italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res.</italic><bold>46</bold> (W1), W257–W263 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29718510</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6031011</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edache</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of novel Anti-SARS-CoV-2 compounds by targeting nucleoprotein and envelope protein through homology modeling, Docking simulations, ADMET, and molecular dynamic simulations with the MM/GBSA calculation</article-title><source>Intell. Pharm.</source><year>2024</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>366</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Edache, E. I. et al. Evaluation of novel Anti-SARS-CoV-2 compounds by targeting nucleoprotein and envelope protein through homology modeling, Docking simulations, ADMET, and molecular dynamic simulations with the MM/GBSA calculation. <italic toggle="yes">Intell. Pharm.</italic><bold>2</bold> (3), 346–366 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edache</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of action of substituted peramivir phosphonate derivatives as potent oseltamivir-resistant influenza A virus using molecular docking, molecular dynamics simulations, and free energies calculations</article-title><source>Discover Chem.</source><year>2025</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>99</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s44371-025-00184-1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Edache, E. I. et al. Mechanism of action of substituted peramivir phosphonate derivatives as potent oseltamivir-resistant influenza A virus using molecular docking, molecular dynamics simulations, and free energies calculations. <italic toggle="yes">Discover Chem.</italic><bold>2</bold> (1), 99 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Woldekidan, H. B. &amp; Woldesemayat, A. A. <italic toggle="yes">In Silico Method for ssDNA Aptamer Binding with Aurora Kinase A Protein</italic> (Springer, 2025).<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/7651_2024_596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39776073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LSPR biosensing for the early-stage prostate cancer detection using hydrogen bonds between PSA and antibody: molecular dynamic and experimental study</article-title><source>J. Mol. Liq.</source><year>2021</year><volume>324</volume><fpage>114736</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molliq.2020.114736</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Mahani, M. et al. LSPR biosensing for the early-stage prostate cancer detection using hydrogen bonds between PSA and antibody: molecular dynamic and experimental study. <italic toggle="yes">J. Mol. Liq.</italic><bold>324</bold>, 114736 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoosefian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A suitable drug structure for interaction with SARS-CoV‐2 main protease between boceprevir, masitinib and rupintrivir; a molecular dynamics study</article-title><source>Arab. J. Chem.</source><year>2023</year><volume>16</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>105051</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arabjc.2023.105051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37323221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10246938</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Yoosefian, M. et al. A suitable drug structure for interaction with SARS-CoV‐2 main protease between boceprevir, masitinib and rupintrivir; a molecular dynamics study. <italic toggle="yes">Arab. J. Chem.</italic><bold>16</bold> (9), 105051 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37323221</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arabjc.2023.105051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10246938</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edache</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2D-QSAR, docking, molecular dynamics simulations with the MM/GBSA approaches against graves’ disease and PTPN22</article-title><source>Borneo J. Pharm.</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33084/bjop.v6i3.4915</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Edache, E. I. et al. 2D-QSAR, docking, molecular dynamics simulations with the MM/GBSA approaches against graves’ disease and PTPN22. <italic toggle="yes">Borneo J. Pharm.</italic><bold>6</bold> (3), 229–248 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoosefian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular dynamics simulations on interaction of ssDNA-causing DM1 with carbon and Boron nitride nanotubes to inhibit the formation of CTG repeat secondary structures</article-title><source>Appl. Surf. Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>524</volume><fpage>146572</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsusc.2020.146572</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Yoosefian, M. et al. Molecular dynamics simulations on interaction of ssDNA-causing DM1 with carbon and Boron nitride nanotubes to inhibit the formation of CTG repeat secondary structures. <italic toggle="yes">Appl. Surf. Sci.</italic><bold>524</bold>, 146572 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gheidari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrdad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Etedali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of natural compounds as potential inhibitors of Interleukin-23: virtual screening, ADMET, drug-likeness, and dynamic simulation</article-title><source>Front. Drug Discovery</source><year>2025</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1525533</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fddsv.2025.1525533</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Gheidari, D., Mehrdad, M. &amp; Etedali, M. Identification of natural compounds as potential inhibitors of Interleukin-23: virtual screening, ADMET, drug-likeness, and dynamic simulation. <italic toggle="yes">Front. Drug Discovery</italic>. <bold>5</bold>, 1525533 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amiri</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gheidari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of thiazoloquinolinone derivatives: molecular docking, MD simulation, and Pharmacological evaluation as VEGFR-2 inhibitors</article-title><source>BMC Chem.</source><year>2025</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>90</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13065-025-01459-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40188066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11972512</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Amiri, Z., Bayat, M. &amp; Gheidari, D. Synthesis of thiazoloquinolinone derivatives: molecular docking, MD simulation, and Pharmacological evaluation as VEGFR-2 inhibitors. <italic toggle="yes">BMC Chem.</italic><bold>19</bold> (1), 90 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40188066</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13065-025-01459-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11972512</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masarkar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetic, docking, and DFT analyses reveal Moringa Oleifera phytochemicals as inhibitors of HIF-1α/VEGF/GLUT1 signaling pathway in breast cancer</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>36837</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-20757-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41125614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12546829</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Masarkar, N. et al. Pharmacokinetic, docking, and DFT analyses reveal Moringa Oleifera phytochemicals as inhibitors of HIF-1α/VEGF/GLUT1 signaling pathway in breast cancer. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold> (1), 36837 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41125614</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-20757-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12546829</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>