<article article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4" xml:lang="en"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACG Case Rep J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACG Case Rep J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2725</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">acgcasereps</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AC9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ACG Case Reports Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2326-3253</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American College of Gastroenterology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12900175</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12900175.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12900175</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12900175</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41696668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/crj.0000000000001980</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ACGCR-25-0930</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version article-version-type="Version of Record" vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Liver</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Late-Onset Efavirenz-Induced Liver Toxicity in a 17-Year-Old, Filipino, Patient With HIV</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clutario</surname><given-names initials="JDC">John Derek C.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, DPCP</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><email>johnderekclutario@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="false" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-4381-2563</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names initials="SNL">Sharlene Nicole L.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedregosa</surname><given-names initials="GS">Gerardo S.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FPCP, FPSG</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><email>g96p71@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Labio</surname><given-names initials="MED">Madalinee Eternity D.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FPCP, FPSG</degrees><email>elabio@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caoili</surname><given-names initials="JC">Janice C.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FPCP, FPSMID</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><email>janice.caoili@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendoza</surname><given-names initials="RD">Redante D.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><email>redmendoza@yahoo.com</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Makati Medical Center, Makati City, Philippines</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Sharlene Nicole L. Chan, MD (<email>sharlenechan96@gmail.com</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">506896</issue-id><elocation-id>e01980</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>03</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-16 15:25:13.347"><day>16</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2026 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. on behalf of The American College of Gastroenterology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref content-type="ccbyncndlicense" specific-use="textmining" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND)</ext-link>, where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ac9-13-e01980.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><self-uri xlink:href="ac9-13-e01980.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Efavirenz is a non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor widely used in HIV treatment. Although generally well-tolerated, rare cases of severe hepatotoxicity have been reported. We present a case of a patient on efavirenz-based highly active antiretroviral therapy who developed jaundice and marked transaminitis 1 year after initiation. Infectious, autoimmune, and toxic causes were ruled out, and genetic testing revealed no metabolic abnormalities. Treatment involved corticosteroids, immunosuppressants, and switching to dolutegravir, leading to resolution. This is the first documented case in the Philippines of delayed-onset efavirenz-induced liver injury, underscoring the importance of ongoing liver monitoring during antiretroviral therapy.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS:</title><kwd>Efavirenz-induced liver toxicity</kwd><kwd>drug-induced liver injury</kwd><kwd>HIV treatment</kwd><kwd>immunocompromised state</kwd><kwd>Filipino</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Efavirenz, a non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor, is widely used in HIV treatment and is generally well-tolerated.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> However, hepatotoxicity has been reported and can range from asymptomatic transaminitis to fulminant liver failure. Compared to nevirapine, efavirenz-induced liver injury (EFV-DILI) is less frequent and lacks distinct clinical features. The latency period is typically within 6 months, and late-onset cases are rare. We present a unique case of EFV-DILI manifesting after 1 year of therapy in a patient without known risk factors.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>CASE REPORT</title><p>This is a 17-year-old male patient diagnosed with HIV, acquired from a previous blood transfusion, and was started on tenofovir, lamivudine, and efavirenz. He was admitted as a case of community-acquired pneumonia and treated with piperacillin-tazobactam and azithromycin, and trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole. The patient was discharged stable 2 months later and completed anti-TB treatment as an outpatient. One year after starting highly active antiretroviral therapy, he was readmitted for scleral icterus and jaundice. No new medications, dietary supplements, or antibiotics were taken. Before initiation of highly active antiretroviral therapy, baseline aspartate transferase and alanine transaminase were normal at 19.5 U/L and 20.4 U/L, respectively. The patient was negative for tests for hepatitis B, hepatitis C, and hepatitis A. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) was elevated at 1,304.42 U/L, alanine aminotransferase (ALT) elevated at 1,550.88 U/L, while the following were elevated: alkaline phosphatase (ALP) 297.9 U/L, total bilirubin 213.6 umol/L. R factor was more than 5, which suggests hepatocellular pattern of liver injury; however, on Roussel Uclaf Causality Assessment Method, the score was 6–8 points (probable cause of hepatic injury from efavirenz) and Naranjo Adverse Drug Reaction Probability Scale +3 (possible); the reaction occurred after the drug was given, and possibly followed a pattern consistent with drug reaction. After which, efavirenz was discontinued and replaced with dolutegravir. At this time, the patient was referred to hepatology and considered acute cholestatic hepatitis and ruled out opportunistic infection (cytomegalovirus, herpes simplex virus, tuberculosis). Although antinuclear antibody was positive (1:1,280 speckled pattern), autoimmune disease was less likely based on negative results for Anti-ds DNA, Anti-Smith, Anti-RNP 70, Anti-Sjögren’s syndrome A, Anti-Sjögren’s syndrome B, Anti-histidyl tRNA synthetase, antimitochondrial antibodies, anti-liver kidney microsomal antibodies, anti-smooth muscle antibody, and perinuclear anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies. Despite medications being shifted, the patient still had persistent elevation of liver enzymes. A liver biopsy was done and showed findings of liver inflammation, but inconclusive if it was caused by an autoimmune response or drug-induced. Although R factor was more than 5 suggesting hepatocellular pattern of liver injury, liver biopsy slides on hematoxylin and eosin stains showed the following on Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>: portal triaditis with ductular proliferation, periductular cholestasis, and confluent hepatocellular necrosis—findings consistent with a mixed hepatocellular-cholestatic pattern of drug-induced liver injury. This pattern is characterized by simultaneous hepatocellular injury (evidenced by necrosis, mononuclear infiltrates, and sinusoidal collapse) and cholestatic features (ductular reaction and periductular cholestasis). The coexistence of portal inflammation with interface activity and mild eosinophilia also supports an immune-allergic or autoimmune-like mechanism, which has been described in efavirenz-associated hepatotoxicity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup> On Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, special stains showed no iron deposition, parenchymal collapse, and there is early fibrosis. Despite ursodeoxycholic acid and Minophagen, the patient had persistent elevated liver enzymes. Prednisone was started at 10 mg/tab one tablet twice a day for 2 months then tapered to prednisone 5 mg 1 tablet once daily for 3 months. After which, prednisone was given at 5 mg tab once daily on alternating days 3 times a week for 1 month and was discontinued. Mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) was given at a dose of 500 mg tablet 1 tablet once daily. After 2 weeks of shifting from efavirenz to dolutegravir and starting on prednisone, AST and ALT levels decreased to 212.61 U/L and 254.62 U/L, respectively. ALP slightly increased from 196.32 U/L to 197.39 U/L but significantly improved from the time efavirenz was introduced. Total bilirubin slightly increased from 421.4 to 432.2 umol/L. After a year, AST, ALT, ALP, and bilirubin levels decreased to normal levels (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Liver biopsy slides on hematoxylin and eosin stains: (A) there are portal areas with triaditis as well as ductular proliferation (red arrow). There is periductular cholestasis, and central areas show congestion. There is also interstitial hepatitis and evidence of sinusoidal collapse (black arrow) (magnification: 10×). (B) There are areas of mainly mononuclear infiltrates with some neutrophils and rare eosinophils (blue arrow). In some areas, hepatocytes showed binucleation, as well as Kupffer cell proliferation. There is confluent necrosis and beginning fibrosis (orange arrow) (magnification: 40×).</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="ac9-13-e01980-g001.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Liver biopsy slides (magnification: 200×). (A) Iron stain with no iron deposition seen. (B) Trichrome showed parenchymal collapse and the early fibrosis seen in hematoxylin and eosin staining. (C) Periodic acid schiff-diastase stain with no diastase resistant intracytoplasmic contents.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="ac9-13-e01980-g002.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Temporal trend of AST, ALT, ALP, and total bilirubin levels after discontinuation of efavirenz and initiation of corticosteroid and mycophenolate therapy. ALP, alkaline phosphatase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="ac9-13-e01980-g003.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Total bilirubin, direct bilirubin, and indirect bilirubin levels after discontinuation of efavirenz and initiation of corticosteroid and mycophenolate therapy.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="ac9-13-e01980-g004.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>EFV-induced drug-induced liver injury mostly occurs within 14–24 weeks of EFV initiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>; however, our case is unusual in that DILI manifested 1 year after starting EFV therapy, a timeframe not previously documented. EFV DILI lacks specific clinical characteristics, although predictors include elevated baseline liver enzymes, high EFV plasma concentration, and CYP2B6 polymorphisms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup> The patient was advised to do whole genome sequencing; however, he was not amenable. The patient's histology revealed submassive necrosis with eosinophilic infiltrate, consistent with one of 3 EFV DILI patterns described in South African cohorts.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup> Management of non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor–related liver injury typically involves discontinuation of the offending agent in cases of grade 3–4 liver enzyme elevation or symptomatic hepatitis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> Corticosteroids are often administered and appear to aid in alleviating fever and rash; however, their efficacy in improving liver disease remains uncertain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup></p><p>In our patient, the decision to initiate corticosteroid therapy followed the recognition of a likely immune-allergic or autoimmune-like pattern of drug-induced liver injury associated with efavirenz. The pathophysiology of idiosyncratic DILI increasingly implicates immune-mediated mechanisms, including human leukocyte antigen associations, T-cell activation, and hypersensitivity features such as eosinophilia and portal mononuclear infiltrates on biopsy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> Although current guidelines emphasize prompt drug withdrawal as the cornerstone of DILI management, corticosteroids may be considered in cases where the clinical or histologic pattern overlaps with autoimmune hepatitis (AIH) or when immune-allergic features are evident.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup> At present, no standardized corticosteroid tapering protocol exists for autoimmune-like drug-induced liver injury. Management is generally guided by AIH experience and observational data, with initial prednisolone dose of 30 mg/d was selected in accordance with established AIH treatment protocols, which recommend 0.5–1 mg/kg/d but typically limit the starting dose to 30–40 mg/d to optimize therapeutic efficacy while minimizing adverse effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup></p><p>Based on established regimens for AIH, MMF was given in doses ranging from 1 to 2 g per day in divided doses and subsequently tapered according to biochemical response and tolerance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup> MMF has shown efficacy in AIH and immune-mediated liver injury refractory to corticosteroids or in those intolerant to azathioprine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> This combined strategy aligns with current expert recommendations for AIH and has been adapted for autoimmune-like drug-induced liver injury, aiming to suppress immune-mediated hepatic inflammation while minimizing prolonged corticosteroid exposure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup></p><p>This case underscores the importance of recognizing EFV as a potential cause of late-onset hepatotoxicity and supports individualized treatment strategies.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>DISCLOSURES</title><p>Author contributions: JDC Clutario, GS Pedregosa, JC Caoili, and MED Labio conceptualized the study; JDC Clutario and SNL Chan reviewed the literature, collected, and analyzed the data. JDC Clutario and SNL Chan finalized the manuscript. RD Mendoza furnished and provided photos of slides and discussed histopathologic results. JDC Clutario is the article guarantor.</p><p>Financial disclosure: None to report.</p><p>Previous presentation: Presented as oral presentation at Asian Pacific Association for the Study of the Liver (APASL); March 28, 2024; Kyoto, Japan.</p><p>Informed consent was obtained for this case report.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>ABBREVIATIONS:</title><def-list><def-item><term id="G1">AIH</term><def><p>autoimmune hepatitis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">ALP</term><def><p>alkaline phosphatase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">ALT</term><def><p>alanine aminotransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">Anti-Jo-1</term><def><p>anti-histidyl tRNA synthetase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">Anti-SSA</term><def><p>anti-Sjogren’s syndrome A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">Anti-SSB</term><def><p>anti-Sjogren's syndrome B</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7">ASMA</term><def><p>anti-smooth muscle antibody</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G8">AST</term><def><p>aspartate aminotransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G9">EFV</term><def><p>efavirenz</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G10">EFV-DILI</term><def><p>efavirenz-induced liver injury</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G11">HIV</term><def><p>human immunodeficiency virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G12">MMF</term><def><p>mycophenolate mofetil</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G13">p-ANCA</term><def><p>perinuclear anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mitty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Overview of Antiretroviral Agents Used to Treat HIV</source>. <publisher-name>UpToDate</publisher-name>, <year>2025</year>. Accessed May 3, 2025. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.uptodate.com/contents/overview-of-antiretroviral-agents-used-to-treat-hiv" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.uptodate.com/contents/overview-of-antiretroviral-agents-used-to-treat-hiv</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Björnsson</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vucic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stirnimann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Robles-Díaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Role of corticosteroids in drug-induced liver injury. A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Front Pharmacol.</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>820724</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35222034</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.820724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8867035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madasu</surname><given-names>MVSL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Devarapalli</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kursam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Devalaraju</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dasari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A brief review on Efavirenz and it's adverse effects</article-title>. <source>World J Pharm Res.</source>
<year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1932</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maughan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sonderup</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gogela</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A natural history of efavirenz drug-induced liver injury</article-title>. <source>S Afr Med J.</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1190</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34949306</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.7196/SAMJ.2021.v111i12.14584</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mira</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Liver toxicity induced by non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother.</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17255142</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkl524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Efavirenz</article-title>. In: <source>LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury [Internet]</source>. <publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>. Updated February 10, 2018. Accessed May 3, 2025. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK548521/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK548521/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31643176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An immunological perspective on the mechanism of drug induced liver injury: Focused on drugs for treatment of hepatocellular carcinoma and liver transplantation</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source>
<year>2023</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>5002</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36902432</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms24055002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10003078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalasani</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maddur</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group>, <collab>Practice Parameters Committee of the American College of Gastroenterology</collab>. <article-title>ACG clinical guideline: Diagnosis and management of idiosyncratic drug-induced liver injury</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol.</source>
<year>2021</year>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>878</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33929376</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/ajg.0000000000001259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Czaja</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis and management of autoimmune hepatitis: Current status and future directions</article-title>. <source>Gut Liver.</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26934884</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.5009/gnl15352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4780448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharzehi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schreibman</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mycophenolate mofetil for the treatment of autoimmune hepatitis in patients refractory or intolerant to conventional therapy</article-title>. <source>Can J Gastroenterol.</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21037986</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2010/891252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2975470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dara</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Buhler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Elwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Beware of drug-induced autoimmune-like hepatitis</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology.</source>
<year>2024</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e1</fpage>–<lpage>e4</lpage>.<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2023.09.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37797776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Optimizing the tapering scheme of corticosteroid treatment for acute onset of autoimmune hepatitis</article-title>. <source>J Autoimmun.</source>
<year>2025</year>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>103387</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40015068</pub-id>
<pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaut.2025.103387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>