<article article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4" xml:lang="en"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JACC Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JACC Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4067</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jacccasereps</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JACC Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-0849</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12790193</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12790193.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12790193</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12790193</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41123532</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaccas.2025.105776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-0849(25)02559-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105776</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Imaging</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Case</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Endocarditis Involving Iatrogenic Atrial Septal Defect as a Rare Sequela of Pulmonary Vein Isolation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurata</surname><given-names initials="A">Ayumu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuzoe</surname><given-names initials="H">Hiroki</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>hmatsuzoe@med.kindai.ac.jp</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">c</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">∗</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinugawa</surname><given-names initials="T">Takakazu</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names initials="N">Nobuko</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names initials="S">Sachiyo</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names initials="G">Gaku</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">b</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Yodogawa Christian Hospital, Osaka, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Cardiology, Kindai University Faculty of Medicine, Osaka, Japan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine, Yodogawa Christian Hospital, Osaka, Japan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr Hiroki Matsuzoe, Department of Cardiology, Kindai University Faculty of Medicine, 377-2 Ohno-Higashi, Osakasayama, Osaka 589-8511, Japan. <email>hmatsuzoe@med.kindai.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>30</volume><issue>37</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">504826</issue-id><elocation-id>105776</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-11 10:25:12.723"><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref content-type="ccbyncndlicense" specific-use="textmining" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Infective endocarditis (IE) is an uncommon but serious complication of catheter-based cardiac procedures, particularly when atypical intracardiac sites are involved.</p></sec><sec><title>Case Summary</title><p>A 48-year-old man with atopic dermatitis developed fever, dyspnea, and left knee pain 1 week after pulmonary vein isolation for atrial fibrillation. Blood and synovial fluid cultures revealed methicillin-sensitive <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. Transesophageal echocardiography revealed vegetation at an iatrogenic atrial septal defect (iASD) with shunt flow. Septic arthritis was successfully managed after 6 weeks of intravenous antibiotics. Follow-up imaging revealed improved vegetation and shunt closure.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>This case illustrates the potential for IE to develop at iASDs, particularly in patients with chronic dermatologic conditions that predispose them to bacteremia. iASD involvement highlights the need for close surveillance after ablation.</p></sec><sec><title>Take-Home Messages</title><p>iASDs are possible sites of endocarditis in bacteremia settings. Atopic dermatitis may elevate the risk of <italic toggle="yes">S aureus</italic> bacteremia and postablation IE.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><fig id="undfig1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="ga1.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Key words</title><kwd>atopic dermatitis</kwd><kwd>iatrogenic atrial septal defect</kwd><kwd>infective endocarditis</kwd><kwd>pulmonary vein isolation</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> a<italic toggle="yes">ureus</italic></kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><def-list><title>Abbreviations and Acronyms</title><def-item><term id="kwrd0040">ASD</term><def><p>atrial septal defect</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0050">iASD</term><def><p>iatrogenic atrial septal defect</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0060">IE</term><def><p>infective endocarditis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0070">IL</term><def><p>interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0080">MSSA</term><def><p>methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="kwrd0090">TEE</term><def><p>transesophageal echocardiography</p></def></def-item></def-list></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>History of Presentation</title><p id="p0010">A 48-year-old man presented to the emergency department with a high-grade fever (104 °F), progressive dyspnea, and acute left knee pain occurring 1 week after undergoing catheter ablation for paroxysmal atrial fibrillation. On arrival, the patient was alert and hemodynamically stable, with a blood pressure of 128/84 mm Hg and a heart rate of 117 beats/min. However, signs of a systemic inflammatory response and respiratory compromise were observed, including tachypnea (33 breaths/min) and an oxygen saturation of 99% requiring 10 L/min of supplemental oxygen via a nasal cannula. Cardiac auscultation revealed no murmurs, and pulmonary examination showed clear breath sounds without crackles or wheezing.<boxed-text id="dtbox1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><sec id="dtbox1sec1"><title>Take-Home Messages</title><p id="p0015"><list id="ulist0010" list-type="simple"><list-item id="u0010"><label>•</label><p id="p0020">iASDs are possible sites of endocarditis in the setting of bacteremia.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>•</label><p id="p0025">Atopic dermatitis may elevate the risk of <italic toggle="yes">S aureus</italic> bacteremia and postablation IE.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></boxed-text></p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Past Medical History</title><p id="p0030">The patient had a history of atopic dermatitis since 10 years of age, and atrial fibrillation and sleep apnea diagnosed 4 months before presentation.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p0035">The differential diagnoses included infective endocarditis (IE), septic arthritis, pulmonary embolism (PE), and thrombus at the iatrogenic atrial septal defect (iASD). Transthoracic echocardiography on admission showed no clear vegetation or valve lesions; however, the image quality was poor, possibly because of body habitus. Given purulent joint findings, initial management prioritized septic arthritis. Transesophageal echocardiography (TEE) on day 5 revealed a mobile atrial septal mass. In retrospect, earlier high-quality imaging may have expedited the IE diagnosis.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Investigations</title><p id="p0040">On hospital admission, laboratory investigations revealed leukocytosis (12,300/μL), mild anemia (hemoglobin: 11.7 g/dL), elevated C-reactive protein level (20.9 mg/dL), increased brain natriuretic peptide concentration (172.2 pg/mL), and a D-dimer level of 2.79 μg/mL. These findings suggested a systemic inflammatory response, possible hemodynamic stress, and a prothrombotic state. Supine chest radiography revealed mild pulmonary congestion and cardiomegaly, with a slightly overestimated cardiothoracic ratio in the supine position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). Additionally, 2 sets of blood cultures obtained at the time of admission revealed methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MSSA). On hospitalization day 5, TEE revealed a mobile, isoechogenic mass originating from the atrial septum and protruding into the right atrium, with an associated left-to-right shunt surrounding the structure. This lesion was not observed on TEE performed before pulmonary vein isolation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc1">Videos 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc2">2</xref>). These findings led to an IE diagnosis. The patient's respiratory distress likely reflected mild pulmonary congestion, systemic inflammation, and hemodynamic stress, as suggested by the elevated brain natriuretic peptide level.<fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Spine Chest Radiograph at Admission</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="gr1.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>TEE on Day 5 Shows a Mobile, Isoechogenic Vegetation Measuring 15.6 × 9.8 mm on the Atrial Septum, Protruding Into the Right Atrium (Midesophageal Short-Axis View)</p><p>Ao = aorta; AV = aortic valve; LA = left atrium; PVI = pulmonary vein isolation; RA = right atrium; TEE = transesophageal echocardiography.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="gr2.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Management</title><p id="p0045">The patient was diagnosed with IE, meeting 2 majors and 2 minor criteria of the 2023 European Society of Cardiology Endocarditis Management Guidelines.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1"><sup>1</sup></xref> The vegetation location was highly atypical, and although the differential diagnosis considered intracardiac thrombus, its likelihood was low given the direct oral anticoagulant use after catheter ablation and the absence of stagnant blood flow around the left-to-right shunt. Based on the chief complaint of fever, IE was suspected as the primary diagnosis. Empirical antibiotic therapy using meropenem was initiated. Simultaneously, the patient underwent surgical irrigation and debridement of the left knee for septic arthritis, which resulted in a marked symptomatic improvement. On hospitalization day 3, MSSA was identified in both blood and joint fluid cultures obtained at admission, prompting a switch to cefazolin, which was continued for approximately 6 weeks.</p><p id="p0050">Follow-up TEE performed on hospitalization day 17 showed decreased vegetation size and persisting left-to-right shunt flow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc3">Video 3</xref>). TEE on day 39 confirmed the disappearance of the shunt flow and significant vegetation resolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="mmc4">Video 4</xref>). After confirming good sensitivity to the causative organism and clearance of blood cultures, antibiotics were continued until day 44. On day 45, in anticipation of discharge, the patient's antimicrobial therapy was de-escalated from intravenous cefazolin to oral cephalexin (1,000 mg/d). However, routine laboratory testing on day 46 revealed elevated hepatic transaminase levels, suggesting drug-induced liver injury. Cephalexin was discontinued promptly. By day 48, the liver enzyme levels had improved, and intravenous cefazolin was reinitiated. The patient's subsequent clinical course was uneventful, and the patient was discharged in a stable condition on day 56.<fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Follow-Up TEE On Day 17 (Midesophageal Short-Axis View) Shows a Smaller Atrial Septal Vegetation (10.5 × 5.1 mm) With Persistent Left-to-Right Shunt</p><p>Abbreviations as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="gr3.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Follow-Up</title><p id="p0055">After discharge, follow-up blood tests showed that the C-reactive protein level had returned to the normal range and there was no significant increase in inflammatory response. Additionally, the electrocardiogram maintained a sinus rhythm, and transthoracic echocardiography did not indicate shunt flow or abnormal structures in the atrial septum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>).<fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Follow-Up TTE (RV-Focused Apical 4-Chamber and Subcostal Views) Shows No Significant Vegetation</p><p>LV = left ventricle; RV = right ventricle; other abbreviations as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="gr4.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0060">IE typically develops when bacteremia coincides with endocardial injury. In heart disease, shear stress from turbulent flow distal to a stenosis or near a high-velocity jet can damage the endothelium and trigger IE.</p><p id="p0065">The damaged endothelial surface is coated with platelets and fibrin, creating a substrate for bacterial adherence during transient bacteremia episodes. Subsequently, these bacteria become embedded in a fibrin-platelet matrix, forming vegetation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2"><sup>2</sup></xref> Thus, in the presence of structural heart disease, particularly significant valvular pathology, even low-virulence bacteria may cause IE. Conversely, in patients without such abnormalities, the risk of IE from low-virulence organisms is considered low because of the absence of predisposing endothelial damage.</p><p id="p0070">However, <italic toggle="yes">S aureus</italic> possesses distinct pathogenic mechanisms enabling it to cause IE, even in structurally normal hearts. A key virulence factor is coagulase, an extracellular enzyme that activates a thrombin-like substance in host plasma, converting fibrinogen into fibrin and promoting localized coagulation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3"><sup>3</sup></xref> Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">S aureus</italic> expresses various surface adhesion molecules, collectively referred to as microbial surface components recognizing adhesive matrix molecules, which bind extracellular matrix proteins such as fibronectin and fibrinogen. This interaction promotes platelet aggregation and enhances bacterial adhesion to endothelial surfaces, thereby contributing to infection initiation. In addition to adhesion, <italic toggle="yes">S aureus</italic> can invade host endothelial cells via integrin α5β1-mediated endocytosis, enabling immune evasion and persistent infection.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4"><sup>4</sup></xref> These mechanisms collectively enable <italic toggle="yes">S aureus</italic> to cause IE regardless of the underlying structural heart disease, with reports describing its adherence to atypical sites for endocarditis to initiate infection.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref> Although differential diagnoses such as PE and intracardiac thrombus were considered, none explained the full constellation of systemic inflammation, MSSA bacteremia, and mobile atrial septal mass in the present case. IE was ultimately favored based on the clinical, microbiological, and imaging findings. PE was considered unlikely due to the absence of unilateral symptoms, right ventricular dysfunction, or other supportive evidence. MSSA bacteremia and TEE-confirmed vegetation supported the diagnosis.</p><p id="p0075">In the present case, transseptal puncture was performed during catheter ablation, resulting in an iASD. Although causality is unproven, the early onset of IE postablation suggests that endothelial injury from transseptal puncture may have played a primary role. Turbulent shunt flow across the iASD may have augmented shear stress, promoting bacterial adherence. However, this remains hypothetical and warrants further investigation.</p><p id="p0080">Chronic atrial fibrillation and cardiomegaly may indicate elevated left atrial pressure, increasing iASD shunt velocity and turbulence to promote endothelial injury and bacterial adherence. Given their small size, iASDs may be especially susceptible, making left atrial pressure a modifiable risk factor for IE.</p><p id="p0085">Among congenital cardiac anomalies, atrial septal defects (ASDs) are generally considered to pose a minimal risk of IE because of their low shunt velocities. For instance, Li and Somerville<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8"><sup>8</sup></xref> followed 500 patients with congenital heart disease for 18 years and reported no cases of IE in those with ASD before or after surgical correction. Isolated reports of IE in patients with ASD typically involve concurrent bacteremia or other risk factors. Thus, IE risk likely arises not from the shunt itself, but rather from endothelial injury combined with transient bacteremia under specific conditions.</p><p id="p0090">In addition, IE has been reported with atrial septal occluder devices, where prosthetic material serves as a nidus for infection.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9"><sup>9</sup></xref> Although no device was used, the iASD created by transseptal puncture may pose a similar risk via turbulent flow and endothelial injury. Unlike congenital ASDs or closures, iASDs are rarely recognized as infection sites. To our knowledge, IE at an iASD after pulmonary vein isolation has not been previously reported.</p><p id="p0095">Additionally, the patient's history of atopic dermatitis may have contributed to the <italic toggle="yes">S aureus</italic> infection. Normally, antimicrobial peptides, such as β-defensin and cathelicidin, provide innate skin defense. However, in atopic dermatitis, the overproduction of cytokines such as interleukin (IL)-4, IL-10, and IL-13 suppresses antimicrobial peptide synthesis, thereby weakening the skin barrier.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10"><sup>10</sup></xref> Although the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">S aureus</italic> colonization in healthy skin ranges from 2% to 25%, it exceeds 90% in patients with atopic dermatitis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10"><sup>10</sup></xref> Although this single case report has limited generalizability and cannot establish causality, it raises concern that iASD may serve as a rare nidus for infection, particularly in patients with dermatologic conditions like atopic dermatitis, which may predispose them to <italic toggle="yes">S aureus</italic> bacteremia. This association remains speculative and warrants further investigation. Enhanced vigilance is advised postablation when systemic symptoms occur.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0100">This case highlights the potential for IE to occur at iASDs after catheter ablation, especially in patients with atopic dermatitis. The findings emphasize the importance of recognizing dermatologic conditions as potential risk factors for postprocedural bacteremia and IE. This report adds to the limited data on iASD-related IE and suggests a need for heightened clinical vigilance. Further studies are required to guide risk stratification and preventive strategies in susceptible patients.</p></sec><sec id="coi0010" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Funding Support and Author Disclosures</title><p id="p0105">The authors have reported that they have no relationships relevant to the contents of this paper to disclose.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation id="sref1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajmone Marsan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Waha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2023 ESC guidelines for the management of endocarditis</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><volume>44</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>3948</fpage><lpage>4042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37622656</pub-id><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehad193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation id="sref2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sastry</surname><given-names>B.K.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infective endocarditis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>404</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39067905</pub-id><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01098-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation id="sref3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gohdes</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of coagulase-reacting factor in the activation of fibrinogen</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>78</volume><year>1959</year><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14425436</pub-id><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.78.3.450-451.1959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC290564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation id="sref4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eichenberger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>V.G.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infections: epidemiology, pathophysiology, clinical manifestations, and management</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><volume>28</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26016486</pub-id><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00134-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4451395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation id="sref5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Speziale</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pietrocola</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rindi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural and functional role of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> surface components recognizing adhesive matrix molecules of the host</article-title><source>Future Microbiol</source><volume>4</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>1337</fpage><lpage>1352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995192</pub-id><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb.09.102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation id="sref6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuzoe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishio</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takaishi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Right ventricular mural infective endocarditis after traumatic tricuspid valve regurgitation in a 40-year-old man: a case report</article-title><source>J Cardiol Cases</source><volume>27</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36788950</pub-id><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jccase.2022.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9911922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation id="sref7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz-Navarro</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerkhof</surname><given-names>P.L.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Case report on right ventricular mural endocarditis, not diagnosed clinically, but histopathologically after cardiac surgery</article-title><source>Eur Heart J Case Rep</source><volume>6</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ytac376</object-id><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ehjcr/ytac376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9518669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36187935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation id="sref8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infective endocarditis in the grown-up congenital heart (GUCH) population</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><volume>19</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9503191</pub-id><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/euhj.1997.0821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation id="sref9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahadin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infective endocarditis on an atrial septal defect closure device: a rare occurrence</article-title><source>Pediatr Cardiol</source><volume>44</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1187</fpage><lpage>1189</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation id="sref10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bieber</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>358</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1483</fpage><lpage>1494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18385500</pub-id><pub-id assigning-authority="pmc" pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra074081</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1"><title>Appendix</title><p id="p0110">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><title>Video 1</title><p>Transesophageal Echocardiography Before Pulmonary Vein Isolation</p></caption><media orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="mmc1.mp4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><title>Video 2</title><p>Transesophageal Echocardiography Performed on Hospitalization Day 5</p></caption><media orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="mmc2.mp4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><title>Video 3</title><p>Transesophageal Echocardiography Performed on Hospitalization Day 17</p></caption><media orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="mmc3.mp4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><title>Video 4</title><p>Transesophageal Echocardiography Performed on Hospitalization Day 39</p></caption><media orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="mmc4.mp4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="d36e51"><p id="ntpara0015aa">The authors attest they are in compliance with human studies committees and animal welfare regulations of the authors’ institutions and Food and Drug Administration guidelines, including patient consent where appropriate. For more information, visit the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" id="interref1" xlink:href="https://www.jacc.org/author-center" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Author Center</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="appsec2"><p>Appendix</p><p id="p0115">For supplemental videos, please see the online version of this paper.<table-wrap id="tbl1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Visual Summary</label><caption><p>From Pulmonary Vein Isolation to Iatrogenic ASD Endocarditis: A Timeline Summary</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinical Event</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Catheter ablation performed for paroxysmal atrial fibrillation.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Presented with fever (40 °C), dyspnea, and acute left knee pain. MSSA identified in blood cultures.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Empirical meropenem initiated. Surgical irrigation and debridement of left knee.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MSSA confirmed in both blood and joint fluid cultures. Switched to cefazolin.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TEE revealed mobile vegetation at iASD with left-to-right shunt.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow-up TEE: vegetation size reduced; shunt flow persisted.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TEE: shunt flow disappeared; vegetation resolved.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Completion of intravenous cefazolin.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">De-escalated to oral cephalexin.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liver enzymes elevated; cephalexin discontinued.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liver function improved; cefazolin reinitiated.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Discharged in stable condition.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow-up</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CRP normalized; TTE showed no shunt or residual abnormalities.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CRP = C-reactive protein; iASD = iatrogenic atrial septal defect; MSSA = methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>; TEE = transesophageal echocardiography; TTE = transthoracic echocardiography.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></fn></fn-group></back></article>